the following is a conversation with the
leap george
a researcher at the intersection of
neuroscience and artificial intelligence
co-founder of vicarius with scott
phoenix
and formerly co-founder of numenta with
jeff hawkins
who's been on this podcast and donna
dubinsky
from his early work on hierarchical
temporal memory to recursive cortical
networks
to today the leaps always sought to
engineer intelligence
that is closely inspired by the human
brain
as a side note i think we understand
very little about the fundamental
principles
underlying the function of the human
brain but the little we do know
gives hints that may be more useful for
engineering intelligence than any
idea in mathematics computer science
physics and
scientific fields outside of biology and
so the brain is a kind of existence
proof that says
it's possible keep at it i should also
say that brain-inspired ai
is often over-hyped and used as fodder
just as
quantum computing for uh marketing speak
but i'm not afraid of exploring these
sometimes over-hyped areas since
where there's smoke there's sometimes
fire
quick summary of the ads three sponsors
babel
raycon earbuds and masterclass please
consider supporting this podcast by
clicking the special links
in the description to get the discount
it really is the best way to support
this podcast
if you enjoy this thing subscribe on
youtube review 5 stars on apple podcast
support on patreon i'll connect with me
on twitter at lex friedman
as usual i'll do a few minutes of ads
now and never any ads in the middle that
can break the flow of the conversation
this show is sponsored by babel an app
and website that gets you speaking in a
new language within weeks
go to babel.com and use codelex to get
three months free
they offer 14 languages including
spanish french
italian german and yes russian
daily lessons are 10 to 15 minutes super
easy effective
designed by over 100 language experts
let me read a few lines from the russian
poem
by alexander block that you'll start to
understand if you sign up to babel
now i say that you'll only start to
understand this poem
because russian starts with the language
and ends with the vodka
now the latter part is definitely not
endorsed or provided by babble
and will probably lose me the
sponsorship but once you graduate from
babel
you can enroll my advanced course of
late night russian conversation over
vodka
i have not yet developed an app for that
it's in progress
so get started by visiting babel.com and
use code lex
to get three months free this show
is sponsored by raycon earbuds get them
at byraycon.com
flex they become my main method of
listening to podcasts audiobooks and
music
when i run do push-ups and pull-ups or
just
living life in fact i often listen to
brown noise with them
when i'm thinking deeply about something
it helps me focus
they're super comfortable pair easily
great sound
great bass six hours of play time
i've been putting in a lot of miles to
get ready for a potential ultra marathon
and listening to audio books on world
war ii
the sound is rich and really comes in
clear so again get them
at byraycon.com lex
this show is sponsored by masterclass
sign up at masterclass.com
lex to get a discount and to support
this podcast
when i first heard about class i thought
it was too good to be true
i still think it's too good to be true
for 180 bucks a year you get an
all-access pass to watch courses from
to list some of my favorites chris
hadfield on space exploration
neil degrasse tyson on scientific
thinking and communication
will wright creator of some city and
sims like game design
every time i do this read i really want
to play
a city builder game carlos santana on
guitar
caspar daniel negrano on poker and many
more
chris hadfield explaining how rockets
work and the experience of being
launched into space alone
is worth the money by the way you can
watch it on basically any device
once again sign up at masterclass.com to
get a discount and to support this
podcast
and now here's my conversation with the
leap
george do you think we need to
understand the brain
in order to build it yes if you want to
build the brain
we definitely need to understand how it
works so
blue brain or henry markham's project
is trying to build a brain without
understanding it like just trying to
uh put details of the brain
from neuroscience experiments into a
giant simulation
by putting more and more neurons more
and more details but that
is not going to work because
when it doesn't perform as uh what you
expect
it to do then what do you do you do you
just keep adding more details
how do you debug it so it's a so unless
you
understand unless you have a theory
about how the system is supposed to work
how the pieces are supposed to fit
together what they're going to
contribute
you can't you can't build it at the
functional level understand
so can you actually linger on and
describe the blue brain project
it's kind of fascinating uh
principle an idea to try to simulate the
brain
as we're talking about the human brain
right right human brains
and rad brains or cat brains
have lots in common that the cortex the
neocortex structure
is very similar so initially they were
trying to
just simulate a cat brain uh and uh
to understand the nature of evil they
understand the nature of evil
or uh as it happens in most of these
simulations
uh you you easily get one thing out
which is oscillations you know yeah if
you
if you simulate a large number of
neurons they
oscillate and you can adjust the
parameters and say that oh selections
match the
rhythm that we see in the brain etc but
uh oh i see so like uh so the idea is
uh is the simulation at the level of uh
individual neurons
yeah so the blue brain project the
original
idea as proposed was um you
you put very detailed bio physical
neurons
uh bios physical models of neurons
and you interconnect them according to
the
statistics of connections that we have
found from real neuroscience experiments
and then uh turn it on and uh see what
happens
uh and and these neural models are you
know incredibly
complicated in themselves right because
these neurons
are modeled using uh this
idea called hodgkin-huxley models which
are about
how signals propagate in a cable and
there are
active dendrites all those phenomena
which
those phenomena themselves we don't
understand that well uh and then
uh we put in connectivity which is part
guess work
part you know observed and of course if
you do not have any theory about how it
is
supposed to work uh we
you know we just have to take whatever
comes out of it as
okay this is something interesting but
in your sense like these models of the
way signal travels
along or like with the axons and all the
basic models
that's they're too crude oh well
actually
they are pretty detailed and pretty
sophisticated
and they do replicate the
neural dynamics if you take a single
neuron
and you you try to uh
turn on the different channels the
calcium channels and
uh the different receptors uh and see
what the effect
of uh turning on or off those channels
are
in the neurons spike output people have
built pretty sophisticated models of
that and
and they are i i would say um
you know in the regime of correct well
see the correctness
that's interesting because you've
mentioned in several levels uh
the correctness is measured by looking
at some kind of aggregate statistics
it would be more of the the spiking
dynamics
in dynamics yeah and and yeah these
models
because they are they are going to the
level of mechanism right so they are
basically looking at uh okay what what
is the effect of
turning on an ion channel uh and um
and you can you can model that using
electric circuits in
and then so they are model so it is not
just
a uh function fitting it is people are
looking at the mechanism underlying it
and uh putting that in terms of electric
circuit
theory signal propagation theory and and
modeling that and
so those models are sophisticated but
getting a
single neurons model 99
right does not still tell you how to
you know it would be the analog of
getting a transistor
model right and now trying to build a
microprocessor
um and if you if you just uh observe you
know if you did not understand how a
microprocessor works
uh but you say oh i have i now can model
one transistor well
and now i will just try to interconnect
uh the transistors
according to whatever i could you know
guess from the experiments and try to
simulate it
um then it is very unlikely that you
will
produce a functioning microprocessor um
you want to you know when you want to
uh produce a functioning microprocessor
you want to understand boolean logic
how does how do the the gates work all
those things
and then you know understand how do
those gates get implemented using
transistors
yeah there's actually i remember this
reminds me this is a paper
maybe you're familiar with it i remember
going through in a reading group
that approaches a microprocessor from a
perspective a neuroscientist
i think it it basically it uses all the
tools that we have of neuroscience to
try to understand like as if we just
aliens showed up to study computers uh
yeah and and to see if if those tools
could be used to get
any kind of sense of how the
microprocessor works
i think the final the takeaway from
the at least this initials uh
exploration is that
we're screwed there's no way that the
tools of neuroscience would be able to
get us
to anything like not even boolean logic
i mean it's
just a any aspect
of the architecture of the uh
function of the processes involved
uh the the clocks the the timing all
that you can't figure that out from the
tools of neuroscience
yes i'm very familiar with this this
particular paper
i think it was uh called um can
uh a neuroscientist understand a
microprocessor
yeah something like that following the
methodology
in that paper even an electrical
engineer would not understand
microprocessors so i could
so i could so i i don't think it is
that bad in the sense of saying um
neuroscientists do
find valuable things uh by observing the
brain
they they do find good insights um
but those insight cannot be put together
just as a simulation you have to you
have to investigate
what are the computational underpinnings
pinnings of
those findings how do all of them
fit together from an information
processing
perspective you have to you have to
somebody has to
uh painstakingly put those things
together and build hypothesis um
so i don't want to this all of
neuroscience is saying oh they are not
finding anything no that
you know that that paper almost went to
that level of uh uh
neuroscientists will never understand uh
no that that's not true i think they do
find lots of useful things
but it has to be put together in a
computational framework
yeah i mean but you know just the ai
systems will be listening to this
podcast a hundred years from now
and it will probably there's some
nonzero probability they'll find your
words laughable
it's like i remember humans thought they
understood
something about the brain they're
totally clueless there's a sense about
neuroscience that we may be in the very
very early days of understanding
uh the brain but i mean that's one
perspective
in your perspective
how far are we into understanding
uh any aspect of the brain
so the the the dynamics of the
individual neuron communication
to the how when they in in a collective
sense how they're able to store
information transfer information
how the intelligence then emerges all
that kind of stuff where are we on that
timeline
yeah so you know timelines are very very
hard to predict
and you can of course be wrong uh and it
can be wrong in
on either side uh you know we know that
uh now when we look back uh the first
flight
was in 1903. uh in 1900
there was a new york times article on
flying machines that
do not fly and and you know humans might
not fly for another hundred years
that was what that article uh stated and
uh so
but no they they flew three years after
that so it is you know it's very hard to
um so well and on that point one of the
wright brothers
uh i think two years before
uh said that uh like he said like some
number like 50 years
he he has become convinced that it's
it's uh it's impossible
even during their experimentation yeah
yeah yeah i mean that's a tribute to
when
that's like the entrepreneurial battle
of like depression of
going through just like thinking this is
impossible
right but there yeah there's something
even the person that's in it
is not able to see uh estimate correctly
exactly but i can i can tell from the
point of you know objectively what are
the things that we
know about the brain and how that can be
used to build
ai models which can then go back and
inform
how the brain works so my way of
understanding the brain would be to
basically say
look at the insights neuroscientists
have found
understand that from a computational
angle information processing angle build
models using that
and then building the that model which
which
functions which is a functional model
which is which is doing the task
that we want the model to do it is not
just trying to model a phenomena in the
brain it is it is trying to
do what the brain is trying to do on on
the whole
functional level and building that model
will help you
fill in the missing pieces that you know
biology just gives you the hints
and building the model you know fills in
the
rest of the the pieces of the puzzle and
then you can go and
connect that back to biology and say
okay now it makes sense that this part
of
the brain is uh doing this or
this layer in the cortical circuit is
doing this uh
and and and then continue this
iteratively
because now that will inform new
experiments in neuroscience
and of course you know building the
model and verifying that in the real
world
will you will also tell you more about
does the model actually work
uh and you can refine the model find
better ways of putting these
neuroscience insights together
so so i would say it is it is you know
it
so neuroscientists alone just from
experimentation
will not be able to build a model of the
of the brain uh or a functional model of
the brain
so we you know there there's uh lots of
efforts which are very impressive
efforts in
collecting more and more connectivity
data
from the brain yeah you know how how are
the micro circuits of the brain
connected with each other those are
beautiful by the way those are beautiful
uh and at the same time those
those do not itself um by themselves
convey the story of how does it work
yeah uh and
and somebody has to understand okay why
are they connected like that
and what what are those things doing uh
and
and we do that by building models in ai
using hints from neuroscience
and and repeat the cycle so what
aspect of the brain are useful in this
whole
endeavor which by the way i should say
you're you're both the neuroscientists
and
and ai person i guess the dream is to
both understand the brain and to build
agi systems
so you're it's like an engineer's
perspective of trying to understand the
brain so what aspects of the brain
uh functioning speaking like you said
you find interesting
yeah quite a lot of things all right so
one is
um you know if you look at the visual
cortex
um uh and and you know the visual cortex
is
is a large part of the brain uh i forget
this exact fraction but it is
it's a it's a huge part of our brain
area is uh
occupied by just just vision um so
vision
visual cortex is not just a feed-forward
cascade of neurons
um uh there are a lot more feedback
connections in the brain
compared to the feed-forward connections
and and
it is surprising to the level of detail
neuroscientists have actually studied
this
if you if you go into neuroscience
literature and poke around and ask you
know
have they studied what will be the
effect of poking a neuron
in level i.t uh in
level v one and uh um have they studied
that uh
and you will say yes they have studied
that so
every every possible combination i mean
it's it's a it's not a random
exploration at all it's very hypothesis
driven right
they are very uh experimental
neuroscientists are very very systematic
in how they probe the brain uh because
experiments are
very costly to conduct they take a lot
of preparation they
they need a lot of control so they they
are very hypothesis driven in how they
probe the brain
and um often what i find is that when we
have a question
in um in ai uh about
have has anybody probably probed how
lateral connections in the brain works
and when you go and read the literature
yes people have probed it and people
have probed it very systematically
and and they have hypothesis about how
those lateral connections are supposedly
contributing
to visual processing uh but of course
they haven't built
very very functional detail models of it
by the way how do
you know studies start to interrupt that
do they do they stimulate like a neuron
in one particular area of the visual
cortex
and then see how the travel of the
signal travels kind of thing
fascinating very very fascinating
experiments right you know so i can i
can give you one example i was impressed
with um this is
uh so before going to that let me like
let me give you a a you know a
overview of how the the layers in the
cortex are organized
right uh visual cortex is organized into
roughly four hierarchical levels
okay so uh v one v two v four i t
and in v one of v three uh well yeah
there's another pathway okay
okay so there's this this is this i'm
talking about just the object
recognition pathway right
okay and then um in v1 itself
um so it's there is a very detailed
micro circuit in v1 itself there is
there is organization within a level
itself
uh the cortical sheet is organized into
uh you know multiple layers and there
are columnar structure
and and this this layer wise and column
structure is repeated in v1 v2 v4
uh it all of them right and and
the connections between these layers
within a level
with you know in v1 itself there are six
layers roughly
and the connections between them there
is a particular structure to them
uh and um now so one example
of an experiment uh uh people did
is when i when you present a stimulus
uh which is um let's say requires
um separating the foreground from the
background of an object so it is
it's a textured triangle on a textured
background
and you can check
does the surface settle first or does
the contour settle first
cerro settle in the sense that the so
when you find finally form the percept
of the
of the triangle you understand where the
contours of the triangle are
and you also know where the inside of
the triangle is right that's when you
form the final percept
uh now you can ask what is the dynamics
of forming that final percept
um do the do the
neurons um first find the edges
and converge on where the edges are and
then
they find the inner surfaces or does it
go the other way the other way around um
so so what's the answer uh in this case
it it turns out that
it first settles on the edges it it
converges on the edge hypothesis first
and then the the surfaces are filled in
from the edges to the inside that's
fascinating uh and
and the detail to which you can study
this it's it's amazing that you can
actually
not only find um the temporal dynamics
of
when this happens uh and then you can
also find
which layer in the you know in v1 which
layer is encoding
uh the edges which layer is encoding the
surfaces
and which layer is encoding the feedback
which there is encoding the feed forward
and what what's the
combination of them that produces the
final person um
and these kinds of experiments stand out
when
you try to explain illusions uh one one
example of a favorite illusion of mine
is the kanetsa triangle i don't know
that you are familiar with this one
so this is um uh this is an example
where
it's a triangle uh but you know the
corners of the only the corners of the
triangle are shown in the stimuli
the stimulus so they look like kind of
pac-man
oh the black pac-man exactly yeah and
then you start to see
your visual system hallucinates the
edges yeah
um and you can you know you when you
look at it you will see a faint edge
right and you can go inside the brain
and look you know do actually neurons
signal the presence of this edge and
and if this signal how do they do it
because they are not
receiving anything from the input in the
the input is black
for those neurons right uh so how do
they signal it
when does the signaling happen you know
does it you know so
so if a real contour is present in the
input then
the signa the neurons immediately signal
okay there is a there is an edge here
when when it is an illusory edge um it
is clearly not in the input
it is coming from the context so those
neurons fire later
and and you can say that okay these are
it's the feedback connections that is
causing them to fire
uh and and they happen later
and you can find the dynamics of them so
so these studies are pretty impressive
and and very detailed
so by the way just uh just take a step
back you said uh that there may be more
feedback connections and feed forward
connections yeah
uh first of all it's just just for like
a machine learning
folks yeah i mean that for that's crazy
that there's
all these feedback connections i mean we
often
think about i think
thanks to deep learning you start to
think about
um the human brain as a kind of feed
forward mechanism
right so what the heck are these
feedback connections yeah what's their
what's the dynamics well what are we
supposed to think about them yeah so
this is
this fits into a very beautiful picture
about how the brain works
right um so the the beautiful picture of
how the brain works is that
our brain is building a model of the
world
uh i know so our visual system is
building a model of how
objects behave in the world and and we
are constantly projecting that model
back onto the world
so what we are seeing is not just a feed
forward
thing that just gets interpreted in in a
few word party we are
constantly projecting our expectations
onto the world and
and what the final percept is a
combination of
what we project onto the world uh
combined with what the actual sensory
input is
almost like trying to calculate the
difference and then trying to interpret
the difference
yeah it's it's um i wouldn't put just
calculating the difference it's more
like
what is the best explanation for the
input stimulus
based on the model of the world i have
got it got it and that's where all the
illusions come in and that's but that's
that's an incredibly efficient
so uh efficient process so the feedback
mechanism it just
helps you constantly uh yeah
so hallucinate how the world should be
based on your world model and then just
looking at uh if there's
novelty uh like trying to explain it
like that
hence that's why movement we detect
movement really well there's all these
kinds of things
and that this is like at all different
levels
of the cortex you're saying this happens
at the lowest level or the highest level
yes yeah in fact feedback connections
are more prevalent
in everywhere in the cortex and and um
so one way to think about it and there's
a lot of evidence for this
is inference um so you know so basically
if you have a model of the world and
when when
some evidence comes in what you are
doing is inference
right you are trying to now explain this
evidence using your model of the world
yep and this inference
includes projecting your model onto the
evidence
and taking the evidence back into the
model
and and doing an iterative procedure
and this iterative procedure is what
happens
using the feed forward feedback
propagation and
feedback affects what you see in the
world and you know it also affects feed
forward propagation
and examples are everywhere we we see
these kinds of things everywhere the
idea that
there can be multiple competing
hypotheses
in our model trying to explain the same
evidence
and then you have to kind of make them
compete
and one hypothesis will explain away
the other hypothesis through this
competition process
wait what so you have competing
models of the world that tried to
explain what do you mean by explain away
so this is a classic example in uh uh
graphical models probabilistic models um
so if you what are those um okay
um i think it's useful to mention
because we'll talk about them more
yeah yeah so neural networks
are one class of machine learning models
um
you know you have distributed set of
nodes which are called the neurons
you know each one is doing a dot product
and you can you can approximate any
function using this
a multi-level network of neurons so
that's
a class of models which are used for
useful for function approximation
there is another class of models in
machine learning
called probabilistic graphical models
and
you can think of them as each node in
that
model is variable which is which is
talking about something you know
it can be a variable representing is is
an edge
present in the input or not and at the
top of the uh network a
node can be uh representing is there an
object present in the
world or not and and then so it can it
is
it is another way of encoding knowledge
and uh
um and then you once you encode the
knowledge
you can uh do inference
in the right way you know how what is
the best way to uh
you know explain some sort of evidence
using this model that you encoded you
know so when you encode the model
you are encoding the relationship
between these different variables how is
the edge
connected to my the model of the object
how is the surface connected to the
model of the object
and then of course this is a very
distributed complicated model
and inference is how do you
explain a piece of evidence when a set
of stimulus comes in if somebody tells
me
there is a 50 probability that there is
an edge here in this part of the model
how does that affect my belief on
whether
i should think that there should be is
the square present in the image
so so this is the process of inference
so
one example of inference is having this
experience of effect between
multiple causes so uh graphical models
can be
used to represent causality in the world
um
so let's say um you know uh your
uh alarm at home
can be uh triggered by a
burglar getting into your house uh or it
can be triggered by
an earthquake both both can be causes of
the alarm going off
so now you you're right you know you're
in your office you heard
burglar alarm going off you are heading
uh home
thinking that there's a burglar got it
but while driving home
if you hear on the radio that there was
an earthquake in the vicinity
now your hype you know uh strength of
evidence for
a burglar getting into their house is
diminished
because now that that piece of evidence
is explained by
the earthquake being present so if you
if you think about these two causes
explaining at lower level
uh variable which is alarm now what we
are seeing is that
increasing the evidence for some cause
ex
you know there is evidence coming in
from below for alarm being present
and initially it was flowing to a
burglar
being present but now since somebody
some this
there the side evidence for this other
cause it explains away this evidence and
it evidence will now flow to the other
course
this is you know two competing causal uh
things
trying to explain the same evidence and
the brain has a similar kind of
mechanism
for doing so that's kind of interesting
and that
how's that all encoded in the brain like
where's the storage of information are
we talking
just maybe to get it a little bit more
specific
is it in the hardware of the actual
connections is it
in uh chemical communication is it
electrical communication
do we do we know so this is you know a
paper that we are bringing out
soon which one this is the cortical
micro circuits paper that
i sent you a draft of of course this is
uh a lot of it is still hypothesis one
hypothesis is that
a you can think of a cortical column as
encoding a
a concept a concept you know think of it
as say
an example of a concept is um is an edge
present or not
or is is an object present or not okay
so it can you can think of it as a
binary variable a binary random variable
the presence of an edge or not or the
presence of an object or not
so each cortical column can be thought
of as representing
that one concept one variable and then
the connections between these cortical
columns are basically encoding
the relationship between these random
variables and
then there are connections within the
cortical column there are
each cortical column is implemented
using multiple layers of neurons
with very very very rich um
structure there you know there are
thousands of neurons in a cortical
column
but but that structure is similar across
the different cortical columns
yeah correct and also these cortical
columns collect connect to a
substructure called thalamus
in the uh you know so all all cortical
columns
pass through this substructure so our
hypothesis
is that yeah the connections between the
cortical columns
implement this uh you know that's where
the knowledge is stored
about you know how these different
connects concepts connect to each other
and then the the neurons inside this
cortical column and in thalamus in
combination
implement this uh actual computations
needed for
inference which includes explaining a
way and competing between the different
uh hypotheses um and it is all very
so what is amazing is that uh
neuroscientists have
actually done experiments to the tune of
showing these things they might not be
putting it in the overall
inference framework but they will show
things like
if i poke this higher level neuron it
will inhibit
through this complicated loop through
the thalamus it will inhibit this other
column
uh so they will do such experiments but
do they use
terminology of concepts for example so
so
you're i mean is it uh
is it something where it's easy to
anthropomorphize
and think about concepts like you start
moving into
logic based kind of reasoning systems so
um i would just think of concepts in
that kind of way
or is it is it a lot messier
a lot more gray area you know
even even more gray even more messy than
the artificial neural network kinds of
abstractions
the easiest way to think of it as a
variable right it's a binary variable
which is showing the presence or absence
of
something so but i guess what i'm asking
is
is that something that we're supposed to
think of something that's human
interpretable
of that something it doesn't need to be
it doesn't need to be human
interpretable there's no need for it to
be human interpretable uh
but it's it's almost like um
you you will be able to find some
interpretation of it
uh because it is connected to the other
things yes that you know
and the the point is it's useful somehow
yeah
it's useful as an entity
in the graph that in connecting to the
other entities that are
let's call them concepts right okay so
uh by the way what's
are these the cortical micro circuits
correct these are the cortical micro
circuits
you know that's what neuroscientists use
to talk about
the circuits in in uh within a level of
the cortex
so you can think of you know let's think
of a neural
network in artificial neural network
terms you know people talk about the
architecture of the you know so
how many how many layers they build uh
you know what is the fan
in fan out etc that is the macro
architecture
so and then within a layer of the
neural network you can you know the
cortical
neural network is much more structured
with you know within a level there's a
lot more intricate
structure there uh but even um even
within an artificial neural network you
can think of
in feature detection plus pooling as one
one level
and so that is kind of a micro circuit
uh it's much more
uh complex in the real brain uh and
and so within a level whatever is that
circuitry within a column
of the cortex and between the layers of
the cortex that's the micro circuitry
i love that terminology uh machine
learning people don't use
the circuit terminology right but they
should it's a nice so okay
uh okay so that's uh that that's the
the cortical micro circuit so what's
interesting about
what can we say what is the paper that
you're working on
propose about the ideas around these
cortical micro circuits
so this is a fully functional
model for the micro circuits of the
visual cortex
so the the paper focuses and your idea
in our discussions now is focusing on
vision yeah the uh visual cortex
okay yeah this is a model this is a full
model it says this is how vision works
but this is this is a model of science
yeah hypothesis okay so let me let me
step back
a bit um so we looked at neuroscience
for insights on how to build a vision
model
right and and and we synthesized all
those insights into a
computational model this is called the
recursive vertical network model
that we we used for breaking captchas
and and we are using the same model for
robotic picking
and uh tracking of objects and that
again is the vision system
that's the best computer vision system
that's the computer mission
takes in images and outputs what
on one side it outputs the class of the
image
and also segments the image uh
and you can also ask it further queries
where is the edge of the object where is
the interior of the object
so so it's a model that you build to
answer multiple questions
so you are not trying to build a model
for just classification
or just segmentation etc so it's a it's
a it's a joint model that can do
multiple things um and um so
so that's the model that we built using
insights from
neuroscience and some of those insights
are what is the role of feedback
connections
what is the role of lateral connections
uh so all those things went into the
model the model
actually uses feedback connections all
these ideas from you know from your
science
yeah so what what what the heck is a
recursive cortical network like what
what are the architecture approaches
interesting aspects here
which is essentially a brain inspired
approach
to computer vision yeah so there are
multiple layers to this question
i can go from the very very top and then
zoom in okay
so one important thing constraint that
went into the model is that
you should not think vision think of
vision
as something in isolation we should not
think perception
as something as a preprocessor for
cognition
perception and cognition are
interconnected and so you should not
think of
one problem in separation from the other
problem um and
so that means if you finally want to
have a system that understand
concepts uh about the world and can
learn in a very conceptual model of the
world
and can reason and connect to language
all of those things
you need to you need to have think all
the way through and
make sure that your perception system is
compatible with
your cognition system and language
system and all of them and one
aspect of that is top-down
controllability
um what does that mean so that means you
know so
so think of it you know you can close
your eyes and
think about the details of one object
right i can i can
zoom in further and further i can you
know so so think of the bottle in front
of me
right and and now you can think about
okay what the cap of that bottle looks
uh i know we can think about what's the
texture on that bottle
of the of the cap you know you can think
about
you know what will happen if uh
something hits that
uh so you can you can you can manipulate
your visual knowledge in uh
cognition driven ways yes uh and so
this top-down controllability uh and
being able to
simulate scenarios in the world so
you're not just a passive uh
player in this perception game you you
can you can control it you gotta you
you have imagination correct so so
so basically you know basically having a
generating network
yeah which is a model and and it is not
just some
arbitrary generated network it has to be
it has to be built in a way that it is
controllable top-down
it is it is not just trying to generate
a whole picture
at once uh you know it's not trying to
generate photorealistic things of the
world you
you know you don't have good
photorealistic models of the world human
brains do not have if i
if i for example ask you the question uh
what is the color of the letter
e in the google logo
you have no idea right now yeah although
you have seen it millions of times
hundreds of times so yeah so it's not
our model is not photorealistic
but but it is but it has other
properties that we can manipulate it
uh in the uh and you can think about
filling in a different color in that
logo
you can think about expanding the the
letter e yeah
you know you can see what in so you can
imagine the consequence of
you know actions that you have never
performed so so these are the
kind of characteristics the genetic
model need to have so this is one
constraint that went into our model like
you know so this is
when you read the just the perception
side of the paper it is not obvious that
this was a constraint
into the inter that went into the model
this top-down controllability
of the generating model uh so what what
does the top-down controllability
in a model look like
it's a really interesting concept
fascinating concept what is that is that
the recursive
recursiveness gives you that or how do
you how do you do it um
quite a few things it's like what what
does the model factor
or factorize you know what are the what
is the model representing us different
pieces
in the puzzle like you know so so in the
rcn
uh network it it thinks of the world you
know
what i say the background of an image
is modeled separately from the
foreground of the image
so the objects are separate from the
background they're different entities
so there's a kind of segmentation that's
built in fundamentally that's why
and and then even that object is
composed of
parts and also and another one is the
the shape of the object
uh is differently modeled from the
texture of the object
got it so there's like these um
i've been you know who francois charles
is
yeah he's so there's uh he developed
this like iq test type of thing
for arc challenge for and uh it's kind
of cool that there's um
these concepts priors that he defines
that you bring to the table
in order to be able to reason about
basic shapes and things
in the iq test right so here you're
making it
quite explicit that here here are the
things that you should be
there these are like distinct things
that you should be able to
uh model and yes keep in mind that
you you can derive this from much more
general principles
it doesn't you don't need to explicitly
put it as oh
objects versus foreground versus
background uh
the surface versus structure now these
are these are derivable from
more fundamental principles of how
you know what's the property of
continuity of natural signals
what's the property of continuity of
natural signals yeah
by the way that sounds very poetic but
yeah uh so you're saying that's a
there's some low-level properties from
which emerges the idea that shapes
should be different than
like uh there should be a parts of an
object there should be
i mean exactly kind of like friends of
water i mean there's objectness
there's all these things that it's kind
of crazy that we're humans
uh i guess evolved to have because it's
useful for us to perceive the world
correct yeah correct and it
derives mostly from the properties of
natural signals
and yeah and so um natural
signals so natural signals are the kind
of things we'll perceive in the
in the natural world i don't know i
don't i don't know why that sounds so
beautiful natural signals yeah as
opposed to a qr code
right which is an artificial signal that
we created humans are not very good at
classifying qr codes we are very good at
saying something is a cat or a dog
but not very good at you know the
classification computers are very good
at classifying qr codes so our visual
system is tuned for
natural signals and there are
fundamental assumptions
in the architecture that are derived
from natural signals
properties i wonder when you take a
hallucinogenic drugs
does that go into natural or is that
closer to the qr code
it's still natural yeah because it's it
is still operating
using your brains by the way on that on
that topic i i mean i haven't been
following i think they're becoming
legalized at certain i can't wait
until they become legalized to the
degree that you
like vision science futures could study
it yeah
just like through through medical
chemical ways modify there could be
ethical concerns but
modif that's another way to study the
brain is to be
be able to chemically modify it there's
probably
um probably very long a way to figure
out how to do it ethically
yeah but i i think there are studies on
that already
yeah i think so uh because it's not
unethical to give
uh it to rats oh that's true that's true
[Laughter]
there's a lot of drugged up rats out
there okay yeah cool
sorry sorry so okay so there's uh so
there's these
uh low-level uh
things from natural signals that uh that
that
from which these properties will emerge
yes uh but it is still
a very hard problem on how to encode
that again so you don't
you know there is no uh so uh you
mentioned
um the the the priors uh francho wanted
to encode in
uh in the abstract reasoning challenge
but it is not straightforward how to
encode those priors
um so so some of those uh challenges
like you know
the object completion challenges are
things that we purely use our visual
system to do it is uh it
looks like abstract reasoning but it is
purely an output of
the the vision system for example
completing the corners of that condenser
triangle completing the lines of that
cancer triangle
it's a purely a visual system property
there is no abstract reasoning involved
it it uses all these priors but it is
stored
in our visual system in a particular way
that is amenable to inference
and and and that is one of the things
that we tackled in the you know so
basically saying okay these are the
prior knowledge
uh which which will be derived from the
world but then
how is that prior knowledge represented
in the model
such that inference when when some piece
of evidence comes in
can be done very efficiently and in a
very distributed way
um because it is very there are so many
ways of representing knowledge
which is not amenable to very quick
inference
in a quick lookups and so that's one
um core part of what we tackled
in uh the rcn model um uh how do you
encode visual knowledge to uh
do very quick inference and yeah can you
maybe comment on uh
so folks listening to this in general
may be familiar with
different kinds of architectures of
neural networks
what what are we talking about with rcn
uh
what are what does the architecture look
like what are different components
is it close to neural networks is it far
away from neural networks what does it
look like
yeah so so you can uh think of the delta
between the model
and a convolutional neural network if
people are familiar with convolutional
neural networks
so convolutional neural networks have
this feed-forward processing cascade
which is called
uh feature detectors and pooling and
that is repeated in the in the hierarchy
in a
multi-level uh system um and if you
if you want an intuitive idea of what
what is happening feature detectors are
uh you know detecting interesting
co-occurrences
in the input it can be a line a corner
a an eye or a piece of texture
etc and the pooling neurons are
doing some local transformation of that
and making it invariant to local
transformations so this is what the
structure of convolutional neural
network is
um recursive cortical network
has a similar structure when you look at
just the feed forward pathway
but in addition to that it is also
structured in a way that it is
generating
so that again it can run it backward and
combine the forward with the backward
another aspect that it has is
it has lateral connections these
lateral connections um which is between
so if you have an edge here and an edge
here
it has connections between these edges
it is not just feed forward connections
it is um something between these edges
which is the nodes are presenting these
edges which is to enforce compatibility
between them
so otherwise what will happen is the
constraints it's a constraint it's
basically
if you if you do just feature detection
followed by pooling
then your your transformations in
different parts of the visual field are
not coordinated
uh and so you can you will create a
jagged
when you when you generate from the
model you will create jagged um
things and uncoordinated transformations
so these lateral connections are
enforcing
the the transformations is the whole
thing still differentiable
uh no okay no it's not it's not
trade using uh backprop okay that's
really important so
uh so there's this feed forward there's
feedback mechanisms
there's some interesting connectivity
things it's still layered
like uh yes there are multiple levels
multiple
layers okay very very interesting uh and
yeah okay so the interconnection between
um adjacent the connections across
service constraints
that like keep the thing stable got it
okay so what else uh and then there is
this idea of
doing inference a neural network does
not do
inference on the fly so an example of
why
this inference is important is you know
so one of the first applications
of that we showed in the paper was to
crack uh text-based captchas what are
captures by the way
by the way one of the most awesome like
the people don't use this term anymore
is human computation i think
uh i love this term the guy who created
captures
i think came up with this term yeah i
love it anyway uh
yeah uh what what are captures so
captchas
are those strings that you fill in
uh when you're you know when if you're
opening a new account in google
they show you a picture you know usually
it used to be
a set of garbage letters uh that you
have to kind of
figure out what what what is that string
of characters and type in
and the reason cap just exist is because
you know
google or twitter do not want
automatic creation of accounts you can
use a computer
to create millions of accounts uh and uh
use that for in nefarious purposes uh so
you want to make sure that
to the extent possible the interaction
that your their system is having
is with a human so it's a it's called a
human interaction proof
a captcha is a human interaction proof
um so
so this is a captchas are by design
things that are
easy for humans to solve but hard for
computers hard for robots yeah
so and text-based captchas where
was the one which is prevalent and
around 2014
because at that time text-based voice
captures were hard for
computers to crack even now they are
actually
in the sense of an arbitrary text based
capture
will be unsolvable even now but with the
techniques that we have developed it can
be you know you can quickly develop
a mechanism that solves the captcha
they've probably gotten a lot harder too
the people
they've been getting clever and clever
generating these text characters yeah
right so okay so that was one of the
things you've tested
on is these kinds of captures in 2014
15.
got that kind of stuff right right so
what uh
what i mean why by the way why captchas
yeah
yeah even now i would say captcha is a
very
very good challenge problem uh if you
want to
understand how human perception works
and if you want to build
uh systems that work like the human
brain
uh and i wouldn't say captcha is a
solved problem we have
cracked the fundamental defense of
captures but it is not solved
in the way that humans solve it um
so i can give an example i can um take a
five-year-old child
who has just learned characters uh and
uh
show them any new capture that we create
they will be able to solve it
uh i can show you pretty much any new
capture
from any new website you'll be able to
solve it without getting
any training examples from that
particular style of captcha you're
assuming i'm human yeah yes
yeah that's right so if you are human
and
if you otherwise i will be able to
figure that out using this one
but uh so this whole podcast is just a
touring test
a long turing test anyway i'm sorry so
yeah
so human humans can figure it out with
very few examples
or no training examples like no training
examples from that particular style of
capture
and and so you can you know so uh even
now this is
unreachable for the current deep
learning system so
basically there is no i don't think a
system exists where you can basically
say
train on whatever you want and then now
say hey i will show you a new captcha
which i did not show you in
in the in the training setup will the
system be able to solve it
um it still doesn't exist so that is
the magic of human perception yeah and
doug have starter
uh put this uh very beautifully in
one of his uh talks the the central
problem
in ai is what is the letter a
if you can if you can build a system
that reliably
can detect all the variations of the
letter a you don't even need to go to
the
v and the c yeah you don't even know the
b and c or the strings of characters
and uh so that that is the spirit at
which you know with which we
uh tackle that what does it mean by that
i mean is it uh
like without training examples try to
figure out
the fundamental uh elements that make
up the letter a in all of its forms in
all of its forms it can be
a can be made with two humans standing
leaning against each other holding the
hands yeah
and uh it can be made of leaves it can
be yeah you might have to understand
uh everything about this world in order
to understand letter a
yeah exactly so it's common sense
reasoning essentially yeah
right so so to finally to really solve
finally to say that you have solved
captcha
uh you have to solve the whole problem
yeah okay so what how does this kind of
the rcn architecture help us to get a do
a
better job of that kind of yeah so uh as
i mentioned
one of the important things was being
able to do inference
being able to dynamically do in france
can you can you uh
can you uh clarify what you mean because
you said like neural networks don't do
inference
yeah so what do you mean by inference in
this context then so
okay so in captures what they do to
confuse people
is to make these characters crowd
together
yes okay and when you make the
characters crowd together
what happens is that you will now start
seeing combinations of characters as
some other new character or or an
existing character so you would
you would put an r and n together it
will start looking like an m
uh and and so locally they are you know
there is very strong evidence for it
being
uh some uh incorrect character
but globally the only explanation that
fits together
is something that is different from what
you can find locally
yes so so so this is inference you are
basically taking
uh local evidence and putting it in the
global context
and often coming to a conclusion locally
which is
conflicting with the local information
so actually so
you mean inference like uh in the way
it's used
when you talk about reasoning for
example uh as opposed to like
inference which is this when you know
with artificial neural networks which is
a single pass through the network
okay so like you're basically doing some
basic forms of reasoning
like integration of like uh how local
things fit into the the global picture
and and things like explaining away
coming into this one because
you are you are uh explaining that piece
of evidence
uh as something else uh because globally
that's the only thing that makes sense
um so now yeah you
can amortize this inference by
you know in a neural network if you want
to do this what you you can
you can brute force it you can just show
it all combinations of things
that you want to you want to your
reasoning to work over
and you can you know like just train the
help out of that neural network
and it will look like it is doing uh you
know inference on the fly but it is it
is
really just doing amortized inference it
is because you
you have shown it a lot of these
combinations during training time
um so what you want to do is be able to
do dynamic inference rather than just
being able to show all those
combinations in the training time and
that's something we emphasized in the
model
what does it mean dynamic in france is
that that has to do with the feedback
thing yes like what what is dynamic i
i'm trying to visualize what dynamic
influence would be in this case
like what is it doing with the input
it's showing the input the first time
yeah and is is like what's changing over
temporally
over what's the dynamics of this
inference process
so you can think of it as you have um at
the top
of the model the characters that you are
trained on yeah they are the causes
they you are trying to explain the
pixels using
the characters as the causes the you
know the characters
are the things that cause the pixels
yeah so there's this causality thing so
the reason you mentioned causality i
guess is because there's a temporal
aspect of this whole thing
in this particular case the temporal
aspect is not important it is more like
when if if i turn the character on
the the pixels will turn on yeah it will
be after there's a little bit but
okay so that is the causality in the
sense of like a logic causality like
hence inference okay the dynamics is
that
uh even though locally it will look like
okay this is an a
and and locally just when i look at just
that patch of the image
it looks like an a but when i look at it
in the context of all the other courses
it might no am is not the something that
makes sense so that is something you
have to kind of
you know recursively figure out yeah so
okay so
uh and uh this thing performed pretty
well on the captchas
correct and um
i mean is there some kind of interesting
intuition you can provide
why did well like what did it look like
is there visualizations that could be
human interpretable to us humans
yes yeah so the good thing about the
model is that it is
extremely um so it is not just doing a
classification
right it is it is it is it is providing
a full explanation for the scene
so when when it when it um
operates on a scene it is coming at back
and saying look
this is the part is the a and these are
the pixels that turned on
uh these are the pixels in the input
that tells makes me think that
it is an a and also these are the
portions i hallucinated
it you know it it provides a complete
explanation of that form and
then it's again these are the contours
these are this is the interior
and this is in front of this other
object so
that that's the kind of um explanation
it uh
the the inference network provides so so
that
that is useful and interpretable um
and uh um then the kind of errors it
makes
are also i don't want to um
read too much into it but the kind of
errors the network makes are
very similar to the kinds of errors
humans would make in
a similar situation so there's something
about the structure that's uh
feels reminiscent of the way humans
visual
system works well i mean uh how
hard-coded
is this to the capture problem this idea
uh
not really hardcoded because it's the uh
the assumptions as i mentioned are
general right it is more um and and
those
themselves can be applied in many
situations which are
natural signals um so it's it's the
foreground versus
background factorization and the
factorization of
the surfaces versus the contours so
these are all generally applicable
assumptions in our vision so why why
capture why attack the capture problem
which is quite unique in the computer
vision context versus like
the traditional benchmarks of imagenet
and all those kinds of
image classification or even
segmentation tests all that kind of
stuff
do you feel like that's uh i mean what
what's your thinking about those kinds
of benchmarks
in um in this in this context i mean
those benchmarks are useful
for deep learning kind of algorithms
where you
you know so the settings uh that deep
learning works in
are here is my huge training set and
here is my test set so the
the training set is almost uh you know
100 x 1000 x bigger than
uh the test set in many many cases
uh what we wanted to do was invert that
the training set is way smaller than the
the test set yes uh and uh uh
and you know uh captcha is a problem
that is by definition hard for computers
and
it has these good properties of strong
generalization strong
out of training distribution
generalization if you are interested
in studying that and putting
having your model have that property
then it's it's a good data set to tackle
so is there have you attempted to which
i think
i believe there's quite a growing body
of work
on looking at mnist and imagenet
without training so it's like taking
like the basic challenge is
how what tiny fraction of the training
set can we take in order to do
a reasonable job of the classification
task
have you explored that angle in these
classic benchmarks
yes so so we did do mnist so um you know
so it's not just capture we
uh so there was uh also uh
uh versions of multiple versions of
mnist including the
the standard version which where we
inverted the problem which is basically
saying
rather than train on 60 000 uh training
data
uh you know how uh quickly can you
get uh to high level accuracy with very
little training data was
is there some performance do you
remember like how well
how well did it do how many examples did
he need
yeah i i you know i remember that it was
you know uh on the order of uh
tens or hundreds of examples to get into
uh 95
accuracy and it was it was definitely
better than the systems other systems
out there
at that time at that time yeah yeah
they're really pushing i think that's a
really
interesting space actually uh i think
there's an actual name for mnist
that uh like there's different names the
different
sizes of training sets i mean people are
like attacking this problem i think it's
super
interesting yeah it's funny how like
that mnist will probably
be with us all the way to agi yes
it's the data set that just sticks by it
is it's a clean
simple uh data set to uh
to study the fundamentals of learning
with just like captures it's interesting
not enough people i don't know maybe you
can correct me but i feel like captures
don't show up
as often in papers as they probably
should that's correct yeah because you
know
um usually these things have a momentum
uh you know once
once uh something gets established as a
standard benchmark yeah there is a
there is a uh there is a dynamics of
how graduate students operate and how
the academ academy system works
that uh pushes people to track that uh
benchmark so yeah
yeah so nobody wants to think outside
the box okay
okay so good performance on the captures
what else is there interesting um on the
rcn side before we talk about the
cortical microscope yeah so
the same model so the the the important
part of the model was that it trains
very quickly with very little training
data
and it's you know quite robust to out of
distribution
uh perturbations um and and we are using
that
uh very uh fruitfully in uh advocates in
many of the robotic stocks we are
solving
so you know well let me ask you this
kind of touchy question i have to
i i've spoken with uh your friend
colleague
jeff hawkins too i mean he's uh i have
to kind of ask
there is a bit of whenever you have
brain inspired stuff
yeah and you make big claims yeah uh big
sexy claims
yeah there's a you know uh there's
critics i mean machine learning
subreddit
don't get me started on those people uh
their heart i mean criticism is good but
they're a bit
they're a bit over the top um there is
quite a bit of
sort of skepticism and criticism you
know is this work really as good as it
promises to be
yeah what do you have thoughts on that
kind of skepticism
do you have comments on the kind of
criticism you might have received
uh about you know is this approach legit
is this is this a promising approach
yeah
or at least as promising as it seems to
be you know
advertised as yeah i can comment on it
um
so you know our arson paper is published
in science which i would argue
is is a very high quality journal very
hard to uh publish in
and use you know usually it is
indicative of the
of the quality of the work and um
i can i can i am very very certain that
the ideas that we brought together in
that paper uh in terms of
the importance of feedback connections
uh recursive inference
lateral connections uh coming to best
explanation of the scene as the problem
to solve
trying to solve um recognition
segmentation
uh all jointly in a way that is
compatible with higher level cognition
top-down attention all those ideas that
we brought together into something
you know coherent and workable in the in
the world and solving a challenge
tackling a challenging problem i think
that will that will stay and that that
contribution i
stand by right now uh i can i can
tell you a story which is funny in the
in the context of this right um so
if you read the abstract of the paper
and you know the argument we are putting
in
you know we are putting in look current
deep learning systems take a lot of
training data
uh they don't use these insights and
here is our new model
which is not a deep neural network it's
a graphical model it does inference this
is what how the paper is right
now once the paper was accepted and
everything um
it went to the press department in in
science you know to play as
science office we we didn't do any press
release when it was published it was he
went to the press department
what did the what was the press release
that they wrote up a new deep learning
model
solves captchas and uh so
so you can see where was you know what
was being hyped uh in that uh
thing right so so it's like um there is
the
there is a dynamic in the uh in the
community of you know so
uh um that's especially happens when
there are
lots of new people coming into the field
and they get attracted to one thing
and some people are trying to think
different uh compared to that so there's
there is some
uh i think skepticism is science is
important and it is
um you know very much uh required
but it's also it's not uh skepticism
usually it's mostly bandwagon effect
that is happening
rather than well but that's not even
that i mean
i'll tell you what they react to which
is like
i'm sensitive to as well if you if you
look at just companies open ai deep mind
yeah um vicarious i mean it just
there's uh there's a little bit of a
race
to the top and hype right right it's
it's like
it doesn't pay off to be humble
so like uh and and the press is just
uh irresponsible often they they just i
mean don't get me started on
the state of journalism today like it
seems like the people who write articles
about these
things they literally have not even
spent an hour on the wikipedia article
about what is
neural networks like yeah they haven't
like invested
just even the language to laziness
it's like uh robots
beat humans like they they write this
kind of stuff
that just uh and then and then of course
the researchers are
quite sensitive to that because it gets
a lot of attention
they're like why did this work get so
much attention
uh you know that's that's over the top
and people get really sensitive you know
the same kind of criticism with uh
opening i did work with the rubik's cube
with the robot that people criticized
uh same with gpt two and three they
criticize
uh same thing with the deep minds with
alpha zero i mean
yeah i i'm sensitive to it but
and of course with your work you
mentioned deep learning but there's
something super sexy to the
public about brain inspired i mean that
immediately grabs people's imagination
not even like
neural networks but like really brain
inspired like
like brain like neural networks that
seems
really compelling to people and um to me
as well to
to the world as a narrative and so uh
people hook up hook on to that and uh
sometimes you uh the skepticism engine
turns on in the research community and
they're
skeptical but i think putting aside
the ideas of the actual performance on
captures or performance in any data set
i mean to me all these data sets are
useless anyway it's nice to have them
but in the grand scheme of things
they're silly toy examples
the point is is their intuition about
the the ideas just like you mentioned
bringing the ideas
together in a unique way is there
something there is there some value
there
and this is going to stand the test of
time yes and that's the hope
that's the hope i'm my confidence there
is very high
i you know i don't treat brain inspect
as a marketing term
uh you know i am looking into the
details
of biology and i'm puzzling over
uh those things and i am i am grappling
with those things and
so this it is not a marketing term at
all it you know you can use it as a
marketing term and
and people often use it and you can get
combined with them and when
when people don't understand how we are
approaching the problem
it is it is easy to be uh misunderstood
and
you know think of it as you know purely
uh marketing but that's not the way
uh we are so you really i mean as a
scientist
you believe that if we kind of just
stick to
really understanding the brain that's
going to
that's the right like you should
constantly meditate on the
how does the brain do this because
that's going to be really helpful for
engineering intelligent systems
yes you need to so i think it is it's
one input and it is it is helpful
but you you should know when to deviate
from it
too um so an example is convolutional
neural networks
right uh convolution is not an operation
brain
in implements uh the visual cortex is
not convolutional
visual cortex has local receptive fields
local connectivity
but the you know the um there is there
is no
translation in in variance in the um
uh the network weights um in in the
visual cortex that is a
a computational trick which is a very
good engineering trick that we use
for sharing the training between the
different uh nodes
um so and and that trick will be with us
for some time it will go away when
we have um
robots with eyes and heads that move uh
and
so then that trick will go away it will
not be uh useful at that time
so so the brain doesn't so the brain
doesn't have translational invariance
it has the focal point like it has a
thing it focuses on correct it does it
has a phobia
and and because of the phobia um the
receptive fields are not
like the copying of the weights like the
the weights in the center are very
different from the weights in the
periphery
yes at the periphery i mean i did this
uh
actually wrote a paper and just gotten
the chance to really study peripheral
peripheral vision which is a fascinating
thing
very under understood thing
of what the br you know at the every
level the brain does
with the periphery it does some funky
stuff yeah so it's uh
it's another kind of trick than
uh convolutional like it does it
it uh it's a you know convolutional
convolution in neural networks is a
trick to for efficiency
is efficiency trick and the brain does a
whole another kind of thing yeah yes got
it
so so you need to understand the
principles
or processing so that you can still
apply
engineering tricks yeah when where you
want to do you don't want to be
slavishly making
all the things of the brain um and and
so yeah so it should be one input and i
think it is
extremely helpful uh but you it should
be the point of
really understanding so that you know
when to deviate from it
so okay that's really cool that that's
work from
a few years ago so you'd uh you did work
in jumento with jeff hawkins
yeah uh with uh hierarchical temporal
memory
how is your just if you could give a
brief history
how is your view of the way the models
of the brain changed over the past
few years leading up to to now is there
some interesting aspects where
there is an adjustment to your
understanding of the brain or is it all
just building on top of each other
in terms of the higher level ideas
especially the ones jeff wrote about in
the book if you if you blur out
right you know yeah on intelligence
right on intelligence if you if you blur
out the details
and and if you just zoom out and at the
higher level idea
uh things are i would say consistent
with what he wrote about but
but many things will be consistent with
that because it is it's a blur you know
when you when you
you know deep learning systems are also
you know multi-level hierarchical
all of those things right so so at the
but
um in terms of the detail a lot of
things are different
uh and and and those details matter a
lot
um so so one point of difference i had
with jeff
uh uh was uh how to approach
you know how much of biological
possibility and realism
do you want in the learning algorithms
um
so uh when i was there uh this was you
know
almost 10 years ago now so yeah you're
having fun
i don't know i don't know what just
thinks now but 10 years ago
uh the difference was that i did not
want to
be so constrained on saying uh
my learning algorithms won't need to be
biologically possible
based on some filter of biological
possibility available at that time
to me that is a dangerous cut to make
because
we are you know discovering more and
more things about the brain all the time
new biophysical mechanisms new channels
uh
are being discovered all the time so i
don't want to upfront kill off
an uh a learning algorithm just because
we don't
really understand the full uh the full
uh
biophysics or whatever of how the brain
learns exactly exactly well
let me ask a sergeant like what's our
what's your sense what's our best
understanding of how the brain
learns so things like back propagation
credit assignment so so
many of these algorithms have learning
algorithms have things in common
right it is a back propagation is one
way of credit assignment
there is another algorithm called
expectation maximization
which is you know another weight
adjustment algorithm but is it your
sense the brain does something like this
has to there is no way around it in the
sense of saying that
you do have to adjust the the
connections
so yeah and you're saying credit
assignment you have to reward the
connections that were useful and making
a correct prediction and not
yeah i guess what up but yeah it doesn't
have to be
differentiable i mean yeah it doesn't
have to be differentiable yeah yeah
but you have to have a you know you have
a
model that you start with you where you
have data comes in
and you have to have a way of adjusting
the model such that it better fits the
data yeah so that that is all of
learning right
and some of them can be using backprop
to do that
some of it can be using uh you know very
local
uh graph changes to do that
um that can you know many of these
learning algorithms
have similar update properties locally
in terms of what the neurons need to do
locally
i wonder if small differences in
learning algorithms can have huge
differences in the actual effect
so the dynamics of i mean uh
sort of the reverse like spiking like
the uh
if if credit assignment is like a a
lightning versus like
a rainstorm or something like whether
whether there's a like a looping
local type of situation with the credit
assignment
yeah whether there is uh
like regularization like how
um how it injects robustness into the
whole thing
like whether it's chemical or electrical
or mechanical yeah uh all those kinds of
things like that
i feel like it that yeah
i feel like those differences could be
essential right it could be
it's just that you don't know enough to
on the learning side you don't know
enough to say that is definitely not the
way the brain does it
got it so you don't want to be stuck to
it right so that yeah
so you you've been open-minded on that
side of that correct on the
infrastructure on the recognition side i
am
much more uh i'm able to be constrained
because
it's much easier to do experiments
because you know it's like okay here's
the stimulus
you know how many steps did it get to
take the answer i can trace it back
i can i can understand the speed of that
computation
etc much more readily on the infant side
got it and then
you can't do good experiments on the
learning side correct
so that let's let's go right into the
cortical micro circuits right back
so what uh what are these ideas
beyond recursive cortical network that
uh
you're looking at now so we have made a
you know pass through or you know
multiple of the steps that we
you know i say as i mentioned earlier
you know we were looking at perception
from the angle of cognition right it was
not just perception for perception's
sake
how do you how do you connect it to
cognition uh how do you learn
concepts and how do you learn abstract
reasoning uh
similar to some of the things francois
uh uh talked about right um
so um so
we have uh taken one pass through it
basically saying
what is the basic cognitive architecture
that you need to have which has a
perceptual system
which has a system that learns dynamics
of the world and
then has something like a routine
program learning system on top of it to
learn concepts
so we have we've built one the you know
the version
0.1 of that system uh this was another
uh
science robotics paper uh it is it's the
title of that paper was
you know something like cognitive
programs how do you build cognitive
programs
and and the application there was on
manipulation robotics it was um
so think of it like this suppose you uh
wanted to
tell a new person uh that you met
you don't know the language or that
person uses you want to communicate to
that person
uh to achieve some task right so i want
to say
hey um you need to pick up all the the
red cups from the kitchen counter and
put it here
right how do you communicate that right
you can show
pictures you can basically say look this
is the starting state
the the things are here this is the
ending state
and and what does the person need to
understand from that
the person need to understand what
conceptually happened in those pictures
from the
input to the output right so um
so we are looking at pre-verbal
conceptual understanding without
language
how do you how do you have a set of
concepts that you can
manipulate in your head uh and from
this in a set of images of input and
output
can you infer what is happening in those
images
got it with concepts that are
pre-language okay so what does it mean
for a concept to be pre-language like
yeah why why so why
why is language uh so important here
so i i want to make a distinction
between
concepts that are just learned from text
by just just feeding brute force text uh
you can you can start extracting things
like okay
uh cow is likely to be on grass
so those kinds of things you can extract
purely from text um
uh but that's kind of a simple
association
uh thing rather than a concept as an
abstraction of something
that happens in the real world you know
in a
grounded way that i can i can simulate
it in my mind and connect it
back to the real world and you think
kind of the visual
uh the visual world concepts in the
visual world
are somehow lower level than just the
language the lower level kind of makes
it
feel like okay that's like unimportant
like it's more like
uh i would say uh
the concepts in the visual and the motor
system
and you know the uh the concept learning
system which
if you cut off the language part just uh
just what we learned by interacting with
the world and abstractions from that
that is a prerequisite for any real
language understanding
so you're uh so you disagree with
chomsky because he says language is at
the bottom of everything
no i i yeah i disagree with chomsky
completely
from from universal grammar to yeah
so that was a paper in science beyond
the recursive cortical network
uh what what other interesting problems
are there
the open problems and brain inspired uh
approaches that you're thinking about i
mean everything is over right like you
know no
no no problem is uh solved solved all
right uh
first uh i think of perception as kind
of
the the pro the first thing that you
have to build
but the last thing that you will be
actually solved
so because if you do not build
perception system in the right way
you cannot build concept system in the
right way
so so you have to build a perception
system however wrong that might be
you have to still build that and learn
concepts from there
and then you know keep it rating um and
and finally perception will get
solved fully when perception cognition
language all those things work together
finally so what uh i'm not
so great we've talked a lot about
perception but then maybe on the concept
side and like
common sense or just general reasoning
side
is there some some intuition you can
draw from the brain about
how we can do that so i have i have this
uh classic example i give um
so suppose i give you a few sentences
and then ask you a question following
that sentence this is a
natural language processing problem
right so so here
it goes i'm telling you uh sally pounded
a nail on the ceiling okay
oh that's a sentence now i am asking you
a question was the nail horizontal or
vertical
vertical okay how did you answer that
uh well i imagined sally it was kind of
hard to imagine what the hell she was
doing but
uh but i imagined i
had a visual of the whole situation
exactly
exactly so so here you know i i post a
question in natural language
the answer to that question was you you
got the answer from actually simulating
the scene now i can go more and more
detail about
okay was sally stan standing on
something while doing this you know
could could she have been uh standing on
a light bulb to do this you know i could
i could ask more and more questions
about this and i can ask
make you simulate the synonym scene in
more and more detail right
where is all that knowledge that you are
accessing
stored it is not in your language system
it is not
it was not just by reading text you got
that knowledge
it is stored from the everyday
experiences that you have had
from and and by the by the age of five
you you have pretty much all of this
right and it is stored in your visual
system motor system
in a way such that it can be accessed
through language
i got it i mean right so your the
language is just
almost services the query into the whole
visual cortex and it does the whole
feedback thing
but i mean it is all reasoning kind of
connected to the perception system
in some way you can do a lot of it you
know you can still
um do a lot of it by quick associations
without having to
go into the depth and and most of the
time you will be right
right you can just do quick associations
but i can easily create tricky
situations for you where that quick
association is wrong
and you have to actually run the
simulation so the figuring out the
how these concepts connect
you have a good idea of how to do that
that's exactly what
that does one of the problems that we
are working on and and
and and the uh the way we are
approaching that is basically
saying okay you need to so the the uh
the takeaway is that language is
simulation control
and your perceptual plus uh motor system
is building a simulation of the world
and so so that's basically the way we
are approaching it and
the first thing that we built was a
controllable perceptual system
and we built a schema networks which was
a controllable dynamic system
then we built a concept learning system
that puts
all these things together into programs
are subtractions that you can
run and simulate and now we are taking
the step of connecting into language and
uh and uh it will be very simple
examples initially it will not be
the gpt three like examples but it will
be grounded simulation based language
and for like the the querying would be
like question answering
kind of thing correct correct and it
will be in some simple world initially
on you know uh i but it will be about
okay can the system
connect the language and uh ground it in
the right way and run the right
simulations
to come up with the answer and the goal
is to try to do things that for example
gpg3 couldn't do
got it speaking of which
if we could uh talk about gpt3
a little bit i think it's an interesting
thought-provoking set of ideas that open
ai is pushing forward i think it's good
for us to talk about
the limits and the possibilities in
neural networks so
in general what are your thoughts about
this recently released
very large 175 billion parameter
language model
so i have i haven't uh directly
evaluated it
yet from what i have seen on twitter and
you know other people evaluating it
it looks very intriguing you know i am i
am very intrigued by some of the
properties it is displaying and
and of course the text generation uh
part of
that was already evident in gpt2
you know that it can generate cochrane
text over uh
uh long distances that was uh but
of course the weaknesses are also pretty
visible
in saying that okay it is not really
carrying a world state around
um and you know sometimes you get
sentences like
i went up the hill to reach the valley
or the thing now there
are some you know completely
incompatible statements
or when you're traveling from one place
to the other it doesn't take into
account the time of travel
things like that so those things i think
will happen less than gpt
3 because it is trained on even more
data and
so and it has it can do even more longer
distance
uh uh coherence um but it will still
have the fundamental limitations that it
doesn't have a world model
uh and it can't run simulations in its
head to
find whether something is true in the
world or not
do you think within so it's taking a
huge amount of text from the internet
and forming a compressed representation
do you think
in that could could emerge something
that's an approximation
of a world model which essentially could
be used for reasoning
and it's a it's a it's a i'm not talking
about gpt three i'm talking about gpt
four five and gpt 10. yeah i mean they
will look
more impressive than gpg3 so you can if
you take that to the extreme then
uh a markov chain of just first order
and if you if you go to um
i'm taking the other extreme if you read
shannon's book
right uh he has a model of english text
which is based on faster mark of chains
second order markov chains third markov
chain sentencing that
okay the markov chains look better than
uh
faster markov chains right so does that
mean
a faster markov chain has a model of the
world
yes it does uh so yes in that level
uh when you go higher order models or
more uh sophisticated structure in the
model like the transformer networks have
yes they have a model of the text world
um but that is not a model of
uh the world it's it's a model of the
text world and it will have in
interesting uh properties and it will be
useful
but just scaling it up is not going to
give us a gi or natural language
understanding or meaning well the the
question is
uh whether being forced to compress a
very large amount of text
yeah forces you to construct things that
are
very much like because the ideas of
concepts and meaning is
a spectrum yeah uh
so in order to form that kind of
compression
maybe it will uh be forced to figure out
abstractions which look awfully a lot
like the kind of things that we think
about as uh
as concepts as world models as common
sense
is that possible no i don't think it is
possible because the information is not
there
well the information is uh is there
behind the text
right now unless somebody has written
down all the details
about how everything works in the world
to the
the absurd amounts like okay it is
easier to walk
forward than backward uh that you have
to open the door to go out of the thing
uh doctors wear underwear you know
unless
all these things somebody has written
down somewhere or you know somehow the
program found it to be useful for
compression
from some other text uh the information
is not there
so that's an argument that like text is
a lot lower fidelity than
the you know the experience of our
physical world
like right so you can use a thousand
words like that
kind of thing well in this case pictures
aren't really
so the the richest aspect of the
physical world isn't
even just pictures it's the uh it's the
interactivity of the world
yeah it's being able to um
yeah interact it's almost like
it's almost like if you could interact
so i
i i disagree well maybe i agree with you
that picture's worth a thousand words
but
a thousand it's still yeah you could say
you could capture it with the gpt
x so i wonder if there's some
interactive element where
a system could live in text world where
it could uh be part of the
chat be part of you know talking to
people
it's it's interesting i mean
fundamentally so
you're making a statement about the
limitation of text
okay let's so let's say we have a text
corpus that includes basically
every experience we could possibly have
i mean just a very large corpus of text
and also interactive components i guess
the question is whether the neural
network architecture these very
simple transformers but if they had like
hundreds of trillions or whatever comes
after a trillion
parameters whether that could store
the information needed that's
architecturally do you have
like do you have thoughts about the
limitation on that side of
things with neural networks i mean so
transformer is you know still a feed
forward neural network this uh
uh it's it has a very uh interesting
architecture which is good for
uh text modeling and probably some
aspects of uh video modeling but it is
still a feed forward architecture and
you believe in the feedback mechanism
the recursion oh
and and also because you know causality
you know being able to do counterfactual
reasoning
being able to do you know intervention
so which is uh uh
um actions in the world uh so
all those things uh require different
kinds of models to be built
uh i i don't think uh transformers uh
captures that uh family it is very good
at statistical modeling of
text uh yeah and and it will become
better and better with more data
uh bigger models but that is only going
to get so far
you know finally when you in so i had
this joke on uh
twitter saying that hey this is a model
that has read all of
quantum mechanics and theory of
relativity and we are asking it to do
text completion or
you know we are actually asking you to
solve simple puzzles that you know
when when you have agi if you if you you
know that's not what you ask a system to
do if you just
you know we ask we'll ask the system to
do experiments you know what should
uh and and come up with hypothesis and
uh you know revise the hypothesis based
on evidence from experiments all those
things right
those are the things that we want the
system to do when we have a gi
not solved with simple puzzles so
like impressive demo somebody generating
a red button in html
right uh which are all useful like you
know there's no
not dissing the the usefulness of it
yeah so i get by the way i'm
i mean playing a little bit of a devil's
advocate
uh so calm down internet uh so i just
i'm curious almost
in which ways will a dumb but
large neural network will surprise us
yeah so like i'm it's kind of your i
completely agree with your intuition
it's just that i don't want to
dogmatically like 100 percent
put all the chips there right it's we've
been surprised
so much even the current gpt 2 and
3 are so surprising yeah uh
the self-play mechanisms of alpha zero
are really surprising and
i the reinforcement the fact that
reinforcement learning works at all to
me is really surprising
the fact that neural networks work at
all is quite surprising
given how non-linear the space is the
fact it's able to find
local minima that are at all reasonable
it's very surprising so
it uh i i wonder sometimes
whether us humans just want
it to not the for agi not to be such a
dumb thing
so i just because exactly what you're
saying is like
the ideas of concepts and be able to
reason with those concepts and
and connect those concepts in uh like
hierarchical ways
and then to be able to have uh world
models i mean just
everything we're describing in human
language in this poetic way
seems to make sense that that is what
intelligence and reasoning are like i
i wonder if at the core of it it could
be much dumber
uh well finally it is still connections
and messages passing over them
right right so that way it's done
so i guess the recursion the the
feedback mechanism
that does seem to be a fundamental kind
of thing um
yeah yeah the idea of concepts also
memory
correct like having an episodic memory
yeah yeah
that seems to be an important thing so
how do we get memory
so yeah we have another piece of work
that which came out recently on
how do you form episodic memories and
and form abstractions from them
uh and we haven't figured out a you know
all the connections of that to the
overall cognitive architecture
but um well yeah what are your ideas
about
how you could have episodic memory so at
least it's very clear that
there you need to have two kinds of
memory right that that's very very clear
right because
there are things that happen uh
as statistical patterns in the world uh
but then there is the
the one timeline of things that happen
only once in your life right
uh uh and this day is not going to
happen ever again and and so
and that needs to be stored as a as a
you know
just a stream of uh string right this is
this is my experience and then then the
question is
about how do you take that experience
and connect it to the statistical part
of it how do you
now say that okay i experienced this
thing now i want to
be careful about similar situations uh
and so
so you need to be able to index that
similarity
using your other giant status
you know the the model of the world that
you have learned although the situation
came from the episode you need to be
able to index the other one so
uh the episodic memory
being implemented as an indexing over
the
other uh model that you're building
so the memories remain and they uh
they they're an index into this like the
statistical thing that you formed yeah
statistical
causal structural model that you built
over over time
so so it's basically the idea is that uh
the hippocampus
is uh just storing
or sequencing uh
in a set of pointers that happens over
time
and then whenever you want to
reconstitute that memory and evaluate
the different uh aspects of it whether
it was good bad do i need to encounter
the situation again
you need the cortex to reinstantiate to
replay that memory
so how do you find that memory like
which direction is the important
direction
both directions are units again
bi-directional
so i guess how do you retrieve the
memory so this is again hypothesis right
yeah we're making this work
so when you uh when you come to a new
situation right uh
your your cortex is doing inference uh
over
in the new situation and then of course
hippocampus is connected to different
parts of the cortex
um and and you have this deja vu
situation right
okay i have seen this thing before and
uh and then in the hippocampus you can
have an index of okay this is when it
happened
as a timeline uh and and and
then then you can use the hippocampus to
drive the the similar timelines to say
now i am i am
rather than being driven by my current
input stimuli
i am going back in time and rewinding my
experience for applying it
but putting back into the cortex and
then putting it back into the cortex of
course
affects what you're going to see next in
your current situation
got it yeah so that's that's the whole
thing having a world model and then
yeah uh connecting to the perception
yeah it does seem to be
that that's what's happening it'd be
on the neural network side it's um it's
interesting to think of how we actually
do that
yeah yeah to have a knowledge base
yes it is possible that you can put many
of these structures
into uh neural networks and we will find
ways of combining properties of
neural networks and graphical models so
uh i mean it's already started happening
yes uh graph neural networks are kind of
emerge between them
and there will be more of that thing so
but to me it is
the direction is pretty cl i mean
looking at biology and the histo history
of uh
uh evolutionary history of intelligence
it is pretty clear that
okay what does need is more structure in
the models
and modeling of the world and supporting
dynamic
inference well let me ask you uh
there's a guy named elon musk there's a
company called neurolink
and there's a general field called brain
computing interfaces yeah
um it's kind of uh interface between
your two
loves yes the brain and the intelligence
uh so there's like very direct
applications of brain computer
interfaces
for people with different conditions
more in the short term
yeah but there's also these sci-fi
futuristic kinds of ideas of
ai systems being able to
communicate in a high bandwidth way with
the brain
bi-directional yeah uh what are your
thoughts
about uh neural link and bci in general
as a possibility
so i think bca is a cool
research area and in fact um
when i got interested in brains
initially when you know so i was
enrolled at stanford and when i got
interested in brains it was it was
through a brain uh
computer interface talk that krishna
gave that's when i
even started thinking about the problem
so uh so it is definitely a fascinating
research area and it is
the applications are enormous right um
so
you know there is a science fiction
scenario of you know brains directly
communicating let's you know let's keep
that aside
for the time being uh even just the the
intermediate milestones that pursuing
which are
very reasonable as far as i can see uh
being able to control
an external limb using uh uh
in a direct connection from the brain
and being able to write things into the
brain
uh so so those are all uh
good steps to take and they have
enormous applications you know people
losing limbs being able to control
prosthetics
quadriplegics being able to control
something so
and therapeutics and you know i also
know about another company working in
the space
called paradromix they're doing you know
it's based on a different
uh electrode array but trying to attack
some of the same problems so i think
it's a very also surgery correct
surgically implanted electrons yeah
um so yeah i think of it as a
very very promising field especially
when it is helping people
overcome uh some limitations now at some
point
of course it will advance the level of
being able to communicate
uh how hard is that problem do you think
like so
so okay let's say we magically solve
what i think is a really hard problem of
doing
all of this safely yeah so so like
being able to uh connect electrodes and
not just
thousands but like millions to the right
i i think it's very very hard because
you also
do not know what the what will happen to
the brain
with that right in the sense of how does
the brain adapt to something like that
and it's you know as we're learning it's
the brain is
quite uh in terms of neuroplasticity
it's pretty malleable
so it's going to adjust so the machine
learning side the computer side is going
to adjust and then the brain is going to
adjust
exactly and then what what soup does
this landers
the kind of hallucinations you might get
from this
that might be pretty intense yeah yeah
just connecting to all of wikipedia
it's interesting whether we need to be
able to figure out
the basic protocol of the brain's
communication schemes
in order to get them to the machine and
the brain to talk
because another possibility is the brain
actually just adjusts to whatever the
heck the computer is doing exactly
that's the way
i think that i find that to be a more
promising way
it's basically saying you know okay
attach electrodes to some part of the
cortex
okay and make sure maybe if it is done
from birth
the brain will adapt it says that you
know that part is not damaged it was not
used for anything
these electrodes are attached there
right and now you
you train that part of the brain to do
this high bandwidth communication
between
something else right and and uh if you
do it like that
either then it is brain adapting to and
of course your external system is the
sciences that it is adaptable you know
just like we
you know design computers or mouse
keyboard all of them to be
uh interacting with humans so
of course that feedback system is
designed to be uh
human compatible but um
now it is not trying to record from the
all of the brain
and uh you know now you know two systems
trying to adapt to each other
it's the brain adapting into one way
it's passing
the brain is connected to like the
internet it's connected
yeah just imagine just connecting it to
twitter and just just just taking that
stream
of information um yeah
but again if we take a step back i don't
know what your intuition is
i feel like that is not as hard
of a problem as the
doing it safely there's there's a huge
barrier to surgery right
because because the biological system
it's it's a mush
of like weird stuff correct so
that the surgery part of it biology part
of it the the long term
repercussions part of it again i don't
know what else will
uh you know we we often find uh after a
long time
uh in biology that okay that idea was
wrong right you know so
people used to cut off this
the gland called the thymus or something
and
then they found that oh no that actually
causes cancer
and then there's a subtle like millions
of variables involved
but this whole process the nice thing
and just like again with elon just like
colonizing mars
seems like a ridiculously difficult idea
but
in the process of doing it we might
learn a lot about the biology of the
neurobiology of the brain
the neuroscience side of things it's
like if you want to learn something
do the most difficult version of it yeah
and see what you learn
the intermediate steps that they are
taking sounded all very reasonable to me
yeah yeah it's great well but like
everything with elon is the timeline
seems
insanely fast so that's that's the only
awful question
uh well one we've been talking about
cognition
a little bit so like reasoning
we haven't mentioned the other c word
which is consciousness
uh do you ever think about that one do
is that useful at all
uh in this whole context of
what it takes to create an intelligent
reasoning being
or is that completely outside of uh your
uh
like the engineering perspective uh it
is not outside the realm but it doesn't
on a day-to-day way uh you know basis
inform what we do but it's more so in in
many ways
the company name is connected to this uh
idea of consciousness
what's what's the company name vicarious
you know so vacation is the company name
and uh and so what does victorious mean
right it's
um uh at the first level it is about
modeling the world
and uh and it is internalizing the
external actions
so so you interact with the world and
learn a lot about the world
and now after having learned a lot about
the world
you can run those things in your mind
without actually having to
uh act in the world so you can run uh
things vicariously just in your
in your in your brain and similarly you
can experience
another person's thoughts by you know
having a model of how that person works
and uh and running their you know
putting yourself in some other person's
shoes so that is being vicarious now
it's the same modeling apparatus that
you're using to model the external world
or some other person's thoughts you can
turn it to yourself you can up you know
if that same modeling thing is
applied to your own modeling apparatus
then that is what gives rise to
consciousness i think
well that's more like self-awareness
there's the heart problem of
consciousness which is
like when the model becomes when
when the model feels like something when
this whole process is like
it act it's like you really are
in it you feel like an entity in this
world
not just you know that you're an entity
but it feels like something to be that
entity
it um it you know
and thereby we attribute this you know
then it starts to be wherein something
that has consciousness can suffer
you start to have these kinds of things
that we can reason about that
yes much
much heavier it seems like there's much
greater cost of your
your decisions and like mortality
is tied up into that like the fact that
these things
end right first of all i
end at some point and then other things
end
and you know that that somehow seems to
be
at least for us humans a deep motivator
yes and that you know that that idea of
motivation in general we talk about
goals and ai but right
the goals aren't quite the same thing as
like
the our mortality it feels like
it feels like first of all humans don't
have a goal
and they just kind of create goals at
different levels they like
make up goals because we're
terrified by the mystery of the thing
that
that gets us all so we we
make these goals up so we're like a go
generation
machine as opposed to a machine which
optimizes the trajectory towards a
singular goal
so it feels like that's an important
part of
uh cognition that whole mortality thing
well it is
it is a part of human uh cognition
uh but there is no uh reason
for uh that mortality to
come to the equation for a uh
artificial system because we can uh copy
the artificial system the the
the problem with humans is that we cut i
can't clone you i can't
like you know i can i can close even if
i clone usb
uh you know the hardware your experience
uh that was stored in your brain
uh your uh episodic memory all those
will not be captured in the in the new
clone
um so um but that's not the same with an
ai system
right so but it's also possible
that the the thing that you mentioned
with that with us humans
is actually fundament of fundamental
importance for intelligence so like
the fact that you can copy an ass system
yeah
means that that ai system is not yet an
um
agi so like there it could so if you
look at existence proof
yeah if we reason yeah based on
existence proof would
you could say that it doesn't feel like
death is a fundamental property of an
intelligence system
but we don't yet
give me an example of an immortal
intelligent
being we don't have those it could it's
very possible that
you know that's that is a fundamental
property
of intelligence is a thing that
has a deadline for itself so you can
think of it like this so suppose you
invent a way to freeze people uh for a
long time
it's not dying right yeah uh so so you
can be frozen and woken up
uh thousands of years from now uh so
it's no fear of death
so well no the you're still
it's it's not it's not about time it's
about the knowledge that it's
temporary and the
that aspect of it the finiteness of it
i think um creates a kind of urgency
correct for us for humans yeah for
humans yes
uh and that that is part of our drives
uh
but um and that's why i'm not too
worried about
ai uh you know uh
having motivations to kill all humans
and uh those kinds of things why just
wait
you know so so
why do you need to do that yeah i've
never heard that before that's a good
it's a good point because
yeah just murder seems like a lot of
work we'll just wait
wait it out they'll probably hurt
themselves
let me ask you um people often kind of
wonder
world-class researchers such as yourself
what kind
of books technical fiction philosophical
were
had an impact on you in your life and
maybe ones you could prob possibly
recommend
that others read maybe if you have three
books that pop in the mind
yeah so i definitely liked uh judy
apple's
book uh probabilistic reasoning and
intelligence systems
it's um it's a very deep technical book
but what i liked is that
so there are many uh places where you
can learn about
probabilistic graphical models from but
throughout this book judea pulls
kind of sprinkles his philosophical
observations and
and he thinks about us to how the brain
thinks and attentions and resources
all those things so so that whole thing
makes it
more interesting to read uh he
emphasizes the importance of causality
so that was in his later book so this
was the first book probabilistic
reasoning in interlinked systems he
mentions causality but he hadn't really
sunk his teeth into
like you know how do you actually
formalize that yeah and
uh the second book causality so two
thousand uh
the one in two thousand that one is
really hard so i wouldn't recommend that
uh
uh yes so that looks at the like the
mathematical like
his model of uh calculus do calculus
yeah it was pretty dense mathematically
right
yeah right uh the book of why is
definitely more enjoyable oh for sure
yeah
um so yeah so i would i would recommend
probabilistic reasoning in intelligent
systems
another book i liked uh was uh one from
doug
huff starter uh this is a long time ago
though here's a book he had a book i
think called it was called the mind's
eye it was um uh
probably half starter and daniel dennett
together
uh yeah so and i actually was uh i
i bought that book so much i haven't
read it yet but i
uh i couldn't get an electronic version
of it which is annoying because i'm
you read everything on kindle okay uh
you had to actually purchase the
physical it's like one of the only
physical books i have because yeah
anyway there's a lot of people
recommended it highly so
yeah and the third one uh i would
definitely recommend reading is um
uh this is not a technical book it is
history it's called it's the name of the
book i think is bishop's voice
it's about wright brothers and uh
and their their their path and how
it was uh it's there are multiple books
on this topic
and all of them are great it's um
uh fascinating how a
flight was uh you know treated as an
unsolvable problem
and and and also you know what aspects
did people
emphasize uh you know people thought oh
it is all about
the just powerful engines you know just
need to have powerful lightweight
engines
uh and um so
you know some people thought of it as
how far can we just throw the thing you
know
just throw it yeah catapult yeah so
so it is it's a very fascinating and
even after they
uh made the invention of people not
believing it and
uh uh the social aspect of it this is
the social aspect
it's a different you know very important
do you uh draw any parallels
between you know birds fly
so there's the natural approach to uh to
flight and then there's the engineered
approach
do you um do you see the same kind of
thing with the brain
and are trying to engineer intelligence
yeah it's it's a good analogy to have uh
of course all analogies have their you
know uh yeah
so for sure so people in
uh you know ai often uh use
airplanes as an example of hey we didn't
learn anything from birds look right
there yeah
but the the funny thing is that uh and
and the saying is
uh airplanes don't flap wings yeah right
this is what
they say the funny thing and the ironic
thing is that
that you don't need to flap to fly
is something right brothers found by
observing birds
yeah so they have in their notebook you
know in some of these
books they show their notebook drawings
right they they
make detailed notes about buzzards uh
just
soaring over the thermals and they
basically say
look flapping is not the important
propulsion is not the important problem
to solve here
we want to solve control uh and uh once
you solve control propagation will fall
into place
all of these are people you know they re
realize this by observing birds
beautiful part put that's actually
brilliant uh because people do
use that knowledge a lot i'm gonna have
to remember that one do you have a
advice for people interested in
artificial intelligence like young folks
today i talk to undergraduate students
all the time
uh interested in neuroscience
interesting in
understanding how the brain works is
there advice you would give them
about their career maybe about their
life
in general sure i think every you know
every
piece of advice should be taken with a
pinch of salt of course
because you know each person is
different their motivations are
different
but i can i can definitely say if your
goal is to understand the brain from the
angle of
wanting to build one you know then
uh being an experimental neuroscientist
might not be the way to
go about it um uh it might a better way
to pursue it
might be through computer science
electrical engineering machine learning
and ai
and of course you have to study up the
neuroscience but that you can do on
your own um if you are more
uh attracted by finding something
intriguing about discovering something
intriguing about the brain
then of course it is uh better to be an
experimentalist
so find that motivation what are you
intrigued by and of course find your
strengths too some people
are very good experimentalists uh and
and they
enjoy doing that and essentially to see
which
department if you're if you're picking
in terms of like your education path
whether to um
uh to go with like in mit it's branding
computer uh
no uh bcs
yeah brandon cognitive sciences yeah uh
or or the cs side of things right and
actually uh
the brain folks the neuroscience folks
are more and more
now embracing of uh you know
learning tensorflow by torch right there
they
they see the power of uh trying to
engineer
ideas uh that uh that they get from the
brain
into and then explore how those could be
used to uh
to create intelligent systems so that
might be the right department actually
to uh so this was a question in uh uh
you know one of the
redwood neuroscience institute workshops
or that jeff hawkins organized
almost 10 years ago this question was
put to a panel right what what should be
the undergrad major
you should take if you want to
understand the brain and uh
and the majority opinion that one was
electrical engineering
interesting uh because i mean i'm a
doubly undergrad so i got lucky in that
way
but it i i think it does have some of
the right ingredients because
you learn about circuits you you learn
about
how you can construct circuits to uh you
know approach you know do functions
uh you learn about microprocessors um
you learn information theory you learn
signal processing uh you learn
continuous math
so um so in that way it's it's a good
step
to if you want to go to computer science
or neuroscience you can it's a good step
the downside
you're more likely to be forced to use
matlab
[Laughter]
one of the interesting things about i
mean this is changing the world is
changing but
uh like certain departments lagged on
the programming side of things
on developing good uh good habits as a
software engineering but i think that's
more and more changing
and and students can take that into
their own hands
like learn to program i feel like
everybody
should learn to program because it
uh like everyone in the sciences
because it empowers it puts the data at
your fingertips
so you can organize it you can find all
kinds of things in the data and then you
can also
for the appropriate sciences build
systems that
like based on that so like then engineer
intelligence systems
uh we already talked about mortality so
we hit
no a ridiculous
point but let me ask you the
uh you know
one of the things about intelligence
is it's goal driven and you study the
brain
so the question is like what's the goal
that the brain is operating under what's
what's the meaning of it all for us
humans
in your view what's the meaning of life
the meaning of life is whatever you
construct out of it it's completely open
it's open yeah so there's no there's
nothing uh
uh like you mentioned you like
constraints
what's uh it's it's wide open is there
is there some useful aspect that you
think about
in terms of like the openness of it
and just the basic mechanisms of
generating goals
uh and studying cognition in the brain
that you think about or is it just about
because everything we've talked about
kind of the perception system is to
understand the environment that's like
to be able to like not die exactly
like not fall over and like be able to
uh
you don't think we need to um
think about anything bigger than that
yeah i think so because
it's it's basically being able to
understand the machinery of the world
uh such that you can push you whatever
goals you want right so the machinery of
the world is
is really ultimately what we should be
uh striving to understand the rest is
just
the rest is just whatever the heck you
want to do or whatever whatever is
culturally popular
i think that's i that's beautifully put
i don't think there's a better way to
end it delete i'm so honored that you
you
show up here and waste your time with me
it's been an awesome conversation thanks
so much for talking today oh
thank you so much this was this was so
much more fun than i expected
thank you thanks for listening to this
conversation with the league george
and thank you to our sponsors babel
raycon earbuds
and masterclass please consider
supporting this podcast by
going to babel.com and use codelex going
to buy raycon.com
lex and signing up at masterclass.com
lex click the links get the discount it
really is the best way to support this
podcast
if you enjoy this thing subscribe on
youtube review
five star snap a podcast support it on
patreon i'll connect with me
on twitter alex friedman spelled
yes without the e just f-r-i-d-m-a-n
and now let me leave you with some words
from marcus
aurelius you have power over your mind
not outside events realize this
and you will find strength
thank you for listening and hope to see
you next time
you