the following is a conversation with
brian muirescu author of the immortality
key the secret history of the religion
with no name a book that reconstructs
the forgotten history of psychedelics in
the development of western civilization
to support this podcast please check out
our sponsors
inside tracker give well
ni
indeed and masterclass their links are
in the description
this is the lex friedman podcast and
here's my conversation
with brian murescu
who or what do you think
god is
how is our conception maybe put another
way of god changed throughout history
we're starting with an easy one lex yep
[Laughter]
so what is god well god
is a thought
god is an idea
but it's its reference is to that which
is beyond thinking beyond our ability to
even conceive
um beyond the categories of being and
non-being so how do we talk about that
to talk about it is almost to get it
wrong
right so uh joe campbell famously said
that you know any god that is not
transparent to transcendence is like an
idolatry because it's just a mental
construct
and it can't possibly speak to the
incomprehensible so we use poetic
language we say
the being of beings the um
the infinite
life energy of the universe the the
mystery of transcendence boundless life
unqualified is-ness but it doesn't quite
get to the point i think that if there's
any great insight from mysticism it's
that you and i participate with god
in a very real way lex friedman here in
austin texas that in the here and now to
touch that eternal principle another way
to refer to god to touch that eternal
principle within ourselves
is to participate with with divinity in
some way um so not an external force but
that divine sense within so there's some
aspect in which god is a part of us so
one it's the thing we can't describe
this represents all of the mystery
around us
it's outside our
ability to comprehend and at the same
time it's somehow the thing that's
inside of us
also the ultimate paradox mcfield of
magdeburg 13th century german mystic
maybe the first german mystic um
says that the the day of her spiritual
awakening was the day that she saw and
knew that she saw god in all things and
all things in god and so we can say this
by the way without apology or
lightweight theology or
vapit speculation or even heresy you
know we can we can talk about this
including within the abrahamic faiths
the mystical core of these faiths all
talk about the encounter of divinity
within that's what i explore in the
immortality key that this notion of
techniques
archaic techniques in some cases of
ecstasy that allow that experience of
the eternal principle to actually rise
up in our consciousness
when we're still here as flesh and blood
beings
there's some sense in which our
conception of god though
is conjured up by our own mind
and so
aren't we
creating god
like aren't we the gods
that are creating the idea of god
like if if we are
like when we talk about
god
aren't we playing with ideas that are
created by our
our mind and thereby
we are the creator not god
this is a very kind of
cyclical question but in some sense i
mean
that uh
if god is the thing that represents
the mystery all around us
contrast that with our conception of god
the way we talk about him is more a
creation of our minds it's not the
mystery it's our
uh struggle to comprehend the mystery
and therefore we're creating the god in
terms of the god that we we're talking
about in this conversation or in general
if that makes any sense it makes no
sense whatsoever
but this is this is uh this is the
eternal mystery um
this is why it's so difficult to talk
about and yet it could be the very
center of our beings
you know the upanishads
speak about us as the creators about us
as gods it's a very different creation
myth but the god of the upanishads
in this great verse talks about
pouring themselves
pouring themselves into creation indeed
i have become this creation says god and
there's a great line verily he or she
who knows this becomes in this creation
a creator
so
yeah i mean just our ability to engage
in mentation our ability to to think
about this stuff is partly our divine
nature this is what the humanists were
talking about and in the renaissance by
the way um and that it's not so much
learning putting dots together having
arguments with each other over learned
books it's it's a process of unlearning
is what some of the mystical traditions
talk about
unlearning all these thoughts emotions
traumas and experiences that have gone
into the false construction of our false
self that behind all these layers like
peeling back the onion
is a part of us
that once you can identify that
um begins to look a little bit different
in other words it's one thing to
foster a relationship with god it's a
very different thing to identify as god
and and i mean that quite literally
without being heretical you can you can
find this in the mystery traditions
can you expand on this you mean a human
being can
can embody god
that is um textbook incarnational
theology that you can find in any any
christian mystic um but you can find it
in the mystical tradition of islam and
and judaism as well so rumi for example
the great uh the great sufi mystic talks
about um if you could
get rid of yourself just get rid of
yourself just once the secret of secrets
would open to you that the face of the
unknown would appear on the perception
of your consciousness
rabbi lawrence kushner a modern-day
contemporary mystic
talks about uh because this stuff does
continue there's a continuity the poetry
here is incredible so well listen listen
to rabbi kushner he says that the
emptying of selfhood
allows the soul to attach to true
reality and in kabulism the true reality
is what's called the divine nothingness
i yin and so i like the adage that um
and mystics both essentially believe in
nothing
except that the mystics spell it with a
capital n
the divine nothing yeah and then i'll
give you meister eckhart
another medieval christian mystic he
says that
if you could not yourself right the same
concept if you could not yourself for
just an instant indeed i say less than
an instant you would possess all so
again you're seeing the same thing in
sufism
kabbalism christian mysticism the way to
identify with the divine is to peel back
these layers and attempt to discover
pure awareness
if we look at the universe from a
physics perspective or you know i'm a
computer science person so if the
universe is a
is a computer
there's some sense that
god
the creator of the universe or just the
computer itself
doesn't know what the heck is going to
happen
it just kind of creates some basic rules
and runs the thing
so there is some element in which
you can conceive of humans or conscious
beings or intelligent beings
as uh
as a tool
that the creator uses to understand
itself himself
do you uh do you think that's
a perspective that uh we could or is
useful to take on god that
is basically
the universe created humans to
understand itself
he doesn't actually know the full thing
he needs the human brains to figure out
the puzzle so that's in contrasting to
the unlearning to getting out of the way
that we've talked about it's more like
no we need the humans to figure out this
puzzle well we have no answers to this
which is why philosophers still have
jobs if they have jobs at all but i mean
they're so the physicists take a look at
this um have you seen the article that
came out i think it was this month in
the journal of cosmology and
astroparticle physics um uh robert lanza
the biocentrism theory the idea that the
universe comes into being through our
observation right the whole the god
equation so not just in quantum
mechanics but in general relativity the
idea that that we make the universe
moment by moment which is kind of
mind-blowing gets into ideas of
simulation
okay so that's how the physicists at
least some of them might look at it you
could also look back to the medieval
christian mystics
meister eckhart once again says that the
i with which i see god is the same eye
that sees me right so one sight
one knowledge
one love um
another mind-blowing concept but this is
this is why the arts and poetry and
music are so important because although
i love astroparticle physics
it's another to kind of hear this
the same message um across time
yeah the simulation thing
i was actually looking this morning at
video games just the statistics on video
games and i saw that the two top video
games in terms of hours played
is fortnite and world of warcraft and i
saw that it's 140 billion hours
billion hours have been played at those
games
that's a lot of video games
yeah but that that's very sophisticated
worlds being created especially in the
world of warcraft it's a massive online
role-playing game so you have these
characters that are together sort of
creating a world but they in themselves
they're also developing they have all
these items and they're growing like
they're little humans like there's
complicated societies that are formed
they have goals they're striving and so
on
and it's we're creating a universe
within our universe and for now it's a
kind of um
it's a basic sort of constrained version
of our more richer earth like
civilization but it's conceivable that
you know that
we are this thing on earth is a kind of
video game that somebody else is playing
it's like you could see sort of video
games upon video games being created
that uh and this is something i think a
lot about not from a philosophical
perspective but practically how fun does
this video game have to be
for us to let go of the
silly pursuits in this meet space that
we live in and fully
just stay in wow stay in world of
warcraft stay in the video game for full
time so i think about that from an
engineering perspective like is there
going to be a time when this video game
is actual real life for us and then the
creatures inside the video game
they'll be just borrowing our
consciousness
for sort of to ground themselves will
refer to us as the gods
right like won't we become the gods
this conversation is not going how i
expected but i think about this a lot
from you know because i love video games
and i wonder
more and more of us especially in covet
times of living in the digital world you
could think about twitter and all those
kinds of things you could think about
clubhouse people using just voices to
communicate with little icons sort of in
the digital space you can see more and
more will be moving in the digital space
and let go of this physical space
and then the the remnants
of the the ancients that created the
video games that nobody
centuries from now will even remember
those will be the gods and then there'll
be gods upon gods being created
this is the kind of stuff i think about
but is that any at all useful to you
to this thought experiment of a
simulation basically the fabric of our
reality how did it come to be what is
running this thing is that useful or is
it ultimately
the project of understanding god
of understanding myth
is the project that centers on the human
on the human mind for you
we seem to be at the center of this
divine dance which which sounds awfully
anthropocentric
but
the ancients thought about this too i
mean the concept and sanskrit of lila
that the point behind the existence is
this play right it's ultimately playful
this divine dance
it gets awfully complicated in the
gnostic and neoplatonic schools these
chains of being from godhead down to us
right
some invisible right
and we're going to get into terence
mckenna territory later on but we can
start now by talking about discarnate
entities and archons and aliens and
archetypes i mean there is a a world
where terrence mckenna does meet plato
and gnosticism um quite kindly and that
that's in the um this invisible college
right the um
the invisible world uh with which we
seem to have some kind of symbiosis
um that has a higher intent maybe even a
purpose or a plan in mind for us so i
mean these ideas come across when you've
had a heroic dose of mushrooms um they
also pop up in the ancient philosophical
literature this idea of archons who you
know
the puppet masters controlling us flesh
and blood beings
it's all uh it's all a cosmic dance and
there are no answers to this first who
are the archons the second what is this
world where transformative means
play-doh do you mean in the space of
ideas
or are we talking about some kind of
world that connects all of consciousness
throughout human history i think through
different techniques it is you know i
think a lot about i think gordon wassen
is the meeting point of the two so so
gordon watson who i do talk about in the
book uh was this um jp morgan banker
turned ethnomycologist and he's largely
credited with the rediscovery
of psilocybin containing mushrooms
which kind of gave rise to the pop
psychedelic revolution of the 1960s
he visited maria sabina down in mexico
in his wake when bob dylan led zeppelin
the stones and everybody else
and the way he describes his psilocybin
experience
is a bit strange because he thinks of
plato right
and he says that you know whereas our
ordinary reality is kind of this
imperfect view of things
gordon watson felt that on mushrooms he
was spying the archetypes and he talks
about plato and he writes about the
archetypes in this famous article that's
released in 1957 in life magazine and so
a well-read
individual from the mid-20th century has
his
premier psychedelic experience and
outcomes plato because what he was
witnessing was so sharp so brilliant so
detailed
in some sense more real than real this
noetic sense that william james talks
about that when you confront something
more real than real these discarnate
entities these images
this uh these visionary motifs you're
tempted
to believe that you've tapped into the
truest nature and the underlying
structure of the cosmos and that's
difficult to escape from whether you're
plato or terence mckenna or gordon
watson caught in between
so we talk about this
being in touch with something that is
more real than real
and let's just go straight there to
mckenna before we return to the bigger
picture so he's talked about the uh what
is it self-healing machina self
self-transforming self-transforming
machine i was during his uh
dmt
travels
and uh i just talked to rick doblin who
also had different travels through this
hyperspace
but they're all seem to be traveling on
the same spaceships just to different
locations and there is a sense in which
they seem to be traveling
through whatever i don't know if it's
through space time or something else to
meet
something that is more real than real uh
what can you say about this dmt
experience about terence mckenna about
the poetry he used but maybe more
specifically about this place that they
seem to all travel to
so the big question is is it real is it
really more real than real the ancient
philosophers were asking the same
question and their means of attempting
to answer that was by dying
so if you ask plato the definition of
philosophy he will say that
to practice it in the right way
is to practice dying and being dead and
many people describe the psychedelic
experience in sort of near-death
experience terms
um and the encountering of all this
visual imagery tends to be something
that is often described as more real
than real so how does terence talk about
this so i was just listening to the
trial logs which folks should look up um
somewhere between 1989 and 1990 terence
sits down
with his friends ralph abraham and
rupert sheldrake at esalen and they're
they're trying to figure out the meaning
of these discarnate entities and these
non-human intelligences
and terence develops a taxonomy for how
to analyze this and he says that number
one
they're either
um semi-physical
but kind of elusive so think of the
bigfoot or the yeti or things like this
um beings that exist somewhere between
mythology and zoology
which is isn't really appropriate here
so so uh option number two
he says is the mental i'm sorry
you're dropping so many good lines it's
so good okay i apologize
[Laughter]
somewhere between nostalgia and zouave
this is all terence mckenna okay all
right i take no credit for this uh so
but you're combining you're like uh jimi
hendrix only used the blues scale but
he's still uh he still created something
new in the music you played anyway go
ahead well we're going into mixolydian
right now okay so um
uh so uh option number two and this is
this what this is what uh terence calls
sort of the mentalist reductionist
approach
um and this is this is pure mechanical
poetry he says that these beings could
be autonomous fragments of psychic
energy that have temporarily escaped the
controlling power of the ego
um so in jungian senses these would just
be pure projections um the projections
of schizophrenics in some cases so
they're essentially unreal and the third
option the most tantalizing
is that they're both non-physical but
autonomous in other words they actually
exist
in some kind of real place
in some kind of real space and that we
can have congress with them there is
communication he talks about um the
whisperings of the demon artificers and
that it's just possible
that our meetings with these beings have
coaxed the human species
into self-expression in a very real way
that at different times in history our
relationships with these
semi-autonomous beings may actually
guide the species now this is
high speculation and uh terence and
ralph and rupert wind up talking about
the early modern period and the
scientific enlightenment and that even
someone like descartes reports a dream
in which he came face to face with an
angel who said that the conquest of
nature
is to be achieved
uh through measure and number so so even
the hard-minded materialist like like
descartes is confronting these
discarnate entities john d in the 16th
century the high magician of the
elizabethan court
he reports decades worth of what we
would say is extraterrestrial
communication or interdimensional
communication
um and you can find instances of this
throughout history including among the
pre-socratics um and peter kingsley
writes quite a bit about this but i'll
save that until your next question well
first of all we don't seem to understand
from where intelligence came from we
don't understand
from where life came from on earth
but that we can kind of into it because
that's the space of chemistry and
biology you have good theories about the
origins of life on earth but the origins
of intelligent life
that is is a giant mystery and
there's some sense in which
i mean i don't know if you know the
movie 2001 space odyssey
but
it does seem that there is like
important
throughout human history throughout life
on earth there's important phase shifts
of
it feels like something happened
where there's big leaps
it could be something coincidental like
fire and learning how to cook meat and
all those kinds of things
but it feels like there could be other
things and i think that's at the core of
your work is exploring what those things
could be
is there is it
possible talked about joe rogan offline
is it
it's entirely possible is it possible
that psychedelics have in fact
contributed
of being an important uh source of those
phase shifts throughout human history of
the intel basically steering the
intellectual development and growth of
human civilization
it's a hypothesis worth investigating
how about that beautiful and
and maybe not psychedelics in and of
themselves but i think our whole
conversation is kind of wrapped up in
these
non-ordinary states of awareness we
start by talking about god which is
something
unordinary and expansive and i think
that as you
as you trace the intervention of
divinity if that's the case
throughout human history you have to
bump up against the irrational um
mercedes the great scholar
of religions and fellow romanian said
that the history of religions
essentially constitutes the point of
intersection between metaphysics and
biology
right so that we are biological beings
who do interact with our planet with the
with the natural kingdom
and you would think that as you know
early archaic ecologists we would have
figured out what plants work which fungi
don't
and developed maybe language around that
and so this is this is another one of
mckenna's
speculative but very interesting
hypotheses the stoned ape theory
is it is it possible that psychedelics
were involved in one of the several
leaps forward you mentioned the word
leap
jared diamond talks about the great leap
forward 60 000 years ago
the species had been around for a couple
hundred thousand years all of a sudden
the cave painting appears
all of a sudden there's a phase shift
did something like that happen millions
of years ago and i love the way paul
stamets talks about this it would be the
ingestion
of perhaps psilocybin containing fungi
millions and millions of times
over millions and millions of years so
it's not just a one-time event that
cascades but it's this it's the
accumulation of psychedelic experience
that it's really difficult to test that
hypothesis
but i've been talking with a
paleoanthropologist in south africa my
friend lee berger
about ways that we might test for this
and so lee amongst many things is this
national geographic explorer
he's the paleoanthropologist
paleoanthropologist at the university of
waterstrength
he's famous amongst other things for the
discovery of previously undiscovered
hominids like homo naledi
and there's an interesting point
um so naledi
is
this archaic hominid morphologically
archaic but it dates to about 300 000
years ago
which is very strange um what's even
more strange about homo naledi at the
rising star cave system there in south
africa is that lee believes he's
discovered the first bipedal ape
deliberately disposing of its dead
um so there is a recognition of
self-mortality
and the practicing of rituals around
death we're talking about burials and if
you have burials says lee in an archaic
hominid 300 000 years ago maybe you have
language and i mentioned that because
terence mckenna was obsessed with
language in the stone dape theory that
the ingestion of psilocybin in addition
to enhancing visual acuity perhaps
facilitating sexual arousal
leads to proto-language
now isn't it interesting this could be
entirely a coincidence
that the largest sound inventory of any
language is the koi-san
of botswana and namibia
they have something like 164 consonants
and 44 vowels english by comparison has
about 45. so i don't know what to make
of this but what you find in that part
of the world is very
very complex language
language that could be an inheritance
language that could be incredibly
archaic together with this recognition
of self-mortality and when i talk to lee
berger we say when you're looking at
universals like that language around all
human populations the recognition of
self-mortality the contemplation of
death just maybe you have pharmacology
and so maybe we can go out and test for
this
using gas chromatography mass
spectrometry proteomics technology that
doesn't even exist but maybe we can
actually test the stone tape theory to
figure out once and for all if there's
any merit there can you just linger a
little bit on the pharmacology tools
like how how would you how would it be
possible to say something about what was
being ingested so so so long ago that's
what i asked dr berger
so lee
has discovered um in the dental calculus
nice of archaic hominids dental calculus
i like that
evidence of their diet and
you might not believe how old this was
but in in sediba australopithecus sediba
they found evidence of sadiba's diet
going back 2 million years
so through things like phytoliths which
are essentially
fossilized plant tissue they found
evidence that sediba was eating bark and
leaves and grasses and fruits and palm
so no psychedelics to speak of but it
just goes to show that through things
like dental microwave analysis and other
techniques that we're still developing
we can actually figure out what the diet
was at the time i'll fast forward to 50
000 years ago
there was another study out of el cidron
cave in 2012 which found that
neanderthals again preceding our species
50 000 years ago
were ingesting yarrow and chamomile
which had been identified as medicinal
so again not psychedelic or psychoactive
but we kind of have the beginnings of
the technology and this that was nine
years ago to begin figuring out the
ancestral diet of these hominids
presumably there could be a way to
figure out it's not just diet but which
are have psychoactive elements to them
so whether you're chewing it whether
you're smoking it whether i mean i don't
know what licking it i don't know if
there's any kind of ways through the
dental calculus to figure out
which exact substances were being
consumed
is it possible to figure out whether
psychedelic substances are being
consumed by looking at human behavior
like you said organized burials
or cave paintings
no but so that's a little bit of a
stretch to say like where did the sleep
come from but it's not it's not so so so
just last fall as a matter of fact so
that that notion has been out there for
a while the idea that hallucinogens and
the ritual consumption of hallucinogens
were somehow related to the great leap
forward or somehow related to the
initial cape pain and graham hancock
wrote a beautiful book about this called
supernatural which in many ways like
sent me down this rabbit hole back in
2007. and so but even at the time when
he was writing that in the year
subsequent
it was still kind of seen as a kooky
idea
last fall
interestingly enough
the first archaeochemical data for the
ritual consumption
of psychedelics associated with cave art
was finally published it's it's not that
ancient it's only about four or five
hundred years ago but it came from the
pinwheel cave a chumash site in in
california and what they found were
datura quids like these chewed up you
mentioned how did they ingest it these
chewed up quids like these these bunches
of datura which contain these very
powerful tropane alkaloids and what was
believed to be some kind of chumash
initiation site so we can say that there
is initial
you know archaeochemical data for the
consumption of psychedelics and cave art
and so where else might we find this
are there a lot of archaeochemists in
the world
like because this is fascinating it's
through chemistry
through biology through physics whatever
like all the disciplines we perhaps one
day computer science
we um
apply those tools to study not the data
of today but the data of the past
are we talking about dozens here
like how hard is this problem relative
to how many people are taking it on just
as a side a little tangent we're
probably talking
more dozens than hundreds um i
spent many years trying to track down an
archaeochemist who would talk to me
there were a couple um pat mcgovern at
the university of pennsylvania yeah and
then my friend andrew ko at mit which
you might know something about um andrew
really you know on his own time on his
own dime
has been gathering the data
for this organic residue analysis um he
has what's called the open r chem
project which is this online open source
repository for this data but there's
never been a center for this no
university has stood up a dedicated
center a team really which is what you
need
of archaeochemists looking at this stuff
but i mean even despite that there have
been some remarkable discoveries
over the past 10 20 years it's still a
discipline very much in its infancy
maybe it's becoming a toddler but as the
technology gets better and cheaper um i
hope uh you'll see more and more
archaeochemists
joining the fight yeah and andrew is
fascinating his work is fascinating but
uh also i just because of because of
your work i came across an exchange a
few emails with patrick mcgovern
who's basically what would you call him
so he has a center i guess that's
does biomolecular archaeology at upenn
and
he's the author of a bunch of books one
of which is ancient bruise
so he's a scholar of beer and wine
and like ancient alcohol which is
fascinating they influence even just
alcohol but he has like
alcohol with um
hallucinogenic properties as well but
it's fascinating the influ as a russian
it's fascinating to uh
to think about the influence of alcohol
on the development
of human civilization throughout its
history is this is there something you
can comment on
alcohol or in general
patrick's work that was informative to
you inspiring or kind of
added to your conception of of human
history his work was some of the first
hard scientific data that i saw for the
ritual consumption of these intoxicants
um i don't think he's ever found
the hard and fast data for for
psychedelics but what he turned me on to
was this idea
that alcohol or beer and wine
specifically
could have been used as vehicles for the
administration of psychedelics that's
where it all started for me um just just
the notion that ancient beer and ancient
wine is very very different from what we
drink today that typically they were
cocktails they were often fortified and
mixed with different fruits berries
herbs plants maybe even fungi over time
because this was all in the absence of
distilled liquor right there is no hard
alcohol even in russia
before
maybe the 12th century it was in europe
maybe a bit earlier but the the concept
of distillation just didn't exist and so
you know to pack a punch um
you know rather than just drink a kind
of watered-down budweiser these people
were interested in fortifying these
beverages with whatever they could find
in nature and and pat to his credit
found some of the initial data for these
um you could say spiked wines and spiked
beers not with anything overtly
psychedelic but just the fact that in
the 16th century bc at grave circle a in
my senai there's this minoan ritual
cocktail of beer mixed with wine mixed
with mead is very interesting it's even
more interesting that you find that
across the aegean um in gordium at king
midas tomb right the same kind of ritual
cocktail which pat and sam at the
dogfish head brewery uh resurrected as
the midas touch so i mean the notion
that we can go back find this data
resurrect it in some cases 2 800 years
later i found pretty exciting 10 years
ago
yeah bringing back for research
but that's that's fascinating that
people were playing with these ideas and
we'll return to
we'll return to ideas of psychedelic
confused wine which is pretty
fascinating but can we step back and
just kind of look at your work with the
the book immortality key
what is the story that you tell in this
book i knew we'd get there eventually
lex
it's a non-linear path
somehow we were talking about simulation
and the universe is a computer that's
creating video games and wow and uh
fortnite but
we got there and we'll return
always to insane philosophical but uh
your book can mortality what what's the
story that you tell in this book
what do you which part of human history
are you studying
right so that's that's the way to phrase
it so it's you know it's my 12-year
search
for the hard scientific data
for the ritual use of psychedelics and
classical antiquity so we're talking
about amongst the ancient greeks and
romans
and the paleo christians
so the generations that would give birth
to the largest religion the world's ever
known christianity today was two and a
half billion people the big question for
me is you know were psychedelics
actually involved there was a lot
written about this in the 60s john marco
allegro
the book that i follow was published in
1978 before i was born the road to
ellucis
by gordon watson who we talked about
already albert hofmann who famously
discovers lsd or synthesizes it from
ergot and karl ruck
who is still a professor of classics at
boston university the only surviving
member of that renegade trio and now 85
years old so this this all predates us
um but what was lacking in the 60s 70s
80s 90s i think was some of this
technology
and and the hard scientific data now for
years and years i went out to the
archaeobotanists and the archaeochemists
around the world and i asked a very
basic question is there any evidence
for psychedelics and classical antiquity
and the answer would almost invariably
come back no i'm talking to in addition
to pat he put me in touch with hans
peter stika in germany tania valamotti
in greece
florenzano in italy i went all over the
place asking one question and getting
the same answer back time and again and
so the book is essentially my my search
for that data and the eventual
uncovering of two what i think are key
pieces of data one data
one data point
shows the ritual use of a psychedelic
beer
in classical antiquity in iberia with
today's spain and the other shows what
looks like a kind of psychedelic wine
just outside pompeii from the first
century a.d at the right place at the
right time when the earliest christians
were showing up in italy
again these are early steps in the
search for evidence in the space but uh
speaking of early christians
what role do you think
psychedelic infused wine could have
played
in the life of
the
i i won't be clever in the life of jesus
christ
i've been saying recently that and i
hope this doesn't sound
obscurantist but
i think it's impossible
to understand jesus
and the birth of christianity in the
absence of ancient greek
and i'll give you a very specific
example of why i think that's the case
you can read the entire new testament
in ancient greek and not once will you
ever find a reference to alcohol
because there was no word in ancient
greek for alcohol the way the word
sounds alcohol it comes it's semitic it
comes from the arabic
khala means to enliven a refresh it
probably comes from coal kohl sort of
these powdered metallics that were used
in alchemical experiments and cosmetics
so again that's much later in time
when we're using alchemy distillation
etc in the first century ad
the power of wine wasn't necessarily
tied to alcohol right fermented grapes
the way we think about wine today so pat
mcgovern found some of that early
organic data for wine being mixed
with uh
with beer and with mead but if you look
at the literature from the first century
a.d diocerities for example he writes
this this massive treatise at the exact
same time the gospels are being written
and diascorides
in just one of his books talks about 56
detailed recipes
for spiking wine with all kinds of
things like salvia and hellebore and
frankincense and myrrh these spiced
perfumes but also more dangerous things
like henbane and mandrake which he says
in greek can be fatal with just one
cupful and in book 474 of his materia
medica
he talks about black nightshade
producing fantasias
none not unpleasant visions
what today we would say is psychedelic
so just looking at the literature and
the kind of literature that even most
classicists i didn't really learn it in
undergrad i came across diasporities
later um
just a basic look at the literature
supports what mcgovern has been testing
which is the fact that wine was
routinely mixed with different compounds
it's fascinating by the way that
language affects our
conception
of the tools we use to understand the
world so like
like it you can see wine
you can see psychedelics
if they're not
called drugs
you can uh
you can maybe reframe
how you see them in terms of their role
in on us thinking about the world
understanding the world that's really
interesting that language has that power
but what language was used to understand
wine at the time so we're talking about
a greek speaking world right so you know
jesus
uh is born and does his public ministry
in the holy land but think about the
early church think about where the
church takes root you know paul the
greatest evangelist of the time writes
basically half the new testament he's
writing letters in greek to greek
speakers in places like corinth
in greece
or philippi a defunct city just north of
the island of thaus or he's writing to
folks in what today is is turkey uh the
colossians the galatians he writes
letters to the romans um these are greek
speakers in these pockets these hellenic
pockets all around the ancient
mediterranean and for them again
ignore discordies ignore pat mcgovern's
work to them to think about wine was to
think about a mixed a mixed potion and
so the word oinos in ancient greek does
show up in the new testament but there
was another word to describe wine and it
exists for like a thousand years before
during and after the life of jesus the
word used for wine is farmacon which
obviously gives us the word pharmacy it
means drug
so in greek a greek speaker would
actually use the word drug
to refer to wine uh ruth skodal the
classicist talks about this as a as a
ritualistic formula um they understood
wine
as this compound beverage a drug against
grief um a medicinal elixir
that could either harm or heal or just
maybe a sacrament to put you in touch
with wine gods old and new
clearly
religion
and myth but
religion very much so has
sort of uh
much like dreams has like an imagery
component like
you're kind of going outside
the
visual constraints of physical space
where you kind of have
very specific conceptions of what things
look like and you kind of use your
imagination to
stretch beyond the world as we know it
things that are
try to get in touch with things that are
more real than real
what role do these tools
do these
uh farmicons
have in trying to stimulate the imagery
of religion like
do you have a sense that they have a
critical role here or is this just a
bunch of different factors
that are utilized a bunch of different
tools that are utilized to construct
this imagery or is this not even or is
imagery the wrong terminology is it more
like space of ideas that's core to to
religion no i think the wine is
absolutely essential and so if it's
impossible to understand paleo
christianity in the absence of ancient
greek i think it's equally difficult in
the absence of
the sacred pharmacopoeia or wine itself
right just think about wine
at the time um i i think that the
ancient greek audience would have heard
that in a very different way um from us
and so they're referring to it maybe as
a pharmacon but the followers of
dionysus which precedes jesus and in
some cases
the story of jesus is kind of a
recapitulation of the mysteries of
dionysus but when you think about
dionysus
maybe from your high school mythology
you think about him as the god of
theater or the god of wine which is
typically what it is or the god of
ecstasy
you know again dionysus is not the god
of alcohol there's no there's no concept
of of fermented grapes the power of
dionysus and the ability to commune with
dionysus through his blood
and before christianity the blood
of dionysus is equated to his wine the
sacramental drinking of the wine was
interpreted and classicist write about
this including walter berkert
it was interpreted as consuming the god
himself in order to become one with the
god this is where we get the idea of
enthusiasm because the language matters
enthusiasm to be filled with the spirit
of the god so that you became identified
with dionysus and acquired his divine
powers now how does that happen
again he's not the god of alcohol he is
the god of wine but he's really the god
of madness and delirium
and frenzy and his principal followers
are women they're called the mine ads
and the way they get in touch with him
is through the consumption of the
sacramental wine
even at the theater of dionysus
separate from his outdoor churches there
was a wine served there called drima
and this is the wine that gives birth to
hollywood i mean the ancient hollywood
was there at the theater of dionysus
this is where comedy and tragedy and
poetry and music come from
but rather than a hot dog and a beer
what they drink at the theater of
dionysus was this wine called trima
which means pounded or rubbed and
professor ruck talks about maybe it was
the drugs that were rubbed into this
theatrical beverage
to help
uh the play come alive so madness is
seen as a positive thing is it like a
creative journey
it's not it's not uh
it's it's the what is it the unlearning
getting out of the way kind of thing
is is that how it seen or is it more
like um
entertaining
escape
from life that is suffering
okay i gotta i gotta inject a little
modern dostoevsky into the old
despair um maybe it's maybe it's a bit
of that
we we can't say that there wasn't
recreational drinking happening um the
greeks also have the symposium right um
and they also were just getting hammered
in some cases yeah but when it comes to
the rights of dionysus yeah what you see
there is um
the creation
of these states of awareness in which
again you identify with the god to
become the god there's there's theophagy
there's the consumption of divinity in
order to become divinity right back to
how we started the conversation right so
if we stop conceiving of god as
something exterior to us but that the
mystery
of being itself is the mystery of your
being and the mystery of my being that
the way to encounter that is through the
sacramental theology that you drink
the actual blood of this greek god to
become
that god and there was a place for this
in ancient greek society so drinking the
wine and drinking the blood of dionysus
do you think jesus
is
an actual physical person that existed
in history or is he an idea
that
came to to life through the consumption
of wine and those kinds of rituals so
this is where i faced my ex
communication depending how i answer
this
[Laughter]
i mean you're you're playing with fire
and wine
[Laughter]
that's a good combination by the way
yeah
uh so
i i shy away from that controversy in
the book i'm perfectly willing to accept
jesus as a historical personage um you
know we have the multiplicity of sources
although it's a generation after his
death um but we have the eucharist being
described in the four gospels we have it
being described by paul
in first corinthians
but when you read john it does read a
bit differently than the other gospels
and in my book i rely a lot on the
scholarship of dennis mcdonald who
writes a fabulous book called the
dionysian gospel
and this is again why the greek matters
because once you start to analyze the
greek of john's gospel
it seems to be a presentation of jesus
very much in the guise of dionysus the
most obvious example is the wedding at
cana right
that only occurs in john's gospel the
famous transformation of water into wine
now again to any greek speaker of the
first century they would have known
about the greek district of ellis on the
peloponnese
and in ellis around the epiphany every
january the priests of dionysus would
deposit these water basins empty basins
in the temple of dionysus they'd return
the next morning
and find them magically filled with wine
now on the island of andros it's even
more interesting around the same
epiphany date the gods gift day
dies theodosia the wine would emanate
from the temple and run like a river
for a week and you can google the
baccanal of the andreans a wonderful
painting by titian which hangs in the
prado and you'll see a river of wine
behind these people having a great time
this exists for centuries and centuries
before the wedding at cana and before
jesus begins his public ministry with
what these scholars call the signature
miracle of dionysus it would not have
been lost on the greek audience that
that something very specific is being
communicated here what's being
communicated
that you just might find in early
christianity
what you hold strong to in these
mysteries of dionysus that you may have
inherited from your parents your
grandparents your great grandparents for
centuries there was a perfectly good
religion there were perfectly good
mystery cults in the ancient greek and
roman worlds and here comes this new
untested illegal cult
illegal of a dozen or so illiterate day
laborers that go on to convert the
empire in a few hundred years
the answer to that
extraordinary growth is not psychedelics
but i do think it's visionary
experiences and i do think it's this
continuity from the pagan world into
early christianity so what part you
mentioned this idea that's really
interesting though i i think you said
paul stamets
of
i guess millions of people over millions
of years
kind of uh consuming
really practicing a ritual or a habit of
some sort this idea of rituals is kind
of interesting
again you mentioned cult
what's the role of ritual consumption of
some of these substances or just ritual
practice of anything in um the
intellectual growth of
particular groups of people or societies
so again i would say it is the the
centerpiece of ancient life not just the
mysteries of dionysus
uh which we've only talked a bit about
but the mysteries of ellucis were
probably the most famous
and longest lasting of these greek
mystery rites and i mean just to put it
in simple terms the best definition for
a mystery religion um as the name
implies is something secret
all right muo from the greek means to
shut the eyes or or to shut the mouth up
to keep quiet about this stuff um you
know we're always teasing details
from the archaeological and the literary
record and we're kind of just
grabbing at these at these secrets but
ellucis which survives for like 2000
years into the christian period from
about 1500 bc to the 4th century a.d
it's kind of this this centerpiece of
greek life cicero the great roman
statesman calls what was happening at a
lucius
the most exceptional and divine thing
that athens ever produced so not
democracy the arts and sciences or
philosophy but the vision
that was encountered atalusis perhaps
through the ritual consumption of a
potent psychedelic over hundreds and
hundreds of years thousands and
thousands if not millions of initiates
pilgrims who would walk from athens to
ellucis to encounter this vision
it seems to have been
not just an important part of greek life
but the thing that made life livable
such that as these mysteries are about
to be exterminated by the newly
christianized roman empire there's this
passage in the ancient literature that
talks about these you know in the
absence of these mysteries life becomes
unlivable abigail
is there ways you can i mean you write
about the mysteries of ulysses and is
there ways you can convert that into
words
why those are so important
to them
more important than any other invention
to them why is it such a source of
meaning to life
so from what we can reconstruct
they would make that pilgrimage 13 miles
northwest of athens to confront their
mortality remember we were talking about
homo naledi and in south africa this
recognition of self-mortality
the deliberate disposal of the dead um
plato talks about the the real practice
of philosophy being the the death and
dying process so
in in some senses you went to elusive to
die
and to experience a a death before your
death we talked about this with with
terence mckenna as well and this the how
the psychedelic state
seems to share something in common with
the near-death or out-of-body
experiences or these ecstatic
experiences whether through wine or beer
or otherwise you went to ellucis to die
um and it was said that only those who
had witnessed this vision whatever
vision was to be witnessed and endemic
or sanctuary
it essentially vouch safe to uh the
afterlife that only those who went there
became immortal um and cicero says that
um you know at that point you
essentially live
with more joy and die with a better hope
can i ask you a question about this uh
human contention with death this uh
confrontation of death
that seems to be at the core of things i
i don't know how deep to the core
but um
it seems to be a central element of the
human condition what do you think about
ernest becker
and those guys that put
put death at the what is it the warm at
the core
which uh
as the main thing
the the main create like this
confrontation of our own mortality first
of all being understand that we're
mortal and then confronting the terror
of it the the fear of it
as the creator like trying to escape the
fear of death as the creative force
of human society it's like the reason we
do anything is because we're just
running away from our death
scared
uh do you find
some of that to be true first of all as
a
somebody who looks in the mirror looks
at yourself and your own as a human
being two just looking at society today
and three at this whole big s spread of
human history and all the cool stuff
we've created including the mysteries of
elusive
i wonder what life would look like in
the absence of the fear of our mortality
i wonder
how we'd interact with one another
if there was relatively little or no
fear of death i really do when it comes
to becker's work and others um if the
ancients were known for anything it was
running to death
it was the opposite in fact dying before
dying which is the immortality key by
the way it's not psychedelic's point
when i when i refer to this key i'm
referring to this notion that's
preserved in greek
if you die before you die
you won't die when you die
for some reason
the ancients prized
that experience and we talked about the
mystics of of sufism and kabbalism and
christian mysticism
where you have this the same self
nodding this death before death the
divine nothingness right for some reason
the mystic saints visionaries and
ancient philosophers they ran to death
and the one message i wanted to try and
communicate with this book is how they
viewed life
that it can only be fully experienced
fully embodied
in the wake
of a really intense
perhaps terrifying
but utterly transformational encounter
with death
so running to death not running away
from death you talk about aldous huxley
and mind changers
so if we look at the history
where
the ancients were running to death and
maybe using some uh
uh performance enhancing permacons
[Laughter]
to run more effectively
towards death and now we're using
like um
tools
of modern society whether they're
psychological sociological or
pharmaceutical to run away from this
conception so where
uh what do you see as a hopeful future
for human civilization like which um
if all of these kinds of
uh societies or ice cream flavors how do
you create the perfect ice cream flavor
like what is the future of religious
experience of psychedelic experience of
intellectual journeys of uh facing death
running away from death
what do you hope
uh that looks like and
what kind of ideas should we look to my
next book will be entitled performance
enhancing pharmaka
you get
yeah yeah i like it so
uh so but that's that's a historical
view i mean what's what in that book
would you suggest in one of the last
chapters about
the the future of this um
of this process well hux huxley has to
stop you in he stopped me in my tracks
aldous huxley
so in in 1958 he he pens this this op-ed
of sorts um
and it's just it reads incredibly
prescient
um because i really do think in many
ways as the fog of the war drug is
ending
and finally lifting
that we we've kind of come full circle
back to
the late 1950s which might sound strange
um it'll make more sense when you hear
what huxley said about psychedelics and
so
he was looking forward to a revival of
religion
which is why i subtitled the book the
religion with no name
and and to him
to huxley this this this revival
wouldn't come about through
televangelistic mass meetings or
photogenic clergymen as he says but he
points to the biochemical discoveries
such as we have today that would allow
for large numbers of men and women to
achieve a radical self-transcendence and
a deeper understanding of the nature of
things in other words that this revival
religion he says would be a revolution
and alan watts comes along and says that
there's there's nothing more
um
dangerous to authority than a popular
outbreak of mysticism but i think
this is what huxley was pointing to and
he talks about religion in these terms
about being less about symbols and
returning to a sense of experience and
intuition
and huxley says that he envisions a
religion
which gives rise to everyday mysticism
and he talks about something that would
undergird everyday rationality everyday
tasks and duties and everyday human
relationships in other words religion
has to mean something
and these
these altered states of awareness that
we seem to be able to produce
quite easily inside the lab at hopkins
nyu and elsewhere with psilocybin
i i think this is kind of
part of huxley's prediction about a time
when we would have legal access safe
access efficacious access to this
material that would allow for
insight in an afternoon and what do you
do
when millions of people can become
mystics in an afternoon
so um psychedelics psilocybin
might be so the
the practical way of having these kinds
of
maybe could be termed religious
experiences
and then many people partaking in those
experiences and then like evolving this
collective intelligence thing we got
going on
that's the that's sort of the practice
of religion that we should be looking
striving for as opposed to kind of um
operating in the space of ideas actually
practicing it
um you you mentioned
and that's the religion with no name
the use of these tools
is there a simple way to summarize
religion for our previous discussion
about god basically discovering the god
inside
what if i give you a very complicated
definition of religion and then we talk
about a more simplified
let's do it so the the most complicated
we can get on this is is the
anthropologist clifford geertz but i
think it's worth defining our terms um
when we're talking about god and
religion so religion religio from the
latin means to bind back so to bind us
back to some meaningful tradition to
bind us back to the source
here's a mouthful from clifford geertz
you know religion he defines as a set of
symbols
which acts to establish powerful
pervasive and long-lasting moods and
motivations by formulating conceptions
of a general order of existence and
clothing those conceptions in such an
aura of factuality that those moods and
motivations seem uniquely realistic
which is complex what does that mean
that religion has to make you feel
something
these moods and motivations
but it can't just do that in the way
that sex does that for us or or sports
or ultimate fighting or the world cup
or going to a concert so we get all that
emotion in these experiences like that
but that emotion has to be concomitant
to a deep existential insight that
answers this question for you in the
morning i know why i'm here
i know why humans are here i think i
know what the meaning of life is that's
what religion is and if you find that
meaning in science then that's your
religion and that's fine
but we need to be more honest about that
if if you're epistemological model is
weighing facts and figures and you think
that's why you're here on this planet
and you find deep meaning that's okay
religion is the thing that makes you
feel right it has the aura of factuality
it just makes you feel like you know the
point behind existence
in other words i think it comes down to
experience like joe campbell was talking
about like alice huxley mentions about
experience and intuition i think this is
how we connect to god
make you feel like you understand
the world i mean so that's that's kind
of bigger than science that includes
science but it's bigger do you think
what is real
like uh
do you think there's an absolute reality
that we're kind of striving towards
understanding or is it all just conjured
up in our minds and that's the whole
kind of point we together create these
realities and play with them
and dance
uh to to somehow derive meaning from
those realities and it's ultimately not
like
very
deeply integrated into what's like um
into atoms of space time
another easy question lex
well i mean you have to kind of
when you're thinking about
emotion and
making it concrete
into something that feels real
you have to start asking like what is
real
it's uh it's something that
you know ben shapiro has the saying of
facts don't care about your feelings
i was always uncomfortable with this
with us i mean he's just being spiffy
whatever but
uh i was always uncomfortable with
somehow
first that the hubris of thinking that
humans can
have
like arrive at uh absolute truth what he
means which is what i assume he means by
facts
like things that are uncontrovertible
and then
somehow deriding feelings like feelings
are not important to me like
the whole thing
is reality
the
facts don't even like facts is reality
feelings are reality
like the entirety of human experience is
reality
all these consciousnesses somehow
interacting together make up making up
random crap and together agreeing
they're all going to wear the same
colors
rooting for one football team or the
other football team or countries all
those things that's re that's real
because we've agreed that it's real in
the same way
and gives us meaning in that same way
religion is a set of ideas that
gives us meaning
but
you know
real
it it's really a difficult
for uh for me as a scientist
that finds comfort
in the physical understanding of the
universe of physics you know i love
physics i love computer science
it makes me feel
like everything is perfectly
understandable
and then i look at humans
they're totally not understandable it's
like a giant mess but that's part of the
beauty like what is love
like what the hell is love
it's certainly not a like a weird uh
hack to convince me to procreate because
it feels something bigger than that
so like taking a purely evolutionary
biologist's perspective is missing the
uh it's not missing it's only capturing
a part of the picture and so it just
keeps making me ask like
what is real because i as a human it's
very human-centric it does certainly
feel like uh
a part a big part of what is real is all
the fake stuff my mind makes up
[Laughter]
i mean okay i guess
is there something you could say
from our discussions about
the tools of psychedelics about our
discussion about religion
of what is real
of what is reality
these are largely unanswerable questions
but we should nevertheless strive to
answer them that's the whole point of
the human experience and i think science
is one way and religion is another and i
think there's actually a sphere where
they intersect you know
there's a way for religion to be
observable testable repeatable
falsifiable when i look at the ancient
mysteries that that's what i find i
think i find people
exploring
alternate states of consciousness and
arriving at conclusions based on that
exploration
and deriving deep meaning from that
which yes are feelings and emotions and
very hard to quantify but nonetheless
these are the things that govern our
lives i mean
i don't know a parent who isn't
motivated by their by the love of their
children um everything i do
at 40 years old now is pretty much
inspired by my love for my two daughters
and i can't prove to you that i love
them i can say it i can show you
behavior but it's very hard for me to
weigh and measure that so
not everything
um is so reducible to this quantifiable
reality and yet i also love science and
and i love the historical process of
weighing this data i love the chemistry
i love the biology um and and for me um
i think this was the message of the
ancient greeks
and i think this is the world in which
paleochristianity was born i think there
is this this meeting ground between
science and religion um uh
which allow for the if not the discovery
then at least
the
the near identification of the ultimate
reality which is another way to describe
god right this being a being is the
transcendent mystery
so speaking of god you mentioned to me
offline you're wearing uh the most
sophisticated clothing choice
um of the elite intellectuals uh like
you mentioned sam harris was wearing a
hoodie this is the sam harris hoodie
he's starting a trend he's starting a
trend
um this is a new religion you could even
say it's a ritual it's a ritual practice
of uh intellectuals of searching for
meaning
uh so there's there's a quite a
fascinating debate so he was for a time
still
um known as one of the sort of new age
atheists
so he was kind of trying to explore the
role of religion society
and the role of science and on the other
side another kind of powerhouse
intellectual is jordan peterson
who in um sometimes
for my taste a bit too poetic of ways is
exploring ideas of religion
and they had these interesting debates
that i think will continue about the
role of religion and society
for uh uh for jordan there's all these
flaws with religion
but
there is
a lot of value to be discovered amidst
the the rituals the traditions the
practice the way we conceive of each
other because of the ideas that religion
propagates and then for sam
it says that everything about religion
is uh basically gets in the way
of us fully realizing our human
potential which is deeply scientific and
rational and um
sort of like we're surrounded by mystery
calling that mystery god is getting in
the way of us understanding that mystery
what do you think about this debate
about the role of religion and society
we should continue having this debate i
talked to jordan a couple weeks ago as a
matter of fact excellent and and his
podcast is public excellent it'll be out
soon
and so
you know he and i
how did that go by the way um it was it
was incredible uh carl rock the
professor joined us as a matter of fact
for one of his rare public appearances
so beautiful we went we went deep um and
jordan is very well read obviously on
the psychedelic literature he had just
had um roland griffiths from hopkins on
the podcast and it's one of roland's
figures that jordan and i again just
like the the language of aldous huxley
it's hard to move past the following
statistic
over the past 20 years
of the modern study of psilocybin
roland will tell you that about three
and four of their volunteers walk away
from their single dose of psilocybin
high dose saying it was among the most
meaningful experiences of their entire
lives if not the most meaningful and
jordan says like how do you
what do you do with that um uh how do we
i mean how do we synthesize that um
you know here we are
quantifying the the qualifiable the
unqualifiable and and yet these these
compounds have dramatic effects on
people's lives and they walk away
feeling like they're more
loving more compassionate um the science
of all talks about um the the welling up
of cooperation and resource sharing and
kindness and all these strange things
from this single chemical intervention
which seems to reduce us to automata as
if enlightenment can be flipped on uh
like a switch and yet there it is
there's the data and i don't see how you
walk away from that i mean i i
completely understand sam's position
but i think there's there's a reading of
religion particularly the mystical core
of of the big faiths and especially
these ancient mystery cults which do
speak again to those moods and
motivations um creating this aura of
factuality that these volunteers never
walk away from permanently transformed
just like the ancient mysteries and part
of that is perhaps language that we need
to continue to evolve language in
in how we conceive of these processes
maybe religion has a bunch of baggage
associated with it
that uh is good to let go of
or perhaps not i don't know it did
this connected to our previous
part of our conversation is the
importance of language in this whole
thing well that's how i start my book
with one of these volunteers from the
nyu psilocybin experiments this this
woman at dinah bazer who's an atheist
and she still describes herself as an
atheist and yet as one of these three
and four people who walked away from
this experiment transformed she says
that her experience of psilocybin was
like being bathed in god's love from an
atheist yes and i asked her why she uses
the word god why not the love of the
cosmos or the universe or mother nature
and she says well frankly you know we
don't know about any of this stuff and
that god makes sense to me um she's
still an atheist
um but it's the way she describes that
as kind of like
the way your mother's love must have
felt when you were a baby
yeah there's a there's a kind of i like
the way einstein uses god god doesn't
play dice there's a poetry there's a
humility that you don't know what the
hell is going on there's a humor to it
i'm a huge fan especially like more and
more
of just kind of
having a big old laugh at the absurdity
of
this world and this life
as uh represented nicely by memes on
twitter kind of thing
i mean there's a there's a sense in
which we want to be playing with these
words and not take them so
seriously and being a little bit
light-hearted
and explore
uh let me ask you about because you
mentioned and nyu
um what i find fascinating is how much
amazing researchers
speaking of science right uh
studying the effects of psilocybin
studying the effects of various
psychedelics mdma on the human mind
right now for helping people but i'm i'm
hoping there'll be studies uh soon
at hopkins and elsewhere that allow
people that are kind of more
quote-unquote creatives or
regular people that don't have a
particular demon they're trying to work
through the
a problem they're trying to work through
but
more like to see what can i
find if i utilize psychedelics to
explore is there something you could say
that is exciting to you it's promising
about
the future what currently is going on
but also the future of psychedelics
research yeah hopkins and elsewhere the
healthy normals the healthy norms
i was looking for the right words
because normal doesn't feel healthy
doesn't feel like a good term and normal
doesn't feel like a good term because
we're all pretty messed up and we're all
weird so well those with ontological
angst in that case
great maybe that'll be a future dsm
qualification yeah um there's no doubt
that that things like psilocybe and mdma
are are useful for things like anxiety
depression end-of-life distress ptsd
alcoholism you name it um
and it's largely because of the clinical
research that mdma and psilocybin will
probably be legal in some fda regulated
way in the next five years um but i mean
again i start the first page of my book
with this question why why do
psychedelics work
across all these different conditions
and uh the best that i could find is is
the meaning right um tony bossus at nyu
talks about psilocybin for example as
meaning making medicine
which is interesting because it puts it
somewhere between a therapeutic and
again this this ontological
instigator
what is it about psychedelics that
creates
these mystical experiences or mystical
like experiences you can call them
emotional breakthroughs you can call
them moments of all
i do think we get locked up in the
language and we're somewhere between
science and religion here um including
legally so the fda is one route to this
what excites me about psychedelics is
the first amendment what is this going
to mean for religion the freedom of
religion being the first thing that's
mentioned in the first amendment before
freedom of speech freedom of assembly oh
interesting yeah if america is known for
anything it's it's a refuge for uh
religious pioneers and so we already
have the native american church
brazilian spawn churches that are using
psychedelics but what would happen if
judaism or christianity or islam were to
begin incorporating
the very ritual very sacred
and discreet use of psychedelics as part
of their liturgy so not replacing the
sunday eucharist in the case of
christianity but um part of the extra uh
extra credit dimension of the faith
and then we can through practice figure
out how essential it is it could be a
minor thing it could be a major thing
that's another thing i wanted to kind of
ask you is um i recently despite the
fact that i'm eating a huge amount of
meat i'm getting fat
i'm loving it i'm you know this is
actually
uh as of two days ago i started this
long road to training for david goggins
to training back to uh to getting back
to competing in jiu jitsu so
the fun is over but i also partake in
fasting and there was a very
strong
there's an almost like a
hallucinogenic aspect of fasting because
it was especially because it was a 72
hour fast versus a more common fast that
i do which is 24 hours
you know
and a bunch of people talk about
throughout history about the value of
fasting in having these kind of
visual these kind of intellectual
experiences
also there's meditation sam harris with
the hoodie uh do do you have a sense
that um
those other
rituals of fasting of meditation and
maybe other things
could uh could be as essential or more
essential to the religious experience as
psychedelics
yes if not
and this is going to sound weird but
maybe not if more so um i look at
psychedelics as a catalyst
for spiritual investigation
not as the superficial means to an end
um i i think their their value
is in kind of um serving as a google
maps for the kingdom of heaven um
all right i like this
well so rom das teacher said that when
when he was was offered psychedelics
that um it'll it'll get you in the room
with jesus but it won't keep you there
okay yeah and i think that's all well
and good but what if you don't know
where the house is in the first place
what if you've never had a mystical
experience what if what if religion
is anathema to you what if you hate god
what if all these words mean nothing to
you and they probably do for many many
people and it's perfectly understandable
i think that we've we've lost the
coordinates to these irrational states
again that were prized throughout
antiquity and that continued to be
prized by the mystical communities even
in big organized religion it just
doesn't filter out that much and so
psychedelics in my mind
help orient
our minds bodies and souls towards the
irrational right we talked about
mckenna's invisible world that seems to
have this symbiosis with our own and
perhaps has this higher intent for us um
you could very well
just you know take catalog of your
dreams right and that would do it too
but psychedelics seem to be particularly
fast acting um particularly potent and
very reliable especially in the clinical
studies and so i looked at them as as
biochemical discoveries like like huxley
did maybe it's once
in your life or infrequently right but
maybe that's the beginning of a genuine
introspection and a life well examined
as the ancients always instructed us
yeah it does seem like in the research
that's
the effect of psychedelics always comes
with the integration where you
use it just like you said as a catalyst
for thinking through stuff it's not it's
not going to be
i don't even know if google maps
oh maybe maybe google maps is the right
analogy but it doesn't do the driving
for you
you still have to do the driving uh it
just kind of gives you the directions
uh so after you come come down from the
trip or whatever you still have to drive
there's other tools that are kind of
interesting we've been talking about
this um
at the psychological level but there's
also a neuroscience perspective if we
kind of like go past the skull into the
brain with the neurons firing there's
ideas of brain computer interfaces first
of all there's a whole field of
neuroscience that's kind of zooming in
and studying the firing of the brain the
firing of the neurons in the brain
of how from those
neurons emerges all the things that we
think that make us human that's a
fascinating exploration in the human
mind
that that's of course where the
psychedelics have the chemical the
biochemical effects on on those
neurons
there's ideas of brain computer
interfaces which
you know if you look at especially what
neural link is doing with this long-term
vision
with elon musk and your link they uh
they hope to expand
well he calls it a wizard hat
[Laughter]
this is back to the humor on the
internet thing uh
the the
the wizard hat that expands the
capabilities the capacity of the human
mind do you think there's something
there
or
is is the human mind so infinitely
complex that
we're quite a long way away from
expanding the capabilities of the human
mind
uh through technology versus something
like psychedelics
i wonder how terence mckenna would
answer that question um no he looked to
shamans as kind of the
the scientists um the high magicians of
the high archaic past and the far-flung
future
i'm not going to discount you know more
about ai than i do so i'm not going to
discount it
but
i do think that ai paired with
um
the sacred recovery right um the
archaeology
of consciousness um and these and these
states these archaic techniques of
ecstasy that were practiced across time
i think that's
a winning combination um you know part
of what i do in the book is just
i try and lay out the sentence setting
that's often talked about with
psychedelics i mean so
maybe psychedelics in the right ai
environment is going to work i think
it'd probably work a lot better
with that myth and ritual incorporated
so the reason ellucis worked for 2 000
years
and let's assume the psychedelic
hypothesis has some merit to it
but i think the reason it worked is
because you were born into a mythology
you were born into a story about demeter
and persephone and you waited your
entire life to meet them
in the flesh so you weren't just
preparing for a few months it was a
lifetime of expectation anticipation
ritual preparation
in fact some of the early church fathers
made fun of the greeks for essentially
just peaking people's curiosity and
revving up the anticipation which has
something to do with the outcome by the
way but in other words i think we need
to create a new mythology
around this i don't think you you pop
into a laboratory i don't think you pop
into a retreat center um from one day to
the next i think that in my own case i
feel like i've been preparing 12 years
for psychedelics and i'm still preparing
including in today's conversation i'm
learning new things
and uh i'm willing to explore it you
know together with the computer
interface but i i but i do think ritual
is a is a gigantic part of this and even
mckenna would say that um i'll
paraphrase him by saying that if if
you'd met someone who didn't know where
they were between the years 1995 and
2005 you would describe them
as a fairly damaged person and yet who
among us knows what was happening in
western civilization between 900 and
1300 let alone 2500 years ago so this is
in many ways the prophet of the
psychedelic renaissance saying that
history has lessons
and i don't think they're superficial
lessons i think it cuts to the very core
of how and why
western civilization came to be born
yeah but that history can be loaded into
ai systems and i do love the idea of
whether it's to bring computer
interfaces or without
intrusive sort of without direct reading
of the neurons and more sort of
interactive experience of the robot
that you can have an ai system that
steers your psychedelic experience
that
helps you sort of
when you take a heroic dose of
psilocybin for example help steer you
steer your mind
say just the right things i mean you
could say that kind of thing with uh
it's a totally open
um
problem i would say
you talk about set and setting this the
interesting thing about
johns hopkins is you know you create a
comfortable environment a safe
environment for
allowing then if you take a heroic like
a large dose
of psilocybin that you could
trust that everything would be safe and
you can really allow the exploration in
your mind but then you don't know from a
psychotherapy perspective of like
during that trip what a human should say
to steer that trip like that's a totally
open set of problems and in some sense
probably throughout history those
rituals you figured out what are the
right things to say to each other
exactly how to collaborate and maybe if
you can turn that into an optimization
problem
ai could figure that out much much
quicker i'm with you so ellucis was
known for three things the legomena the
dromina the numena the things said
the things done the things shown if you
can pack that all into your ai interface
i'm in lex friedman
i'm going to write a proposal and and
then try to get it through the irb at
mit
i mean there there's a certain sense in
which i definitely wanted to to explore
uh psychedelics i mean
in my personal life but also more
rigorously as a scientist
and uh to to push that forward and
especially in the ai space and it is um
difficult kind of
how to do that dance
when there's uh gray areas of legality
and all those kinds of things and we're
dancing around them and some of that is
language and some of that is uh
what we socially uh conceive of as as
drugs or not and
you're right that perhaps we can reframe
it as religious experiences all those
kinds of things i mean it's fascinating
because it feels like there's a bunch of
tools before us that were used by the
ancients that we're not utilizing
for exploring the human mind
that we very well could be in a rigorous
scientific way in a safe way and that's
fascinating
there's this interesting
period of uh
in the 20th century
of lsd use
that uh many of the people doing
research on psychedelics now kind of
have their roots in that history i
mentioned that dr mcdovin
he is one of those people
uh and there's this interesting story of
a bunch of creatives that used lsd or
other drugs to help them
what do you make of the idea of somebody
like ken kizi who wrote one flew over
the cuckoo's nest in part under the
influence of lsd
like what do you
make
of the use of psychedelics to uh
maximize the creative potential of the
human mind
is this um
is this a as a crutch or is this
actually um
an effective
tool that we should explore
one person's crutch might be another's
bungee cord um
you know
it depends on that mind
yeah uh think about paul mccartney i
mean we might not have some of the
better beatles music in the absence of
lsd
and what did sir paul say in 1967 when
he was asked about his use of lsd he
said that he recognized the dangers
inherent in it but that
he did it with a very specific very
deliberate purpose in mind um he wanted
to find the answer to what life is all
about
and i'm not sure what sir paul is doing
this week but he's probably not doing
lsd
speaking back to my theory about these
these substances being catalyzers of
spiritual introspection um
you know it came along at a time in
their life when i think they were right
for it especially george harrison um i
highly recommend the martin scorsese
documentary
about uh about george harrison um you
know for for them i think it was exactly
the way we ought to investigate it which
is
uh well
mind expanders this is what psychedelics
do right that which makes manifest the
contents of the mind um
in the absence of an experience like
that and it can be in a three-day fast
it can be laying down in a cave
it can be in ritual chanting it can be
in a sundance but in the absence of that
kind of experience at the right time in
your life
it may otherwise be very difficult
to find entrance to that kingdom of
heaven which i do think is here and now
getting right back to the very beginning
if we are actually to participate in
that eternal principle how
and when
what do you think nietzsche meant when
he said that god is dead
so there's a sense that religion is
fading from society
and uh there's a cranky german that kind
of wrote about it
what do you think he meant he was a
cranky german who knew a lot about
dionysus by the way
which is why i like him uh so certainly
there's some truth
to the mortality of god um
i think gallup put out a study only a
couple months ago where church
membership is now officially in the
minority in the united states at 47
according to the most recent poll that
number was closer to 70 percent only 20
years ago wow so we're living through
something and we're living through the
unchurching of america and it's the rise
of the spiritual but not religious
um you know the uh the inheritor of all
traditions but the slave to none there's
a rise in the unaffiliated the nuns i
think it was like one-third of
millennials it's probably much higher
now that don't affiliate with any
religion so in that sense god is
absolutely dead um
but maybe not the god that we were
trying to define
at the very beginning you know so
nietzsche also looked forward to the
ubermensch which would be a fully
realized human being
that despite the death of god um did not
fall into
nihilism and amorality existential
despair all that great german stuff
and there are some commentators who talk
about this eternal recurrence that just
maybe by incorporating
some of these techniques not necessarily
doctrine and dogma but i would say the
techniques of antiquity
and again nietzsche writes a lot about
the rationality of dionysus having its
place in society if if anything these
biochemical discoveries i think point us
back they point us back to dionysus and
their responsible incorporation of the
irrational into our otherwise
society of of rational um people and our
kazoo history i i have a sense that
there will be kind of just kind of as
you've implied
that there will be um
maybe the god of old is dying and
there'll be a rebirth of different kind
of god and it'll just keep happening
throughout history i i do think
there will be a time where ai will be
the gods we look to
uh the the other the the
super-intelligent those kinds of things
there's a little bit of an inkling of um
religious
longing for meaning in the way people
conceive of aliens currently
i it i mean i talked to a bunch of
people about ufos eops and aliens and so
to me it's very interesting for perhaps
different reasons because i'm just i
look up to the stars and it's incredibly
uh humbling to me to think that there's
trillions of intelligent alien
civilizations out there which to me
seems likely or not perhaps not
intelligent
perhaps just alien life
and actually
also that we don't even understand what
it means to be intelligent or do we
understand what it means to be alive the
time scale the spatial skill which
patterns of atoms can form in a way that
uh you can call life it's just could be
way weirder
uh than we can imagine that's and
certainly way different than human life
anyway that to me is humbling and so i
it's almost like with the simulation
uh conceding in the world of simulation
thinking of aliens to me is a useful
thought experiment of like what would
aliens look like if they visited how
would we know how would we communicate
with them how do we send signals to them
uh if they're already here
and we don't see them how's that
possible
that seems to me actually likely it
would just be too self-centered and too
dumb to see them if they're already here
anyway uh but so that's kind of the
almost the the the pragmatic the
engineering the the physics
sense of aliens but there's also kind of
a longing
to connect with other intelligent beings
out there both the fear and the
excitement of that that has kind of a
religious aspect to it sure that i find
fascinating and in the right context
when you remove the skepticism
of government from that it's actually a
hopeful longing uh do you have a
do you see this kind of interesting
aliens as it all connected to your study
of religion so you're the first person
to ask me about aliens
in eight months so it looks like i'm
going on the record
let's go so
um i'll drop some j allen heineck on you
um
so heinek
um involved in project blue book
famously says in 1966 when
the long-awaited solution to the ufo
problem comes and we're assuming that
ufos have something to do with aliens
but
um
when the long-awaited solution comes i i
believe it will prove to be not merely
the next small step in the march of
science but a mighty and unexpected
quantum leap
in other words
i do not think that we're dealing with
flesh and blood beings in nuts and bolts
crafts i think it's way
way more complicated than that and if
anything it takes me back to the ancient
world it takes me back to this invisible
college of beings of apparent higher
intent it takes me to the geniuses and
the muses
so the first document in western
civilization homer's
homer's epics they begin by invoking an
alien
they invoke a muse andra moya nepe musa
polutre von jos malabola tell me o muse
about the man so homer isn't inventing
poetry he's channeling
poetry epic poetry from an alien
intelligence
maybe that intelligence
has felt a little
unrecognized in recent years
trying to show up
in human recognizable forms the muse is
trying to give a little hint of
of its existence yeah i mean i i have a
i've been saying i honestly sort of i
don't believe this but i
think about this
whether alien like muse is a great
example whether aliens could be
thoughts
ideas we have are the aliens or
consciousness itself
is the methods by which aliens
communicate with us like i find this
very kind of
liberating
to expand our conception of what
intelligent beings are
you would like julian janes julian janes
writes a great book um
the origins of consciousness and the
breakdown of the bicameral mind it's
this
this theory that the ancient greek mind
was very different from ours and that
when they heard the muses they heard or
the gods and goddesses for that matter
they would hear them as voices in the
head
and
hear it as
an internal god figure offering commands
which they couldn't ignore so were they
walking schizophrenics it might be one
way to talk about it before the
breakdown of the bicameral mind but it's
it's a provocative theory largely
untestable but when you're reading
ancient greek and latin for that matter
you can't read it very long without
bumping up against these discarnate
entities they're everywhere
um and they they survived they they
persist across time which is even
stranger
not just in the form of all the things
my daughters like like fairies and
gnomes and elves but
and mckenna loves this the sylphs and
the boulder grinders and the sprites and
the gins and elementals every society
has them it seems to be fairly universal
and they largely exist in in folklore
mythology this is what jacques vallee
writes about so wonderfully
we've kind of been uh sneaking around it
but let me ask you from
yours
from everything we've been talking about
how do you think about consciousness
is it uh is it a
fun little trick that the human mind
does or is it somehow fundamental to
this whole thing
so
uh this three pound lump of jelly
inside our craniums that can
contemplate
the vastness of interstellar space it
can contemplate the meaning of infinity
and it can contemplate itself
contemplating on the meaning of infinity
that peculiar self-recursive quality
that we call self-awareness so this is
the hard problem right this is this is
uh the unknowable the unknown at least
yeah um i don't know
i have no good answer for that aside
from do you think it's somehow
deeply fundamental to the human
experience or is it just a trick so you
have like
i mean samurais has really been making
me uh think about this so you know
calling free will and illusion
the interesting thing about sam is
it's not just a philosophical little
chat with him about free will
he really says he experiences
the lack of free will
like he's able to you know
large parts of the day to feel like he
has no free will
in that same way
now he thinks that consciousness
is um
not an illusion it is you know it's a
real thing but at the same i'm more
almost like
i'm almost more of like consciousness
seems to be a little bit of an illusion
in the sense that like it feels like
maybe this is a robotics ai perspective
but it feels like in that same way that
sam steps outside of
feeling like he has an agency
feeling like he has a free will i feel
like we should be able to step outside
of
having a consciousness
so that that from my perspective maybe
that's a hopeful perspective for trying
to engineer consciousness but do you
think consciousness is like at the core
of this or is it just uh just like
language
or almost like a thing we build on top
of uh
much deeper human
the things that makes us human i don't
know i am attracted to lanza's notion of
biocentrism i mean it's difficult to
walk away from the double slit
experiment not wondering
why we seem capable of collapsing that
quantum wave function it's very very
weird um giving rise to even weirder
ideas about superposition and spooky
action at a distance and things that mit
guys know a lot better than me but um
it seems to me fundamental maybe
consciousness is is the fundamental
thing um i mean weirdly
some of these ancient incubatory
practices i talked about peter kingsley
before so he's not a proponent of
ancient psychedelic use but is a
proponent of these ancient rites of
incubation
that were practiced by pythagoras
parmenides and pedicles other
pre-socratics and so what were they
doing they were trying to get in touch
with consciousness they were entering
into suspended states of animation
um in these cave-like settings
pythagoras had built one in his basement
and would lie down motionless apparently
for long periods of time and what i
think they were trying to do
was tap into and trying to answer this
question in their own you could call it
a scientific way actually less religion
than science
and what they would
discover or try to discover was a state
of awareness that is somehow beyond life
and death beyond waking and dreaming
where you can be aware of the senses but
also in touch with another reality at
the exact same time what kingsley calls
sensation
that i think is definitely worth
exploring
well and the way i hope to explore is by
trying to build it but
everybody uses the tools they have well
no i do also hope psychedelics can help
so how do you build that i'm curious
that's a whole other discussion
this is uh
there's a lot of things i can say here
but let me put simply
is i believe
that
you can go
a long way
building
towards building consciousness
by trying to fake
consciousness
so fake it till you make it
as an engineering approach i think will
work for consciousness
[Laughter]
you seem satisfied with that i i'm
satisfied with that because i know how
deeply unsatisfied others are
but just wait
so
i mean i don't know what to so most most
the the the topic of consciousness is
mostly handled by philosophers currently
and
that's great uh and their
philosophers are wonderful and good at
what they do i'm not a philosopher i'm
an engineer and i think the approach
there is quite different
i think
in love
is different
than trying to have a podcast
conversation about what is love
uh
you know i i think the engineering
effort is just fundamentally different
than the philosophical effort and i
have a sense that consciousness can be
engineered
even before it is understood by the
philosophers so i think there's a bunch
of things like that in this world that
could be engineered before they're
understood i think the intelligence is
one such thing i think we'll be we'll
we'll be able to engineer
super intelligent beings before we're
able to understand the human mind
that's
um yeah i mean
there's less there's a lot of intuition
to unpack there of why that is but um
as it stands
that's perhaps my engineering
um optimism and engineering ethic under
which i operate
consciousness is easy to build hard to
understand
okay
[Laughter]
are there books or movies in your life
long ago or recently
that had a big impact on you
you've
you've uh
immortality key is exceptionally well
researched
the amount of books you read is uh
i cannot even imagine so is there
something in those in that in those in
your
travels through the land of language
that stuck with you that was especially
impactful i mentioned a couple of them
but
so i i knew nothing about psychedelics
before 2007.
and it was in in hearing about some of
the first psilocybin experiments at
hopkins and then shortly thereafter
i went down this rabbit hole and so the
first set of recommendations all kind of
fit in that time period in my life
2007 2008 it started with jeremy narby
the cosmic serpent dna in the origins of
knowledge
it was a total
impulse buy at the barnes noble on 6th
avenue in new york
and wound up introducing me to
supernatural by graham hancock
um
that that convinced me that there was a
long story to psychedelics that
um he tried to prove in that book and
that we're still trying to prove i
mentioned
the connection between ritual
psychedelics and cave art
this is the the neuropsychological model
that was first proposed by david lewis
williams at the university of
waterstream the the same university
where lee berger is by the way in south
africa so these ideas are old um but
what graham did in that book is just um
it's it's well worth your time it's well
worth a few reads actually
because it was after that that i
discovered
breaking open the head by daniel
pinchback um and and a lot a lot of
other books that just um
kind of blew my mind what is uh breaking
open the head about
so it's it's it's daniel's romp through
contemporary shamanism
and it's his uh very well told
experiences with everything from
psilocybin to iboga being initiated by
the buitis
and it was the the first time i'd read
uh any first-hand accounts aside from
jeremy narby any first-hand accounts but
by a new yorker by the way
um about the potential for these these
compounds that i'd been ignoring for far
too long obviously um and so that's when
i started revisiting the road to ellucis
and
looking through the anthropological
literature reading everything gordon
watson had ever written that carl ruck
had written
and it sent me down a pretty weird
rabbit hole until i found peter kingsley
which is my second recommendation so so
peter again he's not a fan of the
psychedelic hypothesis but what he does
is i think expose
the value of the irrational to the
ancient greeks especially the
pre-socratics here we are talking about
a.i and god and these
you know entangled philosophical
questions um
the best i can read kingsley is that
western civilization is a product of a
gift from the goddess persephone
and this is not a hippie this is this is
a
a pretty gold standard classicist who
went on to write a couple of books uh
one is in the dark places of wisdom and
the other is reality
what better way to title your book
where he talks about these ancient
techniques for exploring the irrational
the same thing carl rock was talking
about
after compiling all this data in the
road to ellucis ruck says that the
biggest challenge is trying to convince
his colleagues in the late 1970s that
the ancient greeks and indeed some of
the most famous and intelligent among
them could enter you know so fully into
irrationality same thing nietzsche's
talking about in his exploration of
dionysus and so i think kingsley just
stands apart
as um you know one of those books
reality that my life was never quite the
same after reading that
we talked about three-pound
uh jelly that uh is able to conceive
of the entirety of um
the fabric of reality in the universe
and everything and uh oh
also of its own mortality
what do you think is the meaning of it
all
what's the meaning of life
is a three-pound jelly able to answer
that one
no but i can plagiarize joseph campbell
which is uh which is good enough um
joe joe campbell says that you know i
don't think what we're looking for is a
meaning of life
i think what we're looking for is an
experience of being alive so that the
experiences we have on the purely
physical plane
will have resonances within that are
those of our innermost being and reality
you talked about the true reality
absolute truth
um these are all constructs and i think
they're they're constructs that that are
made day by day and acquire this aura of
factuality remembering clifford geertz's
definition of religion
we're all just
faking it until we make it and i think a
lot of that has to do with moods and
motivations and feelings and emotions
which is not to discredit facts and
figures
but i think that meaning meaning making
is a
very subjective process that is
not only difficult to talk about but
difficult to quantify an experience is a
primary in that versus
so like the actual subjective experience
is primary to
the meaning making process versus like
some kind of
rigorous analysis of
like uh having an algorithm that runs
and computes and and then finally spits
out 42.
well this this is how families are
created um tell me more about my wife
and i fell in love and made babies we
didn't we didn't type up an excel sheet
and figure out the best way to go about
this that's what i've been doing all
these years
that's why i'm single
[Laughter]
too many excel sheets uh what we say
falling in love right we say fall in
love what does that mean to fall in love
you are surrendering
to an intelligence
um that that that is beyond us um you
could say a god-like intelligence
richard rohr the franciscan friar i
mentioned in the universal christ he
writes a lot about how
the divine for you is is often
encountered in in the other in fact how
could it be otherwise this is this is
bedrock sacramental theology that you
find
the god in the things in your life as
well you should that that's the proving
ground
for identifying as god rather than
creating a relationship with god and so
i think that these irrational states
play a big role in that
ratio well i don't think there's a
better way to end it than on the topic
of love brian thank you so much for a
brilliant exposition of history
and the poetry
i really appreciate you uh talking with
me today i love you alex
i love you too bro
thanks for listening to this
conversation with brian miura rescue and
thank you to inside tracker givewell
and i
indeed and master class check them out
in the description to support this
podcast
and now let me leave you some words from
terence mckenna about psychedelics
part of what psychedelics do
is they decondition you from cultural
values
this is what makes it such a political
hot potato since all culture is a kind
of con game the most dangerous candy you
can hand out is one which causes people
to start questioning the rules of the
game thank you for listening and hope to
see you next time