I think it's actually not that hard to
imagine we are the only civilization in
the Galaxy right now living yeah that's
that's currently extent but there may be
very many extinct civilizations if each
civilization has a typical lifetime
comparable to let's say AI is the demise
of our own that's only a few hundred
years of technological development or
maybe 10 000 years if you go back to the
nearest Revolution the dawn of
Agriculture you know hardly anything can
Cosmic time span
um that that's nothing that's the blink
of an eye and so it's not surprising at
all that we would happen not to co-exist
with anyone else but that doesn't mean
nobody else was ever here
and if other civilizations come to that
same conclusion and realization maybe
they scour the Galaxy around them to
find any evidence for intelligence
then they have two options they can
either give up on communication and just
say well it's never going to happen uh
we just may as well just you know worry
about what's Happening Here on our own
planet or they could attempt
communication but communication is
through time
the following is a conversation with
David Kipping an astronomer an
astrophysicist at Columbia University
director of the cool world lab and he's
an amazing educator about the most
fascinating scientific phenomena in our
universe I highly recommend you check
out his videos on the cool worlds
YouTube channel David quickly became one
of my favorite human beings I hope to
talk to him many more times in the
future this is Alex Friedman podcast to
support it please check out our sponsors
in the description and now dear friends
here's David Kipping
your research at Columbia is in part
focused on what you call cool worlds or
worlds outside our solar system where
temperature is sufficiently cool to
allow for moons rings and Life to form
and for us humans to observe it so can
you tell me more about this idea this
place of cool worlds yeah the history of
discovering planets outside our solar
system was really dominated by these hot
planets and that's just because of the
fact they're easier to find when the
very first methods came online these
were primarily the Doppler spectroscopy
method looking for wobbling stars and
also the transit method and these two
both have a really strong bias towards
finding these hot planets now
hot plants are interesting the chemistry
in their atmosphere is fascinating it's
very alien
um an example of one that's particularly
close to my heart is trace2b whose
atmosphere is so dark it's less
reflective than coal and so they have
really bizarre photometric properties
yet at the same time they resemble
nothing like our own home
and so it said there's two types of
astrophysicists the astrophysicists who
care about how the universe works they
want to understand the mechanics of the
Machinery of this universe why did the
big bang happen why is the universe
expanding how are galaxies formed and
there's another type of astrophysicist
which perhaps
um
speaks to me a little bit more it
Whispers into your ear and that is why
are we here
are we alone are there others out there
and ultimately along this journey the
hot plants aren't going to get us there
we when we're looking for life in the
universe seems to make perfect sense
that there should be plants like our own
out there maybe even moons like our own
planet around gas giants that could be
habitable and so my research has been
driven by trying to find these more
draculous globes that might resemble our
own planet
so they're the ones that lurk more in
the shadows in terms of how difficult it
is to detect that much harder they're
harder for several reasons the method we
primarily use is the transit method so
this is really eclipses as the planet
passes in front of the star it blocks
out some Starlight the problem with that
is that not all planets pass in front of
their star they have to be aligned
correctly from your line of sight and so
the further away the planet is from the
Star the cooler it is the less likely it
is that you're going to get that
geometric alignment so whereas a hot
Jupiter about one percent of hot
Jupiters will transit in front of their
star only about uh 0.5 percent maybe
even a quarter of a percent of
earth-like planets will have the right
geometry to Transit and so that makes it
much much harder for us what's the
connection between temperature of the
plan and geometric alignment the
probability of geometrical element
there's not a direct connection but
they're connected varying intermediate
parameter which is their separation from
the Star so the planet will be cool if
it's further away from the Star which in
turn means the probability of getting
that alignment correct is going to be
less on top of that they also Transit
their star less frequently so if you go
to the telescope and you want to
discover a hot Jupiter you could
probably do it in a week or so because
the orbital periods of order of one two
three days so you can actually get the
full orbit two or three times over
whereas everyone's touched an Earth-like
planet you have to observe that star for
three four years and that's actually one
of the problems with Kepler Kepler was
this very successful mission that NASA
launched
um over a decade ago now I think and it
discovered thousands of planets it's
still the dominant source of exoplanets
that we know about but unfortunately it
didn't last as long as we would have
liked it to it died after about 4.35
years I think it was and so for an
Earth-like planet that's just enough to
catch four transits and four transits
was kind of seen as the minimum but of
course the more transits you see the
easier it is to detect it because you
build up signal to noise if you see the
same thing the more ticks you get the
easier is to find it and so it was
really a shame that Kepler was just at
the limit of where we were expecting it
to start to see earth-ite planets and in
fact it really found zero zero planets
that are around stars like the sun
they're all bits similar to the Earth
around the Sun and could potentially be
similar to our own planet in terms of
its composition and so it's a great
shame but um that's why it gives
astronomers more to do in the future
just to clarify the transit method
is our primary way of detecting these
things
and what it is is uh
when the object passes occludes the
source of light just a tiny bit a few
pixels and from that we can infer
something about its mass and size and
distance geometry all of that that's
like trying to tell
what uh
uh at a party you can't see anything
about a a person but you can just see by
the way they occlude others so this is
the method but is this is super far away
how many pixels of information do we
have
basically how high resolution is the
signal that we
um that we can get about these
occlusions
you're right in your description I think
just to build upon that a little bit
more it might be almost like your vision
is completely blurry like you have an
extreme you know High prescription and
so you can't resolve anything
everything's just blurs and but you can
tell that something was there because it
just got fainter for a short amount of
time something someone passed in front
of a light yeah and so that light in
your eyes would just dim for a short
moment now the reason we have that
problem with blown us a resolution is
just because the stars are so far away I
mean these are the closest stars of four
light years away but most of the Stars
Kappa looked at were thousands of light
years away
and so you there's absolutely no chance
that the telescope can physically
resolve
the star or even the separation between
the planet and the star is too small
especially for a telescope like Kepler
it's only a meter across in principle
you can make those detections but
you need a different kind of telescope
we call that direct Imaging and direct
Imaging is a very exciting distinct way
of detecting planets but it as you can
imagine is going to be far easier to
detect plants which are really far away
from their star to do that because
that's going to make that separation
really big and then you also want the
star to be really close to us so the
nearest Stars not only that but you
would prefer that planet to be really
hot because the hotter it is the
brighter it is and so that tends to bias
direct Imaging towards plants which are
in the processor forming so things which
have just formed the planets still got
all of its primordial heat embedded
within it and it's glowing we can see
those quite easily but for the planets
more like the Earth of course they've
cooled down and so we can't see that the
light is pitiful compared to a newly
formed planet we would like to get there
with direct Imaging that's the dream is
to have the Pale Blue Dart natural
photograph of it maybe even just a one
pixel photograph of it but for now the
entire solar system is one pixel with a
certainly the transit method most of the
telescopes and so all you can do is see
where that one pixel which contains
potentially dozens of planets and the
star maybe even multiple Stars dims for
a short amount of time it dims just a
little bit and from that you're gonna
throw something yeah I mean it's it's
like being a detective in the scene
right it's very it's indirect clues of
the existence of the planet it's amazing
that humans can do that we're just
looking out in these immense distances
and looking you know if there's alien
civilizations out there like let's say
one exactly like our own
or like
would we even be able to see an earth
that passes
in the way of its sun and slightly dims
and that's the only sign we have of that
of that alien human-like civilization
out there is it's a little bit of a
dimming yeah I mean it depends on the
type of style we're talking about if it
is a star truly like the sun the dip
that causes is 84 parts per million I
mean that's just it's like the same as a
um it's like a firefly flying in front
of like a giant floodlight at a stadium
or something that's the kind of the
brightness contrast that you're trying
to compare to so it's it's extremely
difficult detection
and in the very very best cases we can
get down to that but as I said we don't
really have any true Earth analogs that
have been in the exoplank Canada yet
unless you relax that definition you say
it's not just doesn't have to be a star
just like the sun it could be a star
that's smaller than the sun it could be
these orange dwarfs or even the red
dwarf stars and the fact those stars are
smaller means that for the same size
Planet passing in front of it more light
is blocked out and so a very exciting
system for example is trappist-1 which
has seven planets which are smaller than
the earth and those who are quite easily
detectable not with a space-based
telescope even from the ground and
that's just because the star is so much
smaller that the relative increase in or
decrease in brightness is enhanced
significantly because that's smaller
size so trap is one e it's a planet
which is in the right distance for
liquid water
and it has a slightly smaller size on
the earth
um it's about 90 the size of the Earth
about 80 the mass and it's one of the
top targets right now for potentially
having life
um and yet it raises many questions
about
um what would that environment be like
this is a star which is 1 8 the mass of
the sun it's
um stars like that take a long time to
come off that adolescence when stars
first form like the sun it takes them
maybe 10 100 million years to sort of
settle into that main sequence lifetime
but for stars like these late M dwarfs
as we call them they can take up to a
billion years or more to calm down and
during that period they're producing
huge amounts of x-rays ultraviolet
radiation that could potentially rip off
the entire atmosphere it may desiccate
the plants in the system and so even if
water arrived by comets or something it
may have lost all that water due to this
prolonged period of high activity so we
have lots of of open-ended questions
about these M dwarf planets but they are
the most accessible and so in the near
term if we detect anything in terms of
buyer signatures it's going to be for
one of these red dwarf stars it's not
going to be a true Earth twin as we
would recognize it as having a yellow
star well let me ask you I mean there's
a million ways to ask this question I'm
sure I'll ask it about habitable worlds
let's just go to our own solar system
what can we learn about the planets and
moons
in our solar system that
might contain life whether it's Mars or
some of the moons of Jupiter and Saturn
what kind of characteristics because you
said it might not need to be Earth-like
what kind of characteristics might be
we'd be looking for
when we look for life it's hard to
Define even what life is
um but we can maybe do a better job in
defining the sorts of things that life
does and that provides some aspects to
some Avenue for looking for them
um any classically conventionally I
think we thought the way to look for
life was to look for oxygen oxygen is a
byproduct of photosynthesis on this
planet we didn't always have it
certainly if you go back to the Arcane
period
um there was you know you have this
period called the Great oxidation event
where the Earth floods with oxygen for
the first time and starts to saturate
the oceans and then the atmosphere and
so that oxygen if we detect it on
another planet whether it be Mars Venus
or an exoplank whatever it is
um that was long thought to be evidence
for something doing photosynthesis
because if you took away all the plant
life on the earth the oxygen wouldn't
just hang around here it's a highly
reactive molecule it would oxidize
things and So within about a million
years you would probably lose all the
oxygen on planet Earth
so that was a conventionally how we
thought we could look for life and then
we started to realize that it's not so
simple because either might be other
things that life does apart from
photosynthesis
um certainly the vast majority of the
Earth's history had no oxygen and yet
there was living things on it so that
doesn't seem like a complete test
um and secondly could there be other
things that produce oxygen besides from
Life
um a growing concern has been these
false positives in biosignature work and
so one example of that would be
photolysis that happens in the
atmosphere when ultraviolet right hits
the upper atmosphere can break up water
vapor the hydrogen spits off to the
oxygen the hydrogen is much lighter
Atomic species and so it can actually
Escape certainly plants like the Earth's
gravity that's why we don't have any
hydrogen or very little helium and so
that leaves you with the oxygen which
then oxidizes the surface and so there
could be a residual oxygen signature
just due to this photolysis process so
we've been trying to generalize and
um recently in recent years there's been
other suggestions things we could look
for in the solar system Beyond uh
nitrous oxide basically laughing gas is
a product of microbes
um that's something that we're starting
to get more interested in looking for
methane gas in combination with other
gases can be an important biosignature
uh phosphine as well and phosphine is
particularly relevant to the solar
system because there was a lot of
interest for Venus recently
um you may have heard that there was a
claim of a biosignature in Venus's
atmosphere I think it was like two years
ago now
and the the judge and jury is still out
on that
um there was a very provocative claim
and signature of a phosphine-like
spectral absorption
um but it could have also have been some
of the molecule in particular sulfur
dioxide
which is not a buyer signature so this
is a detection of a gas in the
atmosphere yeah Venus and and uh it
might be controversial on several
Dimensions so one had to interpret that
two is a thread gas and three is this
even the right detection is this is
there an error in the detection yeah I
mean how much do we believe that's
actually in the first place if you do
believe it does that necessarily mean
there's life there and um what gives how
can you have life in the Venus's
atmosphere in the first place because
that's you know been seen as like a hell
hole place for imagining life but I
guess the the counter that has been that
okay yes the surface is a horrendous
place to imagine life thriving
um but as you go up in altitude the very
dense atmosphere means that there is a
cloud layer
um where the temperature and the
pressure become actually fairly similar
to the surface of the Earth and so maybe
there are microbes stirring around in
the clouds which are producing phosphine
um at the moment this is fascinating
it's got a lot of us
reinvigorated about the prospects of
going back to Venus and doing another
mission there in fact there's now two
NASA missions Veritas and DaVinci which
are going to be going back and before
23rd to the 2030s
um and then we have a European Mission I
think that's slated now and even a
Chinese Mission might be coming along
the way as well so we might have
multiple missions going to Venus which
has long been overlooked I mean apart
from the Soviets there really has been
very little in the way of exploration of
Venus certainly as compared to Mars Mars
has enjoyed most of the activity from
NASA's Rovers and surveys and Mars is
certainly fascinating there's you know
this signature of methane that has been
seen there before
um again there the discussion is whether
that methane is a product of biology
which is possible something that happens
on the earth or whether it's some
geological process that we are yet to
fully understand could be a for example
a reservoir of methane that's trapped
under the surface and it's leaking out
seasonally so the nice thing about Venus
is if there's a giant living
civilization there it'll be airborne so
you can just fly through and collect
samples yeah with Mars and uh moons of
uh Saturn Jupiter you're gonna have to
dig
under to find the civilizations right
dead or living right and so yeah maybe
it's easier than for Venus because
suddenly you can imagine just a balloon
floating through the atmosphere
um the or a drone or something that
would have the capability of just
scooping up and sampling
um to dig under the surface of Mars is
maybe
feasible-ish with you know especially
with something like Starship that could
launch you know a huge Digger basically
to the surface and you could just
excavate away at the surface but for
something like Europa
um we really are still unclear about how
thick the ice layer is how you would
melt through that huge thick layer to
get to the ocean and then potentially
also discussions about contamination the
problem with looking for life in the
solar system which is different from
looking for life with exoplasts is that
you always run the risk of especially if
you visit there of introduced in the
Life yourself
right it's very difficult to completely
exterminate every single microbe and
Spore on the surface of your of your
Rover or the surface of your Lander and
so there's always a risk of introducing
something I mean
to some extent there is continuous
exchange of material between these
planets naturally on top of that as well
and now we're sort of accelerating that
process to some degree
and so if you dig into europa's surface
which probably is completely pristine
it's very unlikely there has been much
exchange with the outside world for its
subsurface ocean
You Are For the First Time potentially
introducing bacterial spores into that
environment that may compete or may
introduce spurious signatures for the
life you're looking for and so it's it's
almost an ethical question as to how to
proceed with looking for life on those
subsurface oceans and I don't think
we've really
have a good resolution for at this point
that's cool I'll see me as a God in
terms of concern
for the
the like for preserving life elsewhere
not like not to murder it as opposed to
Scientific one I mean we always worry
about a space virus right coming coming
here or you know some kind of external
source and we would be the source of
that potential contamination or the
other direction yeah I mean
they that you know the whatever whatever
survives in such harsh conditions might
be pretty good at uh
surviving in all conditions it might be
a little bit more resilient and robust
so I might actually take a ride on us
back home possibly I mean I'm sure I'm
sure that some people will be concerned
about that I think we would we would
hopefully have some containment uh
procedures as if we did sample return or
you mean you don't even really need a
sample return these days you can pretty
much sound like a little micro
laboratory to the other planet to deal
with experiments you know in situ and
then just send them back to your planet
the data and so I don't think this is
necessary that especially for a case
like that where you might have
contamination concerns that you have to
bring samples back
um although probably if you brought back
European Sushi it would probably sell
for quite a bit with the billionaires in
New York City
Sushi yeah
um I would love from an engineering
perspective just to see all the
different candidates and designs for
like the scooper for Venus and the
scooper for Europa and and Mars I
haven't really look deeply into how they
actually like the actual engineering of
collecting samples because that's the
engineering of that
is probably essential for not either
destroying life or or polluting it with
our own microbes and so on so that's an
interesting engineering challenge I
usually for Rovers and stuff focus on
the on the robot on the
sort of the mobility aspect of it on the
robotics the perception and the movement
and the planning and the control but
there's probably the scooper is probably
where the action is the microscopic
sample collection so basically you have
to first clean
your vehicle make sure it doesn't have
any Earth-like things on it and then you
have to put it into some kind of thing
that's perfectly sealed from the
environment so if we bring it back or we
analyze it it's not
um it's not going to bring anything else
uh external and yeah I don't know it
could be that would be an interesting
engineering design there yeah I mean
Curiosity has been uh leaving these
little pods on the surface quite
recently there's some neat photos you
can find online and it's they kind of
look like a lightsaber hilts which so
um that yeah to me I think I tweeted
something like uh you know this weapon
is your life like don't lose it
curiosity because it's just dumping
these little vials everywhere and it's
yeah it is scooping up these things and
the intention is that in the future
um there will be a sample return mission
that will come and pick these up
um but it's I mean the engineering
behind those things is so impressive the
thing that blows me away the most has
been The Landings
um especially I'm training to be a pilot
at the moment so that's the sort of you
know watching Landings has become like
my I'll be on YouTube at the moment and
how not to do it how to do it with
different levels of conditions and
things but with the you know when we
think about landing on Mars Just the
light travel time effect means that
there's no possibility of a human
controlling that descent and so you have
to put all of your faith and your trust
in the computer code or the AI or
whatever it is that you've put on board
that thing to to make the correct
descent
um and so there's this famous uh period
called seven minutes of hell where
you're basically waiting for that light
travel time to come back to know whether
you're vehicle successfully landed on
the surface or not and during that
period you know in your mind
simultaneously that it is doing these
multi-stages of
um deploying its parachute deploying the
crane
activating its Jets to come down and
controlling its descent to the surface
and then the crane has to fly away so it
doesn't accidentally hit the Rover and
so there's a series of multi-stage
points where any any of them go wrong
you know the whole mission could could
go awry
um and so the fact that we are fairly
consistently able to build these
machines that can do this autonomously
is to me one of the most impressive acts
of engineering that NASA have achieved
yes the unfortunate fact about physics
is the takeoff is easier than the
landing yes yes and you mentioned
Starship one of the incredible
engineering feeds that you get to see is
the reusable rockets that take off but
they land and they land uh using control
and they do so perfectly and sometimes
when it's synchronous it's just it's
beautiful to see and then with Starship
you see the the Chopsticks that catch
the ship I mean there's so much
incredible engineer but you mentioned uh
Starships somehow helpful here so what's
your hope with Starship what kind of
science might it enable possibly there's
two things I mean it's the launch cost
itself which is hopefully going to mean
per kilogram it's going to dramatically
reduce the cost of its the sort of the
level even if it's a factor of 10 higher
than what Elon originally promised this
is going to be a revolution for the cost
to Launch that means you could do all
sorts of things you could launch
um large telescopes which could be
basically like jwst but you don't even
have to fold them up jwst had this whole
issue with a design that it's six and a
half meters across and so you have to
there's no fuselage which is that large
at the time there is four wasn't large
enough for that and so they had to fold
it up into this kind of complicated
origami and so a large part of the cost
was figuring out how to fold it up
testing that it unfolded correctly
repeated testing and you know there was
something like 130 fail points or
something during this unfolding
mechanism and so all of us were holding
our breath during that process but if
you have the ability to Just Launch in
an arbitrarily large masses at least
comparatively compared to wst and very
large mirrors into space you can more or
less repurpose ground-based mirrors
um the Hubble Space Telescope mirror and
the jbsd mirrors are designed to be
extremely lightweight and that increase
their cost significantly they have these
kind of the comb design on the back to
try and minimize the the weight if you
don't really care about weight because
it's so cheap then you could just
literally grab many of the existing
ground-based mirrors across tuskers
across the world four meter five meter
mirrors and just pretty much attach them
to a chassis and have your own
space-based telescope
um I think the Breakthrough foundation
for instance is an entity that has been
interested in doing this sort of thing
and so that raises the prospects of
having not just one wst that just you
know wst is a fantastic resource but
it's split between all of us
cosmologists star formation astronomers
those of us studying exoplanets those of
us wanting to study you know the ultra
deep fields and the origin of the first
galaxies the expansion rate of the
universe everyone has to share this
resource but we could potentially each
have you know one jwst each that is uh
maybe just studying a handful of the
brightest exoplanet stars and measuring
their atmospheres this is important
because if you and we talked about this
plant trap is 1A earlier
that planet if dwc started it and tried
to look for buyer signatures by which I
mean oxygen
nitrous oxide methane it would take it
of order of 200 transits to get even a
very marginal what we call two and a
half Sigma detection of those which
basically nobody would believe with with
that and 100 transits I mean this thing
transits once every six days so you're
talking about sort of four years of
staring at the same star with one
telescope to be some breaks but it'd be
hard to schedule much else because
you'll have to continuously catch each
one of these transits to build up your
signal to noise
and so DRC is never going to do that in
principle technically wst could
technically have the capability of just
about detecting a buyer signature on an
Earth-like planet around around a
non-sung-like star but still
impressively we have basically the
technologists do that but we simply
cannot dedicate all of its time
practically to that one resource and so
Starship opens up opportunities like
that of mass producing these kinds of
telescopes which will allow us to survey
for life in the universe which of course
is one of the grand goals of astronomy I
wonder if you can speak to the the
bureaucracy the political battles the
scientific battles for for time on the
James World telescope is there a there
must be a fascinating it's process of
scheduling that all scientists that are
trying to collaborate and figure out
what the most important problems are
and there's an interesting network of
interfering scientific experiments
probably have to somehow optimize over
it's it's a really difficult process I
don't envy the tech that are going to
have to make this decision we call it
the attack the time allocation committee
that the make this decision
um and I've served on these before and
it's very difficult I mean typically for
Hubble we we were seeing at least 10
sometimes 20 times the number of
proposals for telescope time versus
available telescope time for jdst there
has been one call already that has gone
out we call it cycle one and that was
oversubscribed by I think something like
six to one seven to one and uh the cycle
two which is just been announced uh
fairly recently and the deadline is
actually the end of this month so my
team are totally laser focused on
running our proposals right now
um that is expected to be much more
competitive probably more comparable to
what Hubble saw and so it's hard more
competitive than the second one you said
already because that's already in the
first cycle so I said the first cycle of
James Webb was about six to one
um and this will probably be more like
20 to one I would so these are all
proposals by scientists and so on and
it's not like you can schedule at any
time because if you're looking for
transit times yeah you have you have a
time critical element yes time critical
development and they're conflicting in
non-like non-obvious ways because
they're the the frequency is different
uh the duration is different right and
it's because it's probably computational
needs yeah there are different uh that
there's the type of sensors the
direction pointing all that yeah it's
hard and there are certain programs like
doing a deep field study where you just
more or less point the telescope and
that's pretty open I mean you're just
accumulating photons you can just point
at that at that patch of the sky
um whenever the task is not doing
anything else and just get to your month
let's say a month of integration time is
your is your goal over the lifetime of
wst so that's maybe a little bit easier
to schedule it's harder especially for
us looking at cool worlds
um because as I said earlier these these
plants Transit very infrequently
so we have to wait if you're looking at
the Earth translating the Sun an alien
watching us they they would only get one
opportunity per year to do that
observation the transit lasts for about
12 hours
um and so if they don't get that time
it's hard that's it if it conflicted
with another proposal that wants to do
use the another time critical element
it's much easier for plants like uh
these hot these hot plants or these
close implants because they Transit so
frequently there's maybe 100
opportunities and so then the attack can
say okay they want 10 transits there's a
hundred opportunities here it's easier
for us to give us time to give them time
we're almost in the worst case scenario
we're proposing until it Rex and means
around two cool planets and so we really
only have one bite of the Cherry for
each one and so our sales pitch has been
that these are extremely precious events
and more importantly gwst is the only
telescope the only machine Humanity has
ever constructed acid which is capable
of finding moons the kin to the moon's
in our solar system Kepler can't do it
even Hubble can't do it Judas is the
first one and so there is a new window
to the universe because we know these
moons exist they they're all over the
place in the solar system you have the
moon you have IO Callisto Europa
Ganymede Titan lots of moons are fairly
similar size sort of 30 the size of the
Earth and this telescope is the first
one that can find them and so we're very
excited about the profound implications
of
ultimately solving this journey we're on
in astronomy which is to understand our
uniqueness we want to understand how
common is the solar system are we the
way are we the architecture that
frequently emerges naturally or is there
something special about what happened
here I think this is not the worst case
the best case it's obvious it's super
rare so you have to like I would so I
love scheduling from a computer science
perspective that's my background so
algorithmically to solve a schedule
problem I will schedule the rarest
things first and obviously this is the
the jwst is the first thing that can
actually detect a cool world so this is
a big new thing you can show off that
new thing happens rarely schedule it
first it's perfect you should be an
attack
I'll file my application after we're
done with this I I you know this part of
me is the OCD part of me is the
computational aspect I love scheduling
uh Computing device because you have
that kind of scheduling
on super computers on that scheduling
problem is fascinating how do you
prioritize computational how do you
prioritize science uh data collection uh
sample collection all that kind of stuff
it's actually kind of it's kind of
fascinating because data in ways you
expect and don't expect will unlock a
lot of solutions to uh some fascinating
Mysteries and so collecting the data and
doing so in a way that maximizes the
possibility of Discovery is really
interesting like from a computational
perspective I agree there's a real
satisfaction extracting the maximum
science per unit time yeah exactly out
of your telescope and that that's that's
the tax job but the the attacker are not
machines they're not a piece of computer
code
um they will make their selections based
off human judgment and
um a lot of the telescope is certainly
within the field of exoplanets because
there's different fields of astronomy
but within the field of exoplanets I
think a good expectation is that most of
the telescope time that James jersey
have will go towards atmospheric
retrieval which is uh sort of alluded to
earlier you know like detecting
molecules in the atmospheres not by
signatures because as I said it's really
not designed to do that it's pushing
generous T probably too far are to
expect to do that but it could detect
for example a carbon dioxide Rich
atmosphere on trappist-1e that's not a
biased signature but you could prove
it's like a Venus in that case or maybe
like a Mars in that case like both those
have carbon dioxide Rich atmospheres
doesn't prove or disprove the existence
of life either way but it is our first
characterization of the nature of those
atmospheres maybe we can even tell the
pressure level and the temperature of
those atmospheres so that's very
exciting but um this we are competing
with that and that I I think that
science is completely mind-blowing and
fantastic we have a completely different
objective which is in our case to try
and look for the first evidence of these
small moons around these planets
um potentially even moons which could be
habitable of course so I think it's a
very exciting goal but
um attack has to make a human judgment
essentially about which science are they
most excited by which one has the
highest promise of return the most
highest chance of return and so that's
hard because if you look at a planetary
atmosphere
well you know most time the plant has an
atmosphere already it and so there's
almost a guaranteed success that you're
going to learn something about the
Atmosphere by pointing wst at it whereas
in our case there's a harder cell we are
looking for something that we do not
know for sure exists yet or not and so
we are pushing the telescope to do
something which is inherently more risky
yeah but the existence is shown already
gives a deep
a lesson about what's out there in the
universe but that means that other stars
have similar types of variety as we have
in our solar system they have an IO they
have a Europa and so on which means like
there's a lot of possibility
for Icy planets for water for plants
that enable for planets and moons that I
mean that that's super exciting because
that that means everywhere through our
galaxy and Beyond
there is just innumerable possibility
for weird creatures I agree life forms
you'd have to convince me I mean yeah
NASA has been on this quest for a long
time and it's sometimes called eater
Earth it's the frequency of Earth like
usually they say planets in the universe
how common are plants similar to our
Earth in terms of
um ultimately we'd like to know
everything about these planets in terms
of the amount of water they have how
much atmosphere they have but for now
it's kind of focused just on the size
and the distance from the Star
essentially how how often do you get
similar conditions to that
um that was Kepler's primary Mission and
it it really just kind of flirted with
the answer it didn't quite get to a
definitive answer but I always say look
if we're looking if that's our primary
goal to look for Earth-like
I would say worlds then moons has to be
a part of that because we know that um
Earth-like and from the capital data to
the preliminary Resort is the Earth-like
planets around sunlight stars is not an
inevitable outcome it seems to be
something like a one to ten percent
outcome so it's not particularly
inevitable that happens but we do often
see about half of awesome like stars
have either a mini Neptune a Neptune or
Jupiter in the hyperzone of Their Stars
that's a very very common occurrence
that we see yet we have no idea how
often they have moons around them which
could also be habitable and so there may
very well be if even one in five of them
has an Earth-like moon or even a Mars
like Moon around them then there would
be more habitable real estate in terms
of exomoons than exoplasts you can
essentially 2x 3x 5x maybe 10x the
number of habitable worlds out there in
the universe our current estimate for
like the Drake equation absolutely so
this this is a one way to increase the
confidence
and increase the the value of that
parameter and just know where to look I
mean we we would like to know where
should we listen for techno signatures
where should we be looking for buyer
signatures
um and not only that but what role does
the does the moon have in terms of its
influence on the planet
um we talked about these directly image
telescopes earlier these missions that
want to take a photo to quote Carl Sagan
The Pale Blue Dart of our planet but the
pale blue dot of an exoplanet and that's
the dream to one day capture that but as
impressive as the resolution is that we
are planning and conspiring to design
for the future generation telescopes to
achieve that even those telescopes will
not have the capability of resolving the
Earth and the moon within that it'll be
a pale blue dot pixel but the moon's
gray grayness will be intermixed with
that pixel and so this is a big problem
because one of the ways that we are
claiming to look for life in the
universe is a chemical disequilibrium
so you see two molecules that just
shouldn't be there they normally react
with each other or even one molecule
that's just too reactive to be hanging
around the Atmosphere by itself so if
you had oxygen and methane hanging out
together those would normally react
fairly easily and so if you detected
those two molecules in your pale blue
dot Spectra you bet okay we have
evidence for life something's
metabolizing on this planet
um however the challenge here is what if
that moon was Titan Titan has a
methane-rich atmosphere and what if the
pale blue dot was in fact a plant devoid
of life but it had oxygen because of
water undergoing this photolysis
reaction splitting into oxygen hydrogen
separately so then you have all of the
Hallmarks of what we would claim to be
life but all along you were tricked it
was just a moon that was deceiving you
and so we are never going to we're never
going to I would claim really understand
the
or complete this quest of looking for
Life by signatures in the universe
unless we
have a deep knowledge of the prevalence
and role that moons have they may even
affect the habitability of the planets
themselves of course our own moon is
freakishly large by mass ratio it's the
largest moon in the solar system it's a
one percent Mass Moon if you look at
Jupiter's moons they're like 10 to the
power minus four much smaller and so I
wrote moon seems to stabilize the
obliquity of our planet it gives rise to
Tides especially early on when the moon
was close to those ties would have
covered entire continents and those
those Rock pools that would have been
scattered across the entire Plateau may
have been the origin of Life on our
planet the moon forming impact may have
stripped a significant fractional
lithosphere of the earth which without
it plate tectonics may not have been
possible we'd heard a stagnant lid
because it was just too much lithosphere
stuck on the top of the of the planet
and so there are speculative reasons but
intriguing reasons as to why a large
Moon
Maybe
not just important but Central to the
question of having the conditions
necessary for life so moons can be
habitable in their own right but they
can also play significant influence on
the habitability of the planets they
orbit and further they will surely
interfere with our attempts to detect
life remotely from afar
so uh taking a tangent upon a tangent uh
you've written about binary planets what
what's and that they're surprisingly
common
or they might be surprisingly common
what's the difference between a large
Moon and binary plants what what are
binding planets what uh what's
interesting to say here about giant
rocks flying through space and orbiting
each other the thing that's interesting
that binary objects is that they're very
common in the universe binary stars are
everywhere in fact the majority of stars
seem to live in binary systems
um when we look at the outer edges of
the solar system we see binary Kuiper
Belt objects all the time asteroids
basically bound to one another Pluto
shown is kind of an example of that it's
a 10 Mass ratio system it almost is by
many definitions a binary Planet but now
it's a dwarf planet so yeah I don't know
we can call that now but we know that
these you know the universe likes to
make things in pairs yeah um so you're
saying our sun is an in cell
it's looking so most things are dating
they're in relationships and ours is
alone it's not a complete freak of the
universe to be alone but it is
um it's more common for sunlight Stars
if you count up all the next stars in
the universe about half of the sunlight
star systems are in binary or trinary
systems and the other half are single
but because those binaries are two or
three stars then cumulatively maybe like
a third of all so like stars are single
I'm trying hard to not anthropomorphize
the relationship
with each other but yeah
yeah that's yeah I've met those folks
also
um so is there something interesting to
learn about the habitability the how
that affects the probability of
habitable worlds when they kind of
couple up like that in those different
ways well it depends we're talking about
the stars of the planet certainly if
Stars couple up that has a big influence
on the how to Ability
um of course this is very famous from
Star Wars Tatooine in Star Wars there's
a binary star system and you have Luke
Skywalker looking at the sunset I'm
seeing two stars come down and uh for
years we thought that was purely a
product of George Lucas's incredibly
creative mind and we didn't think that
planets would exist around binary star
systems it seems like two tumultuous an
environment for a quiescent planetary
disk circumstellar disk to form plants
from and yet uh one of the astounding
discoveries from Kepler was that these
appear to be quite common in fact as far
as we can tell they're just as common
around binary stars as single Stars the
only uh caveat to that is that you don't
get plants close into binary Stars they
have like a clearance region in on the
inside where plants maybe they form
there but they don't last
they are dynamically unstable in that
zone but once you get out to about the
distance that the Earth orbits the Sun
or even a little bit closer in you start
to find plants emerging and so that's
the right distance for liquid water so
at distance for potentially life on
those parts and so there may vary will
be plenty of Habitual plants around the
binary Stars binary plants is a little
bit different binary plants I don't
think we have
um any serious connection of plant
banarity to habitability certainly when
we investigated it that wasn't our drive
that this is somehow the solution to
life in the universe or anything
it was really just a like all good
science questions a curiosity driven
question what's the dynamic are they
legit orbiting each other as they orbit
this uh the star so the formation
mechanism proposed here
um because it is very difficult to form
two Proto plants close to each other
like this they were generally merged
within the disc and so that's why you
normally get single planets but you
could have something like Jupiter and
Saturn form at separate distances they
could dynamically be scattered in
towards one another and basically not
quite Collide but have a very close on
encounter now because uh tidal forces
increase dramatically as the distance
decreases between two objects the tides
can actually dissipate the kinetic
energy and bring them bound into one
another so that seemed when we you know
when you first hear that you think that
seems fairly contrived that you'd have
the conditions just right to get these
ties to cause a capture but numerical
simulations have shown that about 10 of
planet planet encounters
are shown to produce something like
binary planets which is a startling
prediction
um and so that seems at odds with
naively the exoplank catalog for which
we know of so far are no binary plants
and we propose one of the resolutions to
this might be that the binary planets
are just incredibly difficult to detect
which is also counter-intuitive because
remember how they form us through this
tidal mechanism and so they form
extremely close to each other so the
distance that IO is away from Jupiter
just a few planetary radii they're
almost touching one another and they're
just tightly locked facing each other
for eternity and so in that
configuration as it transits across the
start it kind of looks like you can't
really resolve those two planets it just
looks like one planet to you that's
going across the star the temporal
resolution of the data is rarely good
enough to distinguish that and so you'd
see one Transit but in fact it's two
players very close together which are
transiting at once and so yeah we wrote
a paper just recently where we developed
some techniques to try and get around
this problem and hopefully provide a
tool where we could finally look for
these plants the problem of detection of
yes that was our Focus was how do you
how do you get around this this merging
problem so whether they're out there or
not uh we don't know we we're planning
to do a search for them but um it it
remains an open question and I think
just one of those fun astrophysics
Curiosities questions where the binary
players exist in the universe because
then you know you have binary Earths you
could have binary Neptune all sorts of
wild stuff that would you know flow to
the Sci-Fi imagination I wonder what the
physics on a binary Planet feels like it
might be trivial I have to think about
that I wonder if there's some
interesting Dynamics like if you're
multiple
or would gravity feel different on
different parts of the the surface of
the sphere when there's another large
sphere yeah I would think that the force
would be uh fairly similar because the
shape of the object would deform to a
flat Geo potential essentially a uniform
geopotential but it would lead to a
distorted shape for the two objects I
think they've become ellipsoids facing
one another
um so it would be pretty wild when you
you know people like Flat Earth or
spherical Earth you fly from space and
you see a football shaped Earth yeah
it's your own Planet finally there's
proof and I wonder how how difficult it
would be to travel from one to the other
because you have to overcome the one
no it might be kind of easy
yeah I mean they're so close to each
other that helps and I think the most
critical Factor would be how massive is
the planet that's always I mean one of
the challenges with escaping plants
there was a fun paper when my colleagues
wrote that suggested that super Earth
planets may be inescapable if you're a
civilization that were born on a super
Earth the surface gravity is so high
that the chemical potential energy of
hydrogen or methane whatever fuel you're
using simply is at odds with the with
the gravity of the planet itself and so
you would uh you know our current
Rockets I'm not sure with a fraction but
maybe like 90 of the rocket is fuel or
something by mass these things would
have to be
um like the size of the the Giza
Pyramids of fuel with just a tiny tip on
the top in order just to escape their
Pantry atmosphere and so it has been
argued that if you live on a super Earth
you may be you may be forced to live
there forever there may be no Escape
unless you invent a space elevator or
something but then how do you even build
the infrastructure and space to to do
something like that in the absence of a
successful rocket program
um and so the more and more we we look
at our Earth and think about the sorts
of problems we're facing
the more you see things about the Earth
which make it ideally suited in so many
regards it's almost spooky right that we
not only live on a planet which has the
right conditions for life for
intelligent life a sustained fossil fuel
industry just happens to be in the
ground we have plenty of fossil fuels
that to get our Industrial Revolution
going
um but also the chemical energy
contained within those fossil fuels and
hydrogen and other fuels is sufficient
that we have the ability to escape our
planetary atmosphere and planetary
gravity to have a space program and we
also happen to have a Celestial body
which is just within reach the moon
which doesn't also necessarily have to
be true were the moon not there what
effect would that have had on our
aspirations of a space program in the
1960s would there have ever been a space
race to Mars or to Venus it's a much
harder it's only for a human program
that seems almost impossible with 1960s
technology to imagine ever come to
fruition it's almost as if somebody
constructed a set of
uh challenging obstacles before us
challenging problems to solve they're
challenging but they're doable and
there's a sequence of them gravity is
very difficult to overcome but we have
given the size of Earth it's not so bad
that we could still actually construct
propulsion systems that can escape it
yeah and it's time with climate change
perhaps I mean climate change is the
next major problem facing That
civilization but we know it is
technically surmountable yeah you know
it's it's a it's it's it does seem
sometimes like there has been a series
of challenges laid out to
um progress us towards a mature
civilization that can one day perhaps
expand to the Stars I'm a little more
concerned about nuclear weapons uh Ai
and uh natural or artificial pandemics
but yes I mean plenty plenty of plenty
of fun Milestones that we need to cross
and we can argue about the severity of
each one but there is no doubt that we
live in a world that has serious
challenges is that are pushing our
intellects now will to the limit of
whether we're really ready to progress
to the next stage of our development so
thank you for taking the tangent and
there'll be a million more but can we
step back to Kepler
1625b what is it and you you've talked
about this kind of Journey this
effort to discover uh EXO moons so moons
out there or small cool objects out
there uh where does that effort stand
and what is coupler 1625b yeah we I mean
I've been searching from experiments for
most of my professional career and I
think a lot of my colleagues think I'm
kind of crazy to to still be doing it
you know after
after five years of not finding anything
I think most people would probably try
doing something else I even had people
say that to me they said um you know
professors and I remember the cocktail
party took me to the side an MIT
Professor he said
um you know you should just look for hot
Jupiters they're everywhere it's really
you can write papers they're so easy to
find and I was like yeah but hardship
just just they're not interesting to me
I want to do something that I feel
intellectually pushes me to the edge and
there's maybe a contribution that not no
one else could do but maybe
um is not certainly the thing that
anybody could do I don't want to just be
the first to something for the sake of
being first I want to do something that
feels like a meaningful intellectual
contribution to our society and so you
know this examine problem has been
haunting me for years to try and solve
this now as I said we looked for years
and years using Kepler
and the closest we ever got was just a
hint for this one star Kepler 1625 has a
jupiter-like planet in orbit of it and
that Jupiter planet is on a 287 day
period so it's almost the same distance
as the Earth around the Sun but for a
Jupiter
um so that was already unusual I don't
think people realize that Jupiter like
planets are quite rare in the universe
certainly many Neptunes and Neptunes are
extremely common but Jupiter is only
about 10 of sun-like stars have Jupiters
around them as far as we can tell when
you say Jupiter which aspect of Jupiter
in terms of its mass and uh it's a major
access so anything beyond about half an
au so half the distance of the Earth and
the Sun and something of order of um a
tenth of a Jupiter Mass that's the mass
of Saturn up to say 10 Jupiter masses
which is basically where you start to
get to Brown dwarfs those types of
objects appear to be somewhat unusual
most solar systems do not have Jupiters
which is really interesting because
Jupiter again like the moon seems to
have been a pivotal character in the
story of the development of our solar
system perhaps especially having a large
influence of the development of
um the late heavy bombardment and the
rate of asteroid impacts that we receive
and things like this anyway to come back
to 1625 this this jupiter-like planet
um had a hint of of something in the
data but what I mean by that is when we
looked at the transit we got the
familiar decrease in light that we
always see when a plant traps in front
of the star but we saw something extra
just on the edges we saw some extra dips
around the outside
it was right at the hairy edge of
detectability we didn't believe it
because
um I think one of the challenges of
looking for something for 10 years is
that you become your own greatest
skeptic and no matter what you're shown
you're always thinking I've been it's
like falling in love so many times and
it not working out you you convince
yourself it's never going to be it's
never going to happen not for me you
know this just isn't this isn't going to
happen and so I saw that and I I didn't
really believe it because I didn't dare
let myself believe it
but being a good scientist we knew we
had an obligation to publish it to talk
about the result and to follow it up and
to try and resolve what was going on
so we asked for Hubble Space Telescope
time which was awarded in that case that
we were one of those lucky 20 that got
telescope time and we started it uh for
about 40 hours continuously and
um to provide some context the dip that
we saw in the capital data correspond to
a neptune-sized moon around a
jupiter-sized planet which was another
reason why I was skeptical I was like
that we don't have that in the solar
system that seems so strange
and then when we got the Hubble data it
seemed to confirm exactly that there was
two really striking pieces of evidence
in the data that suggested this moon was
there another was a fairly clear second
dip in light pretty clearly resolved by
Hubble it was about a five Sigma
detection
and on top of that we could see the
planet didn't Transit when it should
have done it actually translated earlier
than we expected it to by about 20
minutes or so and so that's a Hallmark
of a gravitational interaction between
the planet and the moon we actually
expected that you can also expect that
if the moon transits after the planet
then the planet should come in earlier
than expected because the Barry Center
the center of mass lifts between the two
of them they're kind of like on a
balancing arm between them and so we saw
that as well so the phase signature
matched up the mass of the moon was
measured to be Neptune Mass
and the size of the moon was measured to
be Neptune radius and so everything just
really lined up and
um we spent months and months trying to
kill it this is my strategy for anything
interesting we just try to throw the
kitchen sink it and say we must be
tricked by something and so we tried
looking at the you know the centroid
motion of the telescope but the um the
different wavelength channels have been
observed the pixel level information and
no matter what we did we just couldn't
get rid of it and so uh we submit it to
science and I think at the time science
which is one of the top journals said to
us um would you mind calling your paper
discovery of an exomoon
and I had to push back and we said no
we're not calling it that I don't even
despite everything we've done we're not
calling a discovery we're calling it
evidence for an EXO Moon because for me
I'd want to see this repeat two times
three times four times before I really
would bet my house that this is the real
deal maybe and I do worry as I said that
perhaps that's my own skepticism
self-septicism going too far but
um I think it was the right decision and
since that paper came out there has been
continuous interest in this object
another team independently analyzed that
star and recovered actually pretty much
exactly the same resources us the same
dip the same the same wobble of the
planet and a third team looked at it and
they actually got something different
they saw the dip was diminished compared
to what we saw they saw a little hint of
a dip but not as pronounced as what we
saw and they saw the wobble as well so
there's been a little bit of tension
about
analyzing the reduction of the Hubble
data
um and so the only way in my mind to
resolve this is just to look again we
actually did propose to Hubble straight
after that and we said look if our model
is right if the moon is there it came in
late last time it transited after the
planet because of the orbit we can
calculate that it should Transit before
the planet next time
if it's not there if it doesn't Transit
before and if we even if we see a dip
afterwards we know that's not our moon
it's obviously some instrumental effect
with the data we had a causal prediction
as to where the moon should be and so I
was really excited about that but we
didn't get the telescope time and
unfortunately if you go further into the
future we no longer have the predictive
capability because it's like predicting
the weather you might be able to predict
the weather next week to some level of
accuracy but predicting the weather next
year becomes incredibly hard the
uncertainties just grow and compound as
you go forward into the future more and
more how are you able to know where
where the move would be positioned so
you're able to tell the the
orbiting like geometry and and frequency
yeah so from the uh basically from the
wobbles of the planet itself that tells
us the orbital motion of the moon it's
the reflex motion of the moon but isn't
the planet isn't it just an estimate to
where
like I'm concerned about you making a
strong prediction here because like if
you don't get
if you don't uh get the moon where the
moon leads on the next time around if
you did get Hubble time couldn't that
mean something else if you didn't see
that like because you said it would be
an instrumental I feel I I feel
um
the strong urge to disprove your which
is a really good uh imperative it's a
good way to do science but like uh this
is such a noisy signal right or blurry
signal maybe yeah low resolution signal
maybe that's the but yeah I mean it's
it's a five Sigma signal so that's
that's at the slightly uncomfortable
Edge I mean it's often said that for any
detection of a first new phenomena
you really want like a 20 25 segment
detection then there's just no doubt
that what you're seeing is Real This was
at that edge I mean I guess it's
comparable to the Higgs boson but the
Higgs boson was slightly different
because there was so much theoretical
impetuses to expect a signal at that
precise location
um a neptune-sized moon was not
predicted by anyone no one there's no
papers you can find that expect
neptune-sized moons around Jupiter sized
planets so there was I think we were
inherently skeptical about its reality
for that reason
um but this is science in action and
when we we you know we fit the wobbles
we fit the dips and we we have this 3G
geometric model for the motion of the
orbit and projecting that forward we
were we found that about 80 percent of
our projections led to the Moon to be
before so it's not 100 sure there is
there was maybe 20 of the cases it was
over here but to me that was a hard
enough uh a hard enough projection that
we felt confident that we could refute
the X which was what I really wanted I
wanted a refutable that's the best of
science a falsifiable hypothesis how can
you make progress in science if you
don't have a phosifiable testable
hypothesis and so that was the the
beauty of this particular case so
there's a numerical simulation with the
Moon
uh that fits the data that we observed
and then you can now make predictions
based on that simulation yeah
that's so cool okay it's fun these are
like little
solar systems that we can simulate on
the computer and imagine their motions
um but
we are we are pushing things to the very
limits of what's possible and that's
double-edged sword it's both incredibly
exciting intellectually but you're
always you're always risking to some
degree the pushing too far so I'd like
to ask you about the uh the the recent
paper you co-authored an excellent
survey of 70 cool giant exoplanets and
the new candidate coupler 1708 bi I
would say this I'd say there's like
three or four candidates at this point
of which we have published two of them
uh and to me uh to a quote uh compelling
and deserve follow-up observations
um and so there are to get a confirmed
detection at least in our case we would
need to see it repeat for sure one of
the problems with the some of the other
methods that have been proposed is that
you don't get that repeatability so for
instance an example of a technique that
would lack that would be gravitational
micro lensing so it is possible with a
new telescope coming up in the future
um called the Roman Space Telescope
which is basically a repurposed by a
satellite that's the size of the Hubble
mirror going up into space it will stare
at millions of stars simultaneously and
it will look to see instead of whether
any of those stars get dimmer for a
short amount of time which would be a
Transit it'll look for the opposite
it'll look to see if anything can get
brighter and that brightness increase is
caused by another planetary system
passing in front and then
gravitationally lensing light around it
to cause a brightening and so this is a
method of discovering an entire solar
system but only only for only for a
glimpse you just get a short glimpse of
it passing like a you know a ship
sailing through the night just that that
one photo of it now the problem with
that is that um it's very difficult for
you know the physics of of gravitational
lensing are not surprisingly quite
complicated and so there's many many
possible solutions so you might have a
solution which is this could be a red
dwarf star
with a Jupiter like planet around that's
one solution but another solution is
that it's a free-floating planet a rogue
Planet like Jupiter with an Earth-like
Moon around it and those two solutions
are almost indistinguishable now ideally
we would be able to repeat the
observation we'd be able to go back and
see well if the moon really is there
then we could predict its mass its
particular motion and expect it to be
maybe over here next time or something
with micro lensing it's a one snapshot
event and so for me it's intriguing as a
way of revealing something about the
examine population but I always come
back to transits because it's the only
method we really have that's absolutely
repeatable that we'll be able to come
back and prove everyone you prove to
everyone that look on the 17th of
October the moon will be over here and
the moon will look like this and we can
actually capture that image and that's
what we see with of course many EXO
players so we want to get to that same
point of full confidence full
confirmation the slam dunk detection of
these EXO moons but
um yeah it's it's been a a hell of a
journey to try and push the field into
that direction and
um there's some resistance to the
transit method not to the transmit I
just say to EXO means so the transit
method is by far the most what the most
popular method for looking for EXO
planets but um yeah as I've alluded to
EXO moons is is kind of a niche topic
within the discipline of exoplanets and
that's largely because there are people
I think are waiting for those slime
dunks and it was like the if you go back
to the first exoplanet discovery that
was made in 1995 by Misha mayor and
Didier colors
um I think it's true at the time that
they were seen as Mavericks that the
idea of looking for plants around Stars
was considered fringe science and you
know I'm sure many colleagues told them
why don't you do something more safe
like study eclipsing stars to binary
star systems we know those exist so why
are you wasting your time looking for
planets you're going to get this
um alien moniker or something thing can
you be you'll be seen as a fringe
Maverick scientist and so I think it was
quite difficult for those early Planet
Hunters to get legitimacy and be taken
seriously and so very few people risked
their careers to do it except for those
that were either emboldened to try or
had maybe the career uh maybe like a
tenure or something so they didn't have
to necessarily worry about the
implications of failure and so
once that happened once they made the
first discoveries overnight
you know everyone and their dog was
gunning into exoplas and all of a sudden
the whole you know the whole astronomy
Community shifted and huge numbers of
people that were Once Upon a Time
studying eclipse and binaries you know
changed to becoming exoplat scientists
and so that was the first wave of
exoplanet scientists we're now in a kind
of a second wave or in the third wave
where people like me to some degree kind
of grew up with the idea of exoplanets
as being normal you know I was 11 years
old I guess when the first exploit was
discovered and so to me it was a fairly
uh normal idea to grow up with and so
we've been trained in the exoplanets
from the very beginning and so that
brings
a different perspective to those who
have maybe transitioned from a different
career path
um and so I suspect with EXO moons and
probably techno signatures uh
astrobiology many of the topics which
are seen at the the fringes of what's
possible
they will all open up into becoming
mainstream one day but every there's a
lot of people who are just waiting uh
waiting for that that assuredness that
there is a secure career net ahead of
them before they commit yeah it does
seem to me that Exxon moons open
wider or open for the first time the
door to to aliens so more seriously
academically studying all right let's
let's look at like alien worlds like so
um I think it's still pretty fringe to
talk about alien life even though like
on Mars and the moons and so on you're
kind of like
you know you'll be nice but imagine the
first time to discover a living organism
that's going to change
then everybody would look like an idiot
for not focusing everything on this
because the the possibility of the
things will it's possible it might it
might be super boring it might be very
boring bacteria but even the existence
of life elsewhere yeah some I mean that
changes everything that means life is
everywhere yeah if you knew now that in
five years ten years the first life
would be discovered elsewhere you need
that in advance it would surely affect
the way you approach your entire career
as a especially someone Junior and
astronomy you would surely be like well
this is clearly going to be the
direction we have to dedicate my classes
and my training and my education towards
that direction all the new textbooks all
the yeah that's right written I mean uh
and I think there's a lot of value to
hedging like allocating some of the time
to that possibility because the kind of
Discovery will the kind of discoveries
we might get in the next few decades
um it feels what like we're on the verge
of a lot of getting a lot of really good
data and having better and better tools
that can process that data so there's
just going to be a continuous increase
of the kind of discoveries that will
open like but a slam dunk
that's hard to come by yeah I think a
lot of us are anticipating I mean we're
already seeing it to some degree with
Venus and the phosphine incident
um but we've seen it before with Bill
Clinton it's in the White House lawn
announcing life from Mars and they're
they're inevitably going to be spurious
claims or at least claims which are
um ambiguous to some degree there will
be for sure a high profile Journal like
nature or science that will one day
publish a paper saying buy a signature
Discover it or something like that on
Trappist one or some other planet and
then there will be years of back and
forth in the in the literature and that
might seem frustrating but that's how
science works it's in it that's the
mechanism of science at play of people
scrutinizing the results to intense
skepticism and it's like a crucible you
know you burn away all the relevances
until whatever is left is the truth and
so you're left with this this product
which is that okay we either believe or
don't believe that by signatures are
there so there's inevitably going to be
a lot of controversy and debate and
argument about it we just have to
anticipate that and so I think
you have to basically have a thick skin
to some degree academically to dive into
that world and you're seeing that with
um with phosphine it's been uh it's it's
been uncomfortable to watch from the
outside the kind of dialogue that some
of the scientists have been having with
each other about that because
um they get a little aggressive yeah and
you can understand you can understand
why because jealousy I don't know I
that's me saying that you as me talking
I'm sure there's I'm sure there's some
envy and jealousy involved
um on the on the
behalf of those who are not part of the
original Discovery sure but there's also
in any case just leave you know the
particular people involved in Venus
alone in any case of making a claim of
that magnitude yeah especially life
because life is pretty much one of the
biggest discoveries of all time you can
imagine scientifically
um you can see and I'm so conscious in
myself when I get closer as I said even
the much smaller goal of setting an
exomoon the ego creep in and so as a
scientist we have to be so guarded
against our own egos you see the lights
in your eyes of a Nobel Prize or yeah
um the the fame and fortune and being
Remembered in the history books and we
all
grew up in our training learning about
Newton and Einstein these Giants of the
field fireman Maxwell and you get the
idea of these individual contributions
which get immortalized for all time and
that's seductive it's why many of us
with the skill set to go into maybe
banking instead decided actually there's
something about the idea of being
immortalized and contributing towards
Society in a permanent way that is more
attractive than the financial reward of
applying my skills elsewhere so to some
degree that ego can be a benefit because
it brings in skillful people into our
field who might otherwise be tempted by
money elsewhere
but on the other hand it the closer you
get towards when you start flirting with
that Nobel Prize in your in your eyes or
you think you're on the on the verge of
seeing something you can lose
objectivity
a very famous example this is uh Barnard
star there was a planet claimed there by
Peter Van de Camp I think was in
1968-69 and at the time it would have
been the first ever EXO plan ever
claimed and
um he he felt assured that this planet
was that he was actually using the
wobbling star method but using the
positions of the Stars to see them to
claim this exoplanet
it turned out that this planet was was
not there subsequent analyzes by both
dynamicists and theorists and those
looking at the instrumental data
established fairly
um unanimously that there was no way
this planet was really there but Peter
founder Camp insisted it was there
despite overwhelming evidence that was
occurring against him
um and even to the day he died which was
I think like nine in the early 90s he
was still insisting this planet was that
even when we were starting to make the
first genuine exoplank discoveries and
even at that point I think Hubble had
even looked at that star and had totally
ruled out any possibility of what he was
talking about and so that's a problem
how do you get to a point as a scientist
where you just can't accept
anything that comes otherwise because
you're it starts out with the the dream
of Fame and then it ends in a stubborn
refusal to ever back down of course the
flip side of that
is sometimes you need that to have the
strength to carry a belief against the
entire scientific community that resists
your beliefs
and so it's it's a double-edged sword
that can happen but I guess the
distinction here is evidence yes so in
this case
the evidence was so overwhelming it
wasn't really a matter of um
interpretation it was it was you had to
collect you'd observe this star with the
same
um the same star but with maybe 10 even
100 times greater Precision the
prolonged much longer periods of time
and there was just no doubt at this
point this planet was was a mirage
um and so that's why you have to be very
careful I always say don't have a name
you know my my wife my daughter like
name this planet after me that you
discover and I can't I can't ever name a
planet after you because I'll be I won't
be objective anymore how could I ever
how could ever turn around to you and
say that client wasn't real that I named
after you so you're somebody that talks
about and is clear in your eyes and in
your way of being that you love the
process of discovery their Joy the magic
of just uh you know uh seeing something
a new observation a new idea right
um but I guess the point is when you
have that great feeling is to then
switch on the skepticism
like to start like testing
um what does this actually mean is is
this real what are the possible uh
different interpretations that could
make this a lot less Grand than I first
imagined and yeah all so both have the
wander and the skepticism all in one
brain oh yeah I think the generally the
more I want something to be true the
more I inherently doubt it and I think
that just comes from you know I I grew
up
um with a religious family and was just
sort of indoctrinated to some degree
like many children are okay that's just
normal that you know there's a garden
this is the way the world is uh God
created the Earth and then as I became
more
you know well-read and illiterate of
what was happening in the world
scientifically I started to doubt and it
really just struck me that the hardest
thing to let go of when you when you do
decide not to be religious anymore and
it's not really a like a light bulb
moment but it just kind of happens over
my over sort of 11 to 13 I think for me
it was happening but it's that sadness
of letting go of this beautiful dream
which you had in your mind of eternal
life for you know for for behaving
yourself on Earth you would have this
beautiful Heaven that you could go to
and live forever and that's very
attractive and for me personally
um that was one of the things that
pulled me against it was this it's it's
like it's too good to be true and that
it's very convenient that this could be
um this could be so and I have no
evidence directly in terms of a
scientific sense to support this
hypothesis and it just became uh really
difficult to reconcile my growth as a
scientist and I know some people find
that reconciliation I I have not maybe I
will one day
um but as a general guiding principle
which I think I I obtained from that
experience was that I have to be
extremely guarded about what I want to
be true because it's going to sway me to
say things which which are not true if
I'm not careful and that's the that's
not what we're trying to do as
scientists so you felt from a religious
perspective that there was um a little
bit of a gravitational field in terms of
your opinions like it was affecting how
you could be as a scientist like as a
scientific thinker obviously we're young
yeah I I think um
I I think that's that's true that
whenever you're
whenever there's something you want to
be true it's it's the ultimate seduction
intellectually and I worry about this a
lot with um with you know UFOs and with
um it's it's true already with things
like Venus phosphine and uh searching
for astrological signals
we have to guard against this all the
way through from however we're looking
for life however we're looking for
whatever this big question is there is a
part of us I think I would love that to
be life in the universe
um I hope there is life in the universe
but
um I'm somewhat uh been on record
several times as being fairly firm about
trying to remain consciously agnostic
about that question I don't want to make
up my mind about what the answer is
before I've collected evidence to inform
that decision that's how science should
work if I already know what the answer
is then what am I doing and that's not a
scientific experiment anymore you've
already decided so what are you trying
to learn what's the point of doing the
experiment if you already know what the
answer is there's no point it's still
complicated because so if I'm being
honest with myself
foreign
first thing I imagine uh about our world
is that we humans and me certainly is
one particular human
uh no very
my first assumption is I know almost
nothing about how anything works
so first off that actually applies for
for things that humans do know like uh
there are quantum mechanics and all the
things that there's different expertises
that I just have not dedicated to so
even even that starting point but if we
take all of knowledge as human
civilization we know almost nothing
that's kind of an assumption I have
because it seems like we keep
discovering Mysteries and it seems like
history human history is defined by
moments when we said okay we pretty much
figured it all out and then you realize
a century later you've when you said
that you didn't figure out anything okay
so that's like a starting point the
second thing I have is I feel like the
entirety of the universe is just filled
with alien civilizations
statistically
there's
the important thing that enables that
belief for me is that they don't have to
be human-like they can be anything and
it's just the fact that life exists and
just seeing the way life is on Earth
that it just finds a way it finds a way
in so many different complicated
environments it finds a way whatever
that force is that same Force has to
find a way elsewhere also
but but then if I'm also being honest
and I I don't know how many hours in a
day I spend
seriously considering the possibility
that we're alone
I don't know when I'm when I when my
heart is in mind or filled with wander I
think about all the different life
that's out there
but to really imagine that we're alone
like really imagine all the vastness
that's out there were alone that not
even bacteria
I would say you don't have to believe
that we are alone
um but you have to admit it's a
possibility of our ignorance of the
universe so far
um
you can have a belief about something
and absence of evidence
and Carl Sagan famously described as the
definition of faith if you believe
something when there's no evidence you
have faith that there's life in the
universe but you can't
you can't demonstrate you can't prove it
mathematically you can't show me
evidence of that
um but is there some some mathematically
math is a funny thing is there I mean
the way physicists think like intuition
so it's like basic reasoning
is there some value to that well I'd say
there's certainly you can certainly make
a very good argument I think you've kind
of already made one just the vastness of
the universe is is the is the default
argument people often turn to that
surely there should be others out that's
hard to imagine
um there are order of 10 to the 22 stars
in our observable universe and so really
the question comes down to what's the
probability of one of those 10 to 22
planets let's say earth like planets if
they all have Earthly planets
um going on to form life
spontaneously that's the process of
abiogenesis the spontaneous emergence of
life
also the word spontaneous is the funny
okay maybe when you spontaneous but um
not not being say uh seeded by say some
some other civilization or something
like this it naturally emerges because
even the word spontaneous
makes it seem less likely yeah like
there's there's just this chemistry and
extremely random process it could be a
very gradual process over millions of
years have grown complexity in in
chemical networks maybe there's a force
in the universe that pushes it towards
interesting complexity pockets of
complexity that ultimately creates
something like life which we can't
possibly Define yet and sometimes it
manifests itself into something that
looks like humans but it can be a
totally different kind of computational
information processing system that we're
too dumb to even visualize yeah I mean
certainly I mean it's kind of weird that
complexity develops at all right because
um it seems like the opposite to our
physical intuition returning a physics
of entropy that things should you know
complexity is hard to spontaneously
emote I shouldn't say spontaneously but
hard to emerge in general
um and so that's an interesting problem
I think there's been certainly from an
evolutionary perspective you do see
growing complexity and there's a nice
argument I think it's by gold who who
shows that if you have a a certain
amount of complexity
it can either become less complex or
more complex through random mutation and
the less complex things are stripping
away something something that was
necessary potentially to their survival
and so in general that's that's going to
be not particularly useful in its
survival and so it's going to be
detrimental to strip away a significant
amount of its useful traits whereas if
you add something the most typical thing
that you add is probably not useful at
all it's probably just it doesn't really
affect its survival negatively but it
neither does it provide any significant
benefit
but sometimes on rare occasions of
course it will be of benefit and so if
you're I have a certain level of
complexity it's hard to go back in
complexity but it's fairly easy to go
forward with enough bytes at the charity
you will eventually build up and complex
in that so it tends to be why we see
complexity growing in in certainly in an
evolutionary sense but also perhaps it's
operating in chemical networks that led
to the emergence of life I guess the
real foreign
problem I have with it with the numbers
game just come back to that is that we
are talking about a certain probability
of that occurring it may be to go from
the primordial soup however you want to
call it the ingredients that the earth
started with the organic molecules the
probability of going from that initial
condition to something that was capable
of darwinian natural selection that
maybe we could Define as life the
probability of that is maybe one percent
one percent of the time that happens in
which case you're right the universe
will be absolutely teeming with life but
it could also be 10 to the power minus
10 in which case it's one per Galaxy or
10 to the power of minus 100 in which
case the vast majority of universes even
do not have life within it or 90 or 90
said one percent you said one percent
but it could be 90 if the conditions the
chemical conditions of a planet are
correct or a moon are correct I admit
that it could be any of those numbers
and the challenges we just have no
rigorous reason to expect why 90 is any
because we're talking about a
probability for probability what is is
90 more a priori likely than 10 to the
power minus 20. well the thing is we do
have an observation n of one of Earth
and uh it's difficult to know what to do
with that what kind of intuition you
build build on top of that because on
Earth it seems like life finds a way
okay in all kinds of conditions in all
kinds of crazy conditions good and it's
able to like build up from the basic
chemistry you could say okay
uh maybe it takes a little bit of time
to develop some complicated technology
like mitochondria I don't know like
photosynthesis
fine but it seems to figure it out
figure it out and like do it extremely
well yeah but I would say you're
describing a different process I mean
um maybe I'm I'm at fault for separating
these two processes but to me you're
describing basically natural selection
Evolution at that point
um whereas I'm really describing
abogenesis which is to me a separate
distinct process do you limit it to
human scientists yes but why would it be
a separate process why why is the birth
of Life a separate process from the
process of Life hey uh like why is the
I mean we're uncomfortable with the fir
we are comfortable with a big bang we're
uncomfortable with the first thing I
think like where did this come from
right so I think I would say I just
twist that question around and say what
you're saying why is it a different
process
um why and I would say why shouldn't it
be a different process which isn't
really a good defense except to say that
we we have
we have knowledge of how naturally
Evolution natural selection Evolution
works we think we understand that
process we have almost no information
about the earlier stages of how life
emerged on our planet it may be that
you're right and it is a part of a
Continuum it may be that it is also a
distinct
improbable set of circumstances that led
to the emergence of Life as a scientist
I'm just trying to be open-minded to
both possibilities if I assert that life
must be everywhere
to me you run the risk of experimenters
bias
um if you think you know what the answer
is if you look at an Earth-like planet
and you're a new a preconditioned to
think there's a 90 chance of Life on
this planet it's going to at some level
affect your interpretation of that data
whereas if I however critical you might
be of the agnosticism that I impose upon
myself
remain open to both possibilities then I
trust in myself to make a fairer
assessment as to the reality of that
evidence for life
yeah but I I wonder sort of
scientifically and and that's really
beautiful to hear and inspiring to hear
uh I I wonder scientifically how many
firsts
we truly know of
like and then we don't eventually
explain as as actually
a a step number one million in a long
process so I think that's a really
interesting thing if there's truly first
in this universe like you know for us
the whatever happened at the Big Bang is
is a kind of first the origin of stuff
but it's just again
um
it seems like history shows that we'll
figure out that it's actually a
continuation of something but then
physicists say that time is emergent and
then our causality and time is is a very
human kind of construct that's very
possible that all of this so there could
be really firsts of a thing to which we
attach a name
so whatever we call life
maybe there is an origin of it yeah and
I would also say I'm open to the idea of
it being part of a continuation but the
continuation maybe is more broader and
it's a continuation of chemical systems
and chemical networks and what we we
call this one particular type of
chemistry and this behavior of chemistry
life
um but it is just one manifestation of
all the trillions of possible
permutations in which chemical reactions
can occur and we we assert specialness
to it because that's what we are and so
this is also true of intelligence you
could extend the same thing and say you
know we're we're looking for intelligent
life in the universe and then you
started where does where do you define
intelligence where where's that
Continuum of something that's really
like us are we alone there may be a
Continuum of chemical systems a
Continuum of intelligences out there and
um we have to be careful of our own
arrogance of as of assuming specialness
about what we are that we are some
distinct category of phenomena whereas
the universe doesn't really care about
what category we are it's just doing
what it's doing and doing everything in
you know infinite infinite diversity and
infinite combinations essentially what
it's doing and so we are we are taking
this one slice and saying No this has to
be treated separately and um I I'm open
to the idea that it could be a truly
separate phenomena but it may just be
like uh like a snowflake every
snowflake's different it may just be
that this one particular
iteration is another variant of the vast
Continuum yeah maybe the algorithm of
natural selection itself is an invention
of Earth
I kind of also tend to suspect that this
this whatever the algorithm is it kind
of operates at all levels throughout the
Universe but maybe this is a very kind
of peculiar thing that
um
where there's a bunch of chemical
systems that compete against each other
somehow for survival under limited
resources and that's a very Earth-like
thing we have a nice balance of there's
a large number of resources enough to
have a bunch of different kinds of
systems competing but not so many that
uh
they they get lazy yeah and maybe that's
why bacteria were very lazy for a long
time maybe they had they didn't have
much competition quite possibly I mean I
I tried to as as fun as it is to get
into the speculation about
um the definitions of of life and what
life does and this gross network of
possibilities
honestly for me the strongest argument
for remaining agnostic is is to avoid
that that bias in assessing data and
we've seen we've seen it I mean first of
all I talked about my channel
um and uh maybe last year or two years
ago you know he's a very famous
astronomer who in the 19th century was
claiming the evidence of canals on Mars
and from him from his perspective and
even at the time culturally it was
widely accepted that Mars would of
course have life I mean I think it's uh
seems silly to us but it was kind of
similar arguments to what we're using
now about exoplanets that well of course
there must be life in the universe how
could it just be here and so it seemed
obvious to people that when you looked
at Mars with its polar caps even you
know its atmosphere had Seasons it
seemed obvious to them that that too
would be a place where life Not only was
present but had emerged to a
civilization which actually was fairly
compromable in technology to our own
because it was building Canal systems
um of course a canal system seems a
bizarre tennis signature to us but it
was a product of their time to them that
was The Cutting Edge in technology it
should be a warning shot actually a
little bit for us that if we think you
know solar panels or building star links
or whatever space mining is like an
inevitable techno signature that may be
laughably Antiquated compared to what
other civilizations far more advanced
than this may be doing and so anyway
personal LOL he was he I think was a
product of his time that he thought life
was there inevitably even wrote about it
extensively and so when he saw these
lines these linear on the surface of
Mars to him it was just obvious they
were canals and he was he that was
experimenters by us playing out he was
told for one that he had basically the
greatest eyesight out of any of his
peers and ophthalmologists had taught
him that in Boston that his eyesight was
you know absolutely spectacular so he
just was convinced everything he saw was
was real
um and secondly he was convinced there
was life there and so it to him it just
added up and then that kind of wasted
you know Decades of research of of
treating the idea of Mars being
inhabited by this canal civilization
um but on the other hand it's maybe not
a waste because it is a lesson in
history of how we should be always on
guard against our own preconceptions and
biases about what yeah whether life is
out there and furthermore what types of
things life might do if it is there
if I were running this simulation which
we'll also talk about because you make
the case against it but if I'm running a
simulation I would definitely put you in
a room with an alien it's just to see
you mentally freak out for hours at a
time oh you for sure would have thought
you will be convinced that you've lost
your mind I mean no not not that but I
mean like if we discover Life we
discovered interesting new physical
phenomena I think the right approach is
definitely to be extremely skeptical and
be very very careful about things you
want to be true that's that's yeah I
would say I'm not like some extreme
denialist of evidence if there was if
there was compelling evidence for life
on another planet I would be the first
one to be celebrating that and be
shaking hands with the alien on the
White House alone whatever that would be
you know I grew up with Star Trek and
that was my fantasy was to you know be
Captain Kirk and fly across the Stars
meaning of the civilization so there's
nothing more I'd want to be true as I've
said but um
we we just have to guard against it when
we're we're assessing data
um but uh I'm I have to say I'm very
skeptical that we will ever have that uh
Star Trek moment even if even if there
are other civilizations out there
they're never going to be at a point
which is in technological lock step with
us similar level development even uh
intellectually the idea that they could
uh have a conversation with us even
through a translator I mean we can't
communicate with humpback whales we
can't get rid of dolphins in a
meaningful way we can sort of bark
orders at them but we can't uh have
abstract conversations with them about
things
um and so the idea that we will ever
have that fulfilling conversation I'm
deeply skeptical of and I think a lot of
us are drawn to that it is maybe a
replacement for God to some degree that
that Father Figure civilization that
might step in teach us there of our ways
and bestow wisdom Upon Our civilization
but they could equally be a giant fungus
that has doesn't even understand the
idea of social socialization because
it's the only entity on its Planet it
just swells over the entire surface and
it doesn't it's incredibly intelligent
because maybe each node communicates
with each other to create essentially a
giant neural net but it has no sense of
what communication even is and so
alien life is out there is surely going
to be extremely diverse I'm pretty
skeptical that we'll ever get that that
fantasy moment I always had as a kid of
having a dialogue within the
civilization so dialogue uh yes what
about noticing them what about noticing
signals do you hope so one thing we've
been talking about is getting signatures
biosignature techno signatures about
other planets maybe if we're extremely
lucky In Our Lifetime to be able to meet
life forms
uh get evidence of living or dead life
forms on mars or the moons of Jupiter
and Saturn what about getting signals
from outer space Interstellar signals uh
what kind of what would those signals
potentially look like
that's a hard question to answer because
we are we essentially engaging in Xeno
psychology to some degree what are the
activities of another civilization
but a lot of that is in other words
xenopsychology I apologize to interrupt
mean maybe I'm just fabricating that
word really but they're trying to guess
at the
um the machinations and motivations of
another intelligent being that was
completely evolutionary divorced from us
so it's like like you said EXO moons
it's exop psychology extrasolar yeah
psychology yeah uh Alien psychology is
another way of maybe making it more
grounded but
um the it we we can't really guess at
their their motivations too well but we
can look at the sorts of behaviors we
engage in and at least look for them
um we're always guilty that when we look
for buyer signatures we're really
looking for and even when we look for
planets we're looking for templates of
earth when we look for bias signatures
we're looking for templates of
earth-based life when we look for
tetanus signatures we tend to be looking
for templates of our own behaviors or
extrapolations of our behaviors
um so exactly there's a very long list
of tender signatures that people have
suggested we could look for the the
earliest ones were of course radio
beacons that were sort of project osma
that Frank Drake was involved in I'm
trying to look for radio signatures
which could either be
um just like blurting out high power
radio thing I was saying hey we're here
or could even have encoded within um
Galactic encyclopedias for us to unlock
which has always been the Allure of the
radio technique
um but there could also be unintentional
signatures
um for example you could have something
like the satellite system that we've
produced around the earth artificial
satellite system starlink type systems
we mentioned you could detect the glint
of lights across those satellites as
they orbit around the planet
you could set to geostationary satellite
belt which would block out some light as
the planet transferred across the star
you could detect solar panels
potentially spectrally on the surface of
the planet heat island effects New York
is hotter than New York state by a
couple of degrees because the heat
island are fair to the city and so you
could thermally map different planets
and detect these so there's a large
array of things that we do that we can
go out and hypothesize we could look for
and then on the furthest end of the
scale you have things which go far
beyond their capabilities such as warp
drive signatures which have been
proposed you get these bright flashes of
light or even gravitational wave
detections from ligo could be detected
um you could have Dyson spheres the idea
of covering it basically a star is
completely covered by some kind of
structure which collects all this all
the light from the Star to power the
civilization and that would be pretty
easily detectable to some degree because
you're you're transferring all of the
visible light thermodynamically it has
to be re-emitted so it come out as
infrared light so you have an incredibly
bright infrared star yet one that was
visibly not present at all and so there
would be a pretty intriguing signature
to look for but is there effort to look
for something like that for for
different experience out there for with
the strong infrared signal there has
been yeah that has been and there's been
uh I think in the literature there was
one with the IRA satellite which is an
infrared satellite they targeted I think
I've ordered 100 000 Stars uh nearby
stars and found no convincing examples
of what looked like a Dyson Sphere star
and then Jason Wright and his team um
Extended this I think using wise which
is another info satellite
um to look around galaxies so could an
entire galaxy have been converted into
Dyson spheres or a significant fraction
of the Galaxy which is basically the uh
the kardashev type three right this is
the when you've basically mastered the
entire Galactic pool of resources and uh
again out of a hundred thousand nearby
galaxies there appears to be no
compelling examples of what looks like a
Dyson Galaxy if you want to call it that
um so that by no means uh proves that
they don't exist or don't happen but it
seems like it's an unusual behavior for
civilization mission to get to that
stage of development and start
harvesting the entire Stellar output
unusual yes and I mean ligo is super
interesting with gravitational waves if
that kind of experiment could start
seeing some weirdness some weird signals
some that compare to the to the power of
the cosmic phenomena yeah yeah I mean
it's a whole new window to the universe
not just in terms of astrophysics but
potentially for technical signatures as
well I have to say with the with the
warp drives I am skeptical that warp
drives are possible because you have you
have kind of fundamental problem
relativity you can either really have
relativity faster than light travel or
causality you can only choose two of
those three things you really can't have
all three in a coherent Universe if you
have all three you basically end up with
the possibility of these kind of
temporal paradoxes and time loops and
grandfather paradoxes working therapy
pockets of causality something like that
like where there's uh like pockets of
consistent causality you could design it
in that way you could be you know if you
had a warp drive or a time machine
essentially you could be
um you know you can be very conscious
and careful of the way you use it so as
to not to cause paradoxes or just do it
in a local area or something but the
real fundamental problem is you always
have the ability to do it and so in a in
a vast Cosmic Universe if time machines
were all over the place uh that there's
too much risk of someone doing it right
of somebody having the option of
essentially breaking the universe with
it with this so there's a fundamental
problem Hawking has this chronology
protection conjecture where he said that
essentially that it's this just can't be
allowed because it breaks it breaks all
our laws of physics if time travel is
possible current laws of physics yes
correct yeah um and so we need to rip at
relativity I mean that's the point is
the current law is physics so you'd have
to rip up our current law of relativity
to make sense of how FDL could live in
that Universe because you can't have
relativity FTL and causality sit nice
and play nicely together
but we're currently don't have quantum
mechanics and relativity playing nice
together anyway so it's not like
everything is all a nice little fact
it's certainly not the full picture
there must be more to go yeah but
um so it's already ripped up so might as
well rip it up a little more
and then in the process actually try to
connect the two things because maybe in
the unification of uh of the standard
model and uh general relativity may be
their lies some kind of new wisdom about
of of about warp drive so by the way
warp drives is somehow messing with the
fabric
of the universe to be able to travel
faster than the speed of light yeah
you're basically bending space-time you
could also do it with a wormhole or
attack you know some of the hypothetical
FTR sets doesn't have to necessarily be
uh the Alki bear Drive the warp drive it
could be any faster than my system as
long as it travels super lumily it will
violate causality and presumably that
will be observable with ligo
uh potentially yeah potentially it
depends on I think you know the
properties of whatever the spacecraft is
um I mean one problem with warp drives
is there's all sorts of problems with
rock types but we're like the start of
that sentence one problem there's just
this one minor problem that we have to
get around but uh when it arrives at its
destination it basically collects this
vast uh this has like an event horizon
almost at the front of it and so it
collects all the collects all this
radiation at the front as it goes and
when it arrives all that radiation gets
dumped on its destination basically
completely exterminate the planet it
arrives at
um that radiation is also incident
within the shell itself there's Hawking
radiation occurring within the shell
which is pretty dangerous
um and then you know it also has it
raises all sorts of exacerbations of the
Fermi Paradox of course as well so you
might be able to explain why we don't
see
um a Galactic Empire I mean even here
it's hard you might be able to explain
why we don't see a Galactic Empire if
everybody's limited to Voyager 2 rocket
speeds of like 20 kilometers per second
or something but it's a lot harder to
explain why we don't see the stars
populated by Galactic Empires
when warp drive is imminently possible
because it makes expansion so much more
trivial that um it it makes our life
harder there was there's some wonderful
simulation work being done out at
Rochester where they actually simulate
all the stars in the galaxy or a
fraction of them and they spawn a
civilization and one of them and they
let it spread out at sublight speeds and
actually the very mixing of the Stars
themselves because the stars are not
static they're in orbit of the galactic
center and they have crossing paths with
each other if you just have a range of
even like five light years and your
speed is of order of a few percent the
speed of light is the maximum you can
muster you can populate the entire
galaxy within something like a hundred
thousand to it about a million years or
so so in order a fraction of the
lifetime of the Galaxy itself and so
this raises some uh fairly serious
problems because if any civilization in
the entire history of the uni of the
Galaxy decide to do that then you know
either we shouldn't be here or we happen
to live in this kind of rare pocket
where they chose not to populate to and
so this is sometimes called fact a
heart's fact day
um as you know the fact a is that a
civilization is not here now an alien
civilization has not is not in present
occupation of the earth and that's
difficult to
resolve with the apparent ease at which
even
a small extrapolation of our own
technology could potentially populate a
Galaxy in Far faster than Galactic
history
so to me by the way yeah the firmer
Paradox is truly a paradox for me but
I suspect that if alien visited Earth
I suspect if they do
um if they are everywhere I think
they're already here and we're too dumb
to see it
but leaving that aside
I think we should be able to in that
case have very strong
obvious signals when we look up at the
stars at the emanation of energy
required we would see we will see we'll
see some weirdness that like where these
are these kinds of stars and these are
these kinds of stars that are being
messed with like leveraging the nuclear
fusion of stars to do something useful
right the fact that we don't really see
that like maybe you can correct me
wouldn't we be able to if if there is
like alien civilizations running
galaxies wouldn't we see weirdnesses uh
from an astronomy perspective with the
with the way the stars are behaving yeah
I mean it depends exactly what they're
doing but I mean the Dyson Sphere
example is one that we already discussed
where a set of 100 000 nearby galaxies
find that they are not have all been
transformed into Dyson Sphere collectors
um you could also Imagine them doing
things like we write a paper like this
recently of starlifting where you can
extend the life of your Star by scooping
Mass off the star so you'd be you know
doing Stellar engineering essentially
um space if you're doing a huge amount
of asteroid mining uh you would have a
special signature because you're
basically filling the solar system with
dust by doing that there'd be debris
from that activity and so there are
some limits on this
um certainly we don't see
uh you know bright flashes which would
be you know one of these consequences
warp drives as I said is as they
decelerate they'd produce these bright
flashes of light we don't seem to see
evidence of those kind of things
um we don't see anything obvious around
the nearby stars or the stars that we've
served in detail beyond that that
indicate any kind of artificial
civilization the closest maybe we had
was boyajin star there was a lot of
interest in there was a star that was
just very peculiarly dipping in and out
his brightness and it was hypothesized
for a time that that may indeed be some
kind of dyson-like structure so maybe a
Dyson Sphere that's half built and so as
it comes in and out it's blocking out
huge swaths of the star it was very
difficult to explain it really with
um any kind of planet model at the time
um but an easier hypothesis that was
proposed was it could just be a large
number of comets or dust or something or
maybe a planet that had drawn broken
apart and as its fragments orbit around
it blocks out Starlight and it turned
out with subsequent observations of that
star which especially the amateur
astronomy Community made a big
contribution to as well
um that the the dips were chromatic
which was a a real important clue that
that probably wasn't a solid structure
then that was going around it it was
more likely to be dust dust is chromatic
but chromatic I mean it looks different
in different colors so it blocks out
more red light than blue light if it was
a solid structure
shouldn't do that it's it shouldn't be
it should be opaque right a solid metal
structure or something so that was one
of the clear indications and the the
behavior of in the way the light changed
or the dips changed across wavelengths
was fully consistent with the
expectations of what small particulates
would do
um and so that's that's very hard I mean
the real problem with
alien hunting
technical term this is this is the real
one problem yeah one problem with the
warp drive and the one problem with the
alien hunting yes but well actually I'd
say there's three big problems for me
with any search for life which includes
UFOs or the way to fossils on Mars is
that aliens have three unique properties
as a hypothesis one is they have
essentially unbounded explanatory
capability so there's almost no
phenomena I can show you that you
couldn't explain with aliens to some
degree you could say well the aliens
just have some super high tech uh way of
creating that illusion
um the second one would be unbounded
avoidance capacity so I might see a UFO
tomorrow or and then the next day and
then the next day and then predict I
should see it on Thursday at the end of
the week but then I don't see it but I
could always get out of that and say
well that's just because they chose not
to come here you know they have this
they can always avoid future
observations fairly easily
um if you survey an exoplanet for
biosignatures and you don't see oxygen
you don't see methane that doesn't mean
there's no one living there they could
always be either tricking their
atmosphere engineering it we actually
wrote a paper about that how you can use
lasers to hide your biosignatures as in
fact civilization
um or you could just be living
underground or underwater or something
where there's no bio signatures so you
can never really disprove this life on
another planet or another star it has
infinite avoidance and then finally the
third one is that that we have
incomplete physical understanding of the
universe so if I see a new phenomena
which boyajian style is a good example
of that we saw this new phenomena of
these strange dips we've never seen
before
it was hypothesized immediately this
could be aliens it's like a god of the
gaps but it turned out to be incomplete
physical understanding and so that that
happens all the time in the first Pulsar
that was discovered same story
um Jocelyn Bell kind of somewhat uh
tongue-in-cheek called it little green
man one because it looked a lot like the
radio signature that was expected from a
civilization but of course it turned out
to be a completely new type of star that
we had never seen before which was a
neutron star
um with these two Jets coming out the
top of it and so
um that's a challenge those three things
are really really difficult in terms of
experimental design for a scientist to
work around something that can explain
anything can avoid anything so it's
almost unforcifiable and could always
just be to some degree as you said we
have this very limited knowledge of the
infinite possibilities of physical law
and we're probably only scratching the
surface
each time and we've seen it so often in
history we may just be detecting some
new phenomena well that last one
I think I'm a little more okay with
making mistakes on yeah which is because
it's exciting still but because no
matter so you might exaggerate the
importance of the discovery but the
whole point
is to try to find stuff in this world
that's weird and try to characterize
that weirdness sure you can throw a
little green man as a label on it but
eventually
it like it's as mysterious and as
beautiful as interesting as little
agreement like we we tend to think that
there's some kind of threshold but like
there's all kinds of weird organisms on
this Earth that operate very differently
than humans that are super interesting
uh the human mind is super interesting I
mean like uh weirdness and complexity
is
is as interesting in any of its forms as
what we might think from Hollywood what
aliens are so like that that's that's
okay looking for weirdness is on Mars
that's one of the best sales pitchers to
do tennis signature work is that you
know we always have that as our fullback
that that we're going to look for alien
signatures if we fail we're gonna
discover some awesome new physics along
the way and so even a uh any kind of
signature that we detect is always going
to be interesting
um and so that that compels us to
um have not only the question of looking
for life in the universe but it can it
gives us a strong scientific grounding
as to why this sort of research should
be funded and should be executed because
it always pushes the Frontiers knowledge
I wonder if we'll be able to discover
and be open enough
to a broad definition of aliens where we
see some kind of techno signature
basically like a touring test like this
thing is intelligent like it's
processing information in a very
interesting way but but you can say that
about chemistry you could say that about
physics
maybe not physics chemistry like
interesting complex chemistry you could
say that this is processing this is
storing information this is propagating
information over time so I mean I want I
it's a gray area between a living
organism that we would call an alien and
a thing that's super interesting is able
to carry some kind of intelligence yeah
information is a really useful way to
frame what we're looking for though
because it then you'll then you're
divorced from making assumptions about
even a civilization necessarily or
anything like that so any kind of
information signature indeed you can
take things like the light curve from
boyaging star and ask what is the
minimum number of free parameters or the
minimum information content that must be
encoded within the slide curve and the
hope is that maybe from you know a good
example be from a radio signature you
just text something that has you know a
thousand megabytes of of parameters
essentially contained within it that's
pretty clearly at that point not the
product of a natural process but it's
any natural process that we could
possibly imagine with our current
understanding the universe and so
thinking even if we can't decode which
actually I'm skeptical would be able to
ever decode it in our lifetimes it would
probably take decades to fully ever
figure out what they're trying to tell
us but if there was a message there we
could at least know that there is a high
information content and there is
complexity and that this is a attempt at
communication information transfer and
leave it to our subsequent generations
to figure out what exactly it is they're
trying to say
what again a wild question and thank you
for uh uh
entertaining them entertaining them I
really really appreciate that
um but what kind of signal in our
lifetime what kind of thing do you think
might happen
could possibly happen
where the scientific Community would be
convinced that there's alien
civilizations out there like what uh she
already said maybe a strong infrared
signature for something like a Dyson
Sphere yeah that's possibly that that's
always something to be a little bit
ambiguous
um because right that's the challenge
starting to interrupt is where
your brain would be like you as a
scientist would be like I know it's
ambiguous but this is really weird yeah
I think
if he had some I can imagine something
like a prime number sequence
or a mathematical sequence like the
Fibonacci series something being
broadcast radically provable that this
is not a physical phenomenon right I
mean yeah prime numbers is a pretty good
case because there's no natural
phenomena that produces prime number
sequences it seems to be a purely an
abstract mathematical concept as far as
I'm aware and so if we detected uh you
know if she was a radio Blitz that were
following that sequence it would be
pretty clear to me or it could even be
uh you know cast that you can suggested
that Pi could be encoded in that or you
might use the hydrogen line but multiply
by pi like some very specific uh
frequency of the universe like a
hydrogen line but multiply it by a
abstract mathematical constant that
would imply strongly that there was
someone behind the scenes operating that
um as sorry stored in which phenomena
though there's a thing of a radio wave
but the information I mean we kind of
toyed with this um
uh idea in a video I did about
hypothetical civilization on my channel
but one kind of fun way I do want to
bring the this conversation towards time
a little bit and thinking about
um not just looking for life and
intelligence around us right now but
looking into the past and even into the
future to some degree or communicating
with the future and so we had this fun
experiment of imagining a civilization
that was born at the beginning of the
history of the Galaxy and being the
first and what it would be like for them
and they were desperately searching for
evidence of life but couldn't find it
and so they decided to try and leave
something behind for future
civilizations to discover to tell them
about themselves but of course a radio
signage is not going to work there
because it has have a power source and
that's a piece of Machinery it's going
to eventually break down it's gonna be
hard to maintain that for billions of
years time scale and so you wanted
something that was kind of passive that
doesn't require an energy source but can
somehow transmit information which is
hard to think about something that
satisfies those criteria but there was a
proposal by one of my colleagues Connor
which inspired a lot of us in techno
signatures and he suggested that you
could build artificial transiters so you
could be build sheets of material that
transit in front of the star maybe one
thin sheet passes across first then two
then three then five and seven so you
could follow the prime number sequence
of these and so there'd be a clear
indication that someone had manufactured
those but they don't require any energy
source because they're just sheets of
material in orbit of the star they would
eventually degrade from micrometeorites
so maybe their orbits would become
destabilized but they should have
lifetimes far exceeding the lifetime of
any uh battery or mechanical electronic
system that we could at least without
energy conceive of building and so you
can imagine an extending that and how
could you encode not just a prime number
sequence but maybe in the spatial
pattern of this very complex light curve
we see you could encode more and more
information through 2D shapes and the
way those occupations happen and maybe
uh you could even encode uh messages and
and in-depth information from you know
you could even imagine it being like a a
lower layer of information which is just
the prime number sequence but then you
look closely and you see the smaller
divots embedded within those that have a
deeper layer of information to extract
um and so to me something like that
would be pretty compelling that that was
somebody who would mind if unless it's
just a a very impressive hoax that would
be a pretty compelling evidence in this
civilization and actually the methods of
um astronomy right now are kind of
marching towards
being able to better and better detect a
signal like that yeah I mean to some
degree it's just building bigger
aperture in Space the bigger the
telescope the the finer ability to
detach those minute signals do you think
the current sort of the scientific
Community another weird question but
just the observations that are happening
now do you think they're ready for a
prime number sequence in in the um so if
if we're using the current method the
transit timing variation method like do
you think
you're ready do you have the tools to
detect the prime number sequence
yeah for sure I mean there's
two hundred thousand stars that kept
them monitored and it monitored them all
the time it took a photo of each one of
them every 30 minutes to measure their
brightness and it did that for four and
a half years and so you have already and
Tess is doing it right now another
mission and so you have already an
existing catalog and people are uh
genuinely scouring through each of those
light curves with Automated machine
learning techniques we even developed
some on our own team that can look for
weird Behavior we wrote a code called
the weird detector for instance that of
course you know it was just the most
generic thing possible let don't assume
anything about the signal shape just
look for anything that repeats the
distinguish rate can be anything can we
kind of learn the template of the signal
from the data itself and then we it's
like a template matching filter to see
if that repeats many many times in the
data and so we actually applied that and
found a bunch of interesting stuff but
we didn't see anything that was the
prime number sequence at least on the
Kepler data about 200 000 Stars which
sounds like a lot but compared to 200
billion stars in the Milky Way it's
really just scratching the surface so
one because there could be something
much more generalizable than the prime
number sequence it's ultimately the
question of a signal that's very
difficult to compress
in the general
sensible compressed means so maybe as we
get better and better machine learning
methods that automatically figure out
analyze the data to to understand how to
compress it just you'll be able to
discover data that's for some reason
it's not compressible
but then you know compression really is
a bottomless pit because like that's
really what intelligence is is being
able to compress information yeah and to
some degree the more you I would imagine
I don't work in compression algorithms
but I would imagine the more you
compress your signal
um the the more assumptions that kind of
go on behalf of the decoder the more
skilled they really have to be you know
some of the a prime number sequence is
completely unencoded information
essentially but um if you look at the
Arecibo message
they were fairly careful with their
pixelation of this simple uh image they
sent to try and
make it as interpretable as possible to
be that even a dumb alien would be able
to figure out what we're trying to show
them here because there's all sorts of
conventions and rules that are built in
that we we tend to presume when we
design our messages and so if your
message is assuming they know how to do
an MP3 decoder particular compression
algorithm I'm sure they could eventually
reverse engineer it and figure it out
but you're you're making it harder for
them to get to that point so maybe I
always think you probably would have a
two-tier system right you'd probably
have some lower tier key system and then
maybe beneath that you'd have a deeper
compressed layer of more in-depth
information
what about maybe
observing physical actual physical
objects so first let me go to your Tweet
as a source of inspiration uh you
tweeted that it's interesting to ponder
that if Oort clouds are ever mined by
the systems of alien civilizations
mining equipment from billions of years
ago could be in our org Cloud since the
Oort clouds are they they extend really
really really really far outside the the
actual star yeah that so you know mining
equipment just like basic boring mining
equipment out there I don't know if
there's something interesting to say
about or claws themselves that that are
interesting to you and about possible
non-shiny uh light emitting mining
equipment from Alien civilization yeah I
mean that's all I mean that's kind of
the beauty of the field of techno
signatures and looking for life is
you can find inspiration and
intellectual joy in just the smallest
little thing that starts a whole thread
of building upon it and wondering about
the implications and so in this case I
was just really struck by we couldn't
mentioned this a little bit earlier the
idea that stars are not static we tend
to think of the Galaxy as having stars
in a certain location from the center of
the Galaxy and they kind of live there
but in truth the stars are not only
orbiting around the center of the Galaxy
um but those orbits are themselves
changing over time they're processing
and so in fact the orbits look more like
a spirograph if you've ever done those
as a kid it kind of whirl around and
Trace out all sorts of strange patterns
and so the Stars intersect with one
another and so the current closest star
to us is Proxima Centauri which is about
4.2 light years away but it will not
always be the closest star and over
millions of years it will be supplanted
by other stars in fact data will come
even closer than proximo within just a
couple of light years and that's been
happening not just we can project that
will happen over the next few million
years but that's been happening
presumably throughout the entire history
of the Galaxy for billions of years and
so if you went back in time it you know
there would have been all sorts of
different nearest Stars right different
stages of the Earth's history and those
stars are so close that they're all
clouds do intermix with one another so
the orc card can extend out to even a
light year or two around the earth
there's some debate about exactly where
it ends it probably doesn't really have
a definitive end but kind of more just
kind of Peters out more and more and
more as you go further away whether for
people who don't know nor Cloud I don't
know what the technical definition is
but a bunch of rocks are kind of no
objects that orbit the the the star and
they can extend really really great
because these are objects that probably
are mostly icy Rich they were probably
formed fairly similar distances to
Jupiter and Saturn but we're scattered
out through the interactions of those
giant planets we see a circular disk of
objects around us which kind of looks
like the asteroid belt but just for the
way called the Kuiper belt and then
further beyond that you get the all
clout and the all cloud is not in a disk
it's just a sphere it kind of surrounds
Us in all directions
so these are objects that were scattered
out through three-dimensionally in all
different directions
and so those objects are potentially
resources first especially if you were
planning to do an Interstellar mission
one day you might want to mine the water
that's embedded within those and use
that as either oxygen or a fuel for your
rocket and so it's quite possible and
there's also some rare earth metals and
things like that as well but it's quite
possible that a civilization might use
all Cloud objects as a jumping off point
um or or in the Kuiper belt you have
things like planet nine evens that's
there might even be objects Beyond in
the Oort cloud which are actually
planet-like that we just cannot detect
these objects are very very faint so
that's why they're so hard to see I mean
even planet nine is hypothesized to
exist but we've not been able to confirm
its existence because it's at something
like a thousand a u away from us a
thousand times the distance of the Earth
from the Sun and so even though it's
probably larger than the earth the
amount of light it reflects from the sun
the sun is what just looks like a star
at that point so far away from it that
it barely reflects anything back it's
extremely difficult to detect so there's
all sorts of Wonders that may be lurking
out in the outer solar system
and so this has leads you to wonder
um
you know in the orc cloud
that old Cloud must have intermixed with
other raw clouds in the past and so what
fraction of the hook cloud is truly
belongs to us belongs to the what was
scattered from Jupiter and Saturn what
fraction of it could in fact be uh
Interstellar visitors and of course
we've got excited about this recently
because of omuamua this into cell
asteroid which seemed to be at the time
the first evidence of an Interstellar
object but when you think about the all
Cloud intermixing
um it may be that a large fraction of
comets comets are seeded from the Oort
cloud that eventually come in some of
those comets May indeed have been
Interstellar in the first place that we
just didn't know about through this
process
um there even is an example I can't
remember the name there's an example of
a comment that has a very peculiar
special signature that has been
hypothesized to have actually been an
Interstellar visitor but one that was
essentially sourced through this awk
Cloud mixing and so this is kind of
intriguing
um and also you know the outer solar
system is just such a it's like at the
bottom of the ocean we know so little
about what's on the bottom of our own
plants ocean and we know next to nothing
about watching the outskirts of our own
solar system it's all Darkness yeah so
like
that that's one of the things is to
understand the phenomena we need light
and we need to see how light interacts
with it or what light M A's from it
but most of our universe is Darkness so
it's
there could be a lot of interesting
stuff I mean this is where your interest
is with the with the cool worlds and the
interesting stuff lurks in the darkness
right basically all of us you know 400
years of astronomy are only window into
the universe has been light and that has
only changed quite recently with the
discovery of gravitational waves that's
now a new window and hopefully uh well
to some degree I guess solar neutrinos
we've been detecting from art but they
come from the certain Interstellar space
but we may be able to soon detect
neutrino messages as even hypothesized
as a way of communicating between
civilizations as well or just do
neutrino telescopes to study the
universe and so there's a growing
interest in what we'd call
multi-messenger astronomy now so not
just messages from light but messages
from these but the physical
packets of information that are coming
our way but when it comes to the outer
solar system
light really is our only window there's
two there's two ways of doing that one
is you detect the light from the all
Cloud object itself which as I just said
is very very difficult there's another
trick which we do in the Kuiper belt
especially and that's called um an
occultation and so sometimes those
objects will just pass in front of a
distant star just coincidentally these
are very very brief moments they last
for less than a second and so you have
to have a very fast camera to detect
them which conventionally astronomers
don't usually build fast cameras most of
the phenomena we observe occurs on hours
minutes stays even but now we're
developing cameras which can take you
know thousands of images per second and
yet do it at the kind of astronomical
Fidelity that we that we need for this
kind of precise measurement and so you
can see these these very fast dips you
even get these kind of diffraction
patterns that come around which are
really cool to look at and that's I kind
of love it because it's almost like
passive radar your you have these
pinpricks of light imagine that you live
in a giant black sphere but there's
these little pinholes that have been
poked and through those pinholes almost
laser light is shining through and
inside this black sphere there are
unknown things wandering around drifting
around that we are trying to discover
and sometimes they will pass in front of
those little Pencil Thin laser beams and
block something out and so we can tell
that it's there and it's not an active
radar because we didn't actually you
know beam anything out and get a
reflection off which is what the sun
does the Sun's light comes off and it
comes back that's more like an active
radar system there's more like a passive
radar system where we are just listening
very intently and so
um I'm kind of so fascinated by that the
idea that we could map out the rich
architecture of the outer solar system
just by doing something that we could
have done potentially for a long time
okay which is just listening in the
right way just just tuning Our
instrumentation to the correct way of of
not listening but viewing the universe
to catch those objects yeah I mean it's
really fascinating it seems almost
obvious that your efforts when projected
out and over like 100 200 years will
have a really good map three even
methods that basically Transit timing
high resolution Transit timing but
basically the planetary and the uh the
planet satellite movements that of all
the different
star systems out there yeah and it could
revolutionize the way we think about the
solar system I mean that revolution has
happened several times in the past when
we discovered Vesta in the 19th century
um that was I think the the seventh
planet for a while or the eighth planet
when it was first discovered and then we
discovered Ceres and there was a bunch
of asteroid objects Janus and so for a
while the textbooks had
um there was something like 13 planets
in the solar system and then they and
then that was just a new capability that
was emerging to detach those small
objects and then we ripped that up and
said no no we're going to change the
definition of a planet and then the same
thing happened when we started looking
the outer skirts of the solar system
again we found Eris we found cedner
these objects which resembled Pluto and
the more and more of them we found make
make and eventually we again had to
rethink the way we even contextualize
what a planet is and what the nature of
the outer solar system is so regardless
as to what you think about the debate
about whether Pluto should be demoted or
not which I know often invokes a lot of
strong feelings it is an incredible
achievement that we were able to
transform our view of the solar system
in a matter of years just by basically
you know charge coupled devices the
things that's in in cameras
um though the invention of that device
allowed us to detect objects which were
much further away much fainter and
revealed all of this stuff that was
there all along and so it that's the
beauty of astronomy that's just uh so
much to discover and even in our own
backyard do you ever think about this do
you imagine what are the things that
will completely change astronomy over
the next hundred years like if you
transport yourself forward 100 years
what are the things that will blow your
mind when you look at wait what would it
be just a very high resolution mapping
of things like holy crap like one
surprising thing might be holy crap
there's
like Earth-like moons everywhere yeah
another one could be just totally
different devices for sensing
yeah I think you usually astronomy moves
forward dramatically and Science in
general when you have a new
technological capability come online for
the first time
um and we kind of just gave examples of
that there with the solar system so what
kind of new capabilities might emerge in
the next 100 years the capability I
would love to see is not just I mean we
in the next 10 20 years we're hoping to
take these pale blue dot images we spoke
about so that requires building
something like jwst but on even larger
scale and optimize for direct Imaging
and have to have either coronagraph or a
star shade or something to block out the
Starlight and reveal those pale blue
dots so in the next sort of decades I
think that's the achievement that we can
look forward to in our lifetimes is to
see photos of other Earths going beyond
that maybe in our lifetimes towards the
end of our lifetimes perhaps I'd love it
if we yeah I think it's technically
possible as breakthrough stars are
giving us a lot of encouragement with to
maybe send a small probe to the nearest
stars and start actually taking high
resolution images of these objects
there's only so much you can do from far
away
if you want to have and we can see it in
the solar system I mean there's only so
much you can learn about Europa by
pointing Hubble Space Telescope at it
but if you really want to understand
that that Moon you're going to have to
send something to orbit it to hopefully
land on it and drill down to the surface
and so the idea of even taking a flyby
and doing a snapshot photo that gets
beamed back that could be doesn't even
have to be more than 100 pixels by 100
pixels that even that would be a
completely game-changing capability to
be able to truly image these objects and
um maybe at home in our own solar system
we can certainly get to a point where we
produce crude maps of exoplanets
um one of the kind of the ultimate limit
of what a telescope could do is governed
by its size and so the largest telescope
you could probably ever build would be
one that was the size of the sun
there's a clever trick for doing this
without physically building a telescope
that's the size of the sun and that's to
use the Sun as a gravitational lens this
was proposed I think by vaneshleman in
like 1979 but it builds upon Einstein's
theory of General activity of course
that there is a warping of light a
bending of light from the sun's
gravitational field and so a distant
Starlight is like a magnifying glass
anything that bends light is is
basically can be used as a telescope
it's going to bend light to a point now
it turns out the Sun's gravity is not
strong enough to create a you know a
particularly great telescope here
because the focus point is really out in
the Kuiper belt it's at 550 astronomical
units away from the earth so 550 times
further away from the Sun than we are
and we've you know that's beyond any of
our spacecraft we've ever gone so you
have to send a spacecraft to that
distance which would take
30 40 years even optimistically
improving our chemical propulsion system
significantly you'd have to bound it
into that orbit but then you could use
the entire Sun as your telescope and
with that kind of capability you could
image planets to kilometer scale or
resolution from afar and that that
really makes you wonder I mean if we can
conceive maybe we can't engineer it but
if we can conceive of such a device
what might other civilizations be
currently observing about our own planet
um and
perhaps that is uh why nobody is is
visiting us because there is so much you
can do from afar that to them that's
enough they you know maybe they can get
to the point where they can set our
radio leakage
um they can drift out to restaurant in
you know television signals
um they can map out our surfaces they
can tell we have cities they can even do
infrared mapping of the heat island
effects and all this kind of stuff they
can tell the chemical composition of our
planet and so that might be enough maybe
they don't need to come down to the
surface and study atopla you know do
anthropology and see what our
civilization is like
um but there's certainly a huge amount
you can do which is significantly
cheaper to some degree than flying there
just by exploiting cleverly the physics
of the universe itself
so your intuition is this very well may
be true the observation might be way
easier than travel
from uh from our perspective from an
alien perspective like we could get very
high resolution
Imaging before we can ever get there it
depends on what what information you
want if you want um to know the chemical
composition
um and and you want to know kilometer
scale maps of the planet then you could
do that from afar with some uh version
of these kind of gravitational lenses if
you want to do better than that if you
want to image a newspaper sat on the
porch of somebody's house you're gonna
have to fly there there's no way unless
you had you know a task at the size of
such serious a star or something you
just simply cannot collect enough light
to do that from many light years away
um so there is certainly uh
reasons why visiting will always have
its place depending what kind of
information you want
um we've proposed in my team actually
that the sun is is a is the ultimate
Pinnacle of telescope design but flying
to a thousand Au is a real pain in the
butt because it's just going to take so
long and so a more practical way of
achieving this maybe to use the Earth
now the Earth doesn't have anywhere near
enough gravity to create a substantial
gravitational lens but it has an
atmosphere and an atmosphere refracts
light it bends light so whenever you see
a sunset just as the sun standing below
the Horizon it's actually already
Beneath The Horizon it's just the light
is bending through the atmosphere it's
actually already about half a degree
down beneath and what you're seeing is
is that is that curvature of the light
path and your brain interprets it of
course to be following a straight line
because your brain always thinks that
um and so you can use that bending
whenever you have bending you have a
telescope and so we've proposed to my
team that you could use this refraction
to similarly create an earth-sized
telescope called the terrascope the
tyroscope yeah great video Yeah and uh
there's the other paper on the telescope
I do yeah great um sometimes get
confused this because they've heard of
an earth-sized telescope because if they
may have heard of The Event Horizon
telescope which took an image of
um what's the taken an image right now
at the center of our black hole and it's
very impressive and it previously did
Messi 87 a nearby supermassive black
hole and so those images were
interferometric so they were small
telescopes scattered across the Earth
and they combined the light paths
together interferometrically to create
effectively an earth-sized
um angular resolution telescopes always
have two properties there's the angular
resolution which is how small of a thing
you can see on the surface and then
there's the magnification how much
brighter does that object get versus
just your eye or some small object now
what what the Event Horizon telescope
did it traded off
um amplification or magnification for
for the angular resolution that's what
it wanted it wanted that high angle
resolution but it doesn't really have
much Photon collecting power because
each telescope individually is very
small the terrascope is different
because it is literally collecting light
with a with a light bucket which is
essentially the size of the Earth and so
that gives you both benefits potentially
not only the high angle resolution that
a large aperture promises you but also
actually physically collects all those
photons so you can detect light from
very very far away through the outer
edges of the Universe
um and so we yeah we propose this as a
possible future
technological way of achieving these
these extreme
goals ambitious goals we have in
astronomy but um it's a very difficult
system to test because you essentially
have to fly out to these Focus points
and these Focus points lie beyond the
moon so you have to have
someone who is willing to fly beyond the
moon and hitchhike an experimental
telescope onto it and do that cheaply if
it was something doing low earth orbit
it'd be easier you could just attach a
cubesat to the next Falcon 9 rocket or
something and test it out it probably
only cost you a few tens of thousands
dollars maybe a hundred thousand dollars
but there's basically no one who flies
out that far except for bespoke Missions
such as like a mission that's going to
Mars or something that would that would
pass through that kind of space and they
typically don't have a lot of leeway in
excess payload that they're willing to
strap on for radical experiments so
that's been the problem with it in
theory it should work beautifully but
it's a very difficult idea to
experimentally test can you elaborate
where the focal point is that far away
so you get about half a degree Bend from
the Earth's atmosphere
um when you're looking the Sun at the
Horizon and you get that two times over
if you're outside of the planet's
atmosphere because it comes you know the
star is half a Bend to use on the
horizon then half a degree back out
either way so you get about a one degree
Bend you take the rates of the earth
which is about seven thousand kilometers
and do your arctan function you'll end
up with a distance that's about two it's
actually the the inner focal points
about two-thirds the distance of the
Earth Moon system the problem with that
inner focal point is not useful because
that light Ray path had to basically
scrape the surface of the Earth so it
passes through the clouds it passes
through all the thick atmosphere gets a
lot of Extinction along the way if you
go higher up in altitude you get less
Extinction in fact you can even go above
the clouds and so that's even better
because the clouds obviously going to be
a pain in the neck for doing anything
Optical but the problem with that is
that the atmosphere because it gets
thinner at higher altitude it bends
light less and so that pushes the focal
point out so the most useful focal point
is actually about three or four times
the distance of the Earth Moon
separation and so that's what we call
one little garage points essentially out
there and so there was a stable orbit
it's kind of the outermost stable orbit
you could have around the Earth
um so the atmosphere
uh does bad things to to the signal yeah
it's it's absorbing light
um is that possible to reconstruct this
the to to remove the noise whatever so
it's just strength it's not nothing else
it's possible to reconstruct I mean to
some degree we do this as a technology
called Adaptive Optics that can correct
for what's called wavefront errors that
happen through the Earth's atmosphere
the Earth's atmosphere is turbulent it
is not a
single plane of air of the same density
there's all kind of Wiggles and currents
in the air and so that each little layer
is uh bending light in in slightly
different ways and so the light actually
kind of follows a wiggly path on its way
down what that means is that
um two light rays which are traveling at
slightly different spatial separations
from each other will arrive at the
detector at different times because one
maybe goes on more or less a straight
path and the one Wiggles down a bit more
before it arrives and so you have an
incoherent
um light source
um and when you're trying to image
reconstruction you always want a
coherent light source so the way they
correct for this is that this if this
path had to travel a little bit faster
uh the straight one goes faster and the
wiggly one takes longer the mirror is
deformable and so you actually bend the
mirror on this on the on the straight
one down a little bit to make it an
equivalent light path distance so the
mirror itself has all these little
actuators and it's actually made up of
like thousands of little elements almost
looks like a liquid mirror because they
can manipulate it in kind of real time
and so they scan the atmosphere with a
laser beam to tell what the deformations
are in the atmosphere and then make the
corrections to the mirror to account for
it that's amazing so you could you could
do something like this for the terrorist
group but it would be
um it's cheaper and easier to go above
the atmosphere and just fly out I think
so it would be very it's a very that's a
very challenging thing to do and
normally when you do Adaptive Optics as
it's called you're looking straight up
so you're you know or very close to
straight up if you look at the Horizon
we basically never do astronomical
observations on the horizon because
you're looking through more atmosphere
the if you go straight up you're looking
at the thinnest portion of atmosphere
possible but as you go closer and closer
towards the horizon you're increasing
what we call the air mass the amount of
air you have to travel through so here
it's kind of the worst case because
you're going through the entire
atmosphere in and out again with a
telescope so you'd need a very
impressive adaptive optic system to
correct for that so yeah I would say
it's probably simpler at least for proof
of principle just to test it with um
with with with having some satellite
that was at a much wider orbit now
speaking of traveling out into deep
space you already mentioned this a
little bit uh
you uh made a beautiful video called The
Journey to the End of the Universe
and sort of at the start of that you're
talking about office Centauri
so what would it take for humans
or for human-like creatures to travel
out to Alpha Centauri
there's a few different ways of doing it
I suppose
um one is it depends on how fast your
ship is that's always going to be the
determining Factor if we devised some
inside proportion system that could
travel a fraction of the speed of light
then we could do it in our lifetimes
which is I think what people normally
dream of when they think about
Interstellar you know proportion and
travel that you could literally step
onto the spacecraft maybe a few years
later you step off and have a century B
you walk around the surface and come
back and visit your family there would
be of course a lot of relativistic time
dilation as a result of that trip you
would have aged a lot less than people
back on Earth by traveling close to the
speed of light for some fraction of time
um the challenge of this of course is
that we have no such propulsion system
that can achieve this so but you think
it's possible like uh so yeah
uh you have a paper called the Halo
drive feel free relatively propulsion
large masses via recycled Boomerang
photons
so uh do you think uh first of all what
is that and second of all uh how
difficult are alternate propulsion
systems yeah so the before taking the
Halo drive there was there was an idea
because I think the Halo drive
is not going to solve this problem uh
I'll talk about the Halo drive in a
moment but the Halo drive is useful for
a civilization which is a bit more
advanced than this that has spread
across the stars and it's looking for a
cheap highway system to to get across
the Galaxy
for that first step
um because just to context that the the
Halo drive requires a black hole so
that's why you're not going to be able
to do this on the Earth right now
um but there are lots of black holes in
the Milky Way if that's the good news so
we'll come to that in a moment but if
you're trying to travel to Alpha
Centauri without a black hole
um then the the most you know there are
some ideas out there there was a project
idalis and project Icarus there were two
projects that the
British interplanetary Society conjured
up on sort of a 20 30 year time scale
and they asked themselves if we took
existing and speculatively uh but
realistic attempts at Future technology
that are emerging over the next few
decades how far can we push into that uh
travel system and they settled on Fusion
drives in in that so if we had the
ability to essentially uh either
detonate you can also Imagine That kind
of nuclear fission or nuclear fusion
bombs going off behind the spacecraft
and propelling it that way or having
some kind of successful nuclear fusion
reaction
um which obviously we haven't really
demonstrated yet as a propulsion system
then you could achieve something like 10
the speed of light in those systems but
these are huge spacecrafts I think you
need a huge spacecraft if you're going
to take people along
um the conversation recently is actually
switched and that's that idea is kind of
seems a little bit Antiquated now and
most of us have kind of given up in the
idea of people physically biologically
stepping on board the spacecraft and
maybe we'll be sending something that's
more like a micro probe that maybe just
weighs a gram or two and that's much
easier to accelerate you could push that
with a laser system to very high speed
get it to maybe 20 the speed of light it
has to survive the journey probably a
large fraction of them won't survive the
journey but they're cheap enough that
you could maybe manufacture millions of
them and some of them do arrive and able
to send back an image or maybe even if
you wanted to have a person there we
might have some way of doing like a
telepresence or some kind of delayed
telepresence or
um some kind of reconstruction of the
planet which is sent back so you can
digitally interact with that environment
in a way which is
um not real time but representative of
what that planet would be like to be on
the surface so we might be more like
digital visitors to these plants
certainly far easier practically to do
that than physically forcing this wet
chunk of meat to fly light years across
space to do that
um and so that's maybe uh something we
can imagine down the road the Halo drive
as I said is thinking even further ahead
and if you did want to launch large
masses large masses could even be
planet-sized things in the case of the
Halo drive you can use black holes
so this is kind of
um a trick of physics you know I often
think of the universe as like a big
computer game and you're trying to find
cheat codes hacks exploits that the
Universe didn't intend for you to use
but once you find them you can address
all sorts of interesting capabilities
that you didn't previously have yeah and
the Halo drive does that with black hole
so if you have two black holes which are
very common situation a binary black
hole and they're inspiring towards each
other ligers detected I think dozens of
these things maybe even over 100 at this
point and these things as they merge
together they uh the pre-merger phase
they're they're orbiting each other very
very fast even close to the speed of
light and so Freeman Dyson uh before he
passed away I think in the 70s he had
this provocative paper called
gravitational machines and he suggested
that you could use neutron stars as a
Interstellar propulsion system
and neutron stars are sort of the
um
the you know the lower Mass version of
binary black hole system essentially
in this case he suggested just doing
gravitational slingshot just fly your
spacecraft into this uh very Compact and
relativistic binary system and you do
need neutron stars because if there were
two stars they'd be physically touching
each other so the neutron stars are so
small like 10 kilometers across they can
get really close to each other and have
these very very fast orbits with respect
to each other
you shoot your spacecraft through right
through the middle like throwing through
the eye of a needle and you do a
slingshot around one of them and you do
it around the one that's coming sort of
towards you so when I'm becoming away
you want to be coming towards you any
one point and then you could basically
steal some of the kinetic energy in the
slingshot in principle you can sell up
to twice the speed you can take your
speed and it becomes your speed plus
twice the speed of the black of the
neutron star in this case and that would
be your new speed after the slingshot
this seems great because it's just free
energy basically you're not doing it you
know you're not generally to have a
nuclear power react or anything to
generate this you're just stealing it
and indeed you can get to relativistic
speeds this way so I loved that paper
but I had a criticism and the criticism
was that this is like trying to fly your
ship into a blender right this is this
is two neutron stars which have huge
total forces
um and they're whipping around each
other once every second or even less
than a second and you're trying to fly
your spaceship and do this maneuver that
is pretty precarious and so it just
didn't seem practical to me to do this
but I loved it and so I I took that idea
and this is how science is it's
iterative it's it's you take a previous
great man's idea and you just sort of
maybe slightly tweak it and prove it
that's how I see the Halo drive and I
just suggested why not replace those out
for black holes
which is certainly very common and
rather than flying your ship into that
uh that hell hole of a blender System
you just stand back and you fire a laser
beam now because black holes have such
intense gravitational fields they can
bend light into complete 180s they can
actually become mirrors so you know the
sun bends light by maybe a fraction of a
degree through gravitational lensing but
you know a compact object like a black
hole can do a full 180 in fact if you
obviously if you if you went too close
if you put the laser beam too close to
the black hole just fall into it and
never come back out so you just kind of
push it out push it out push it out
until you get to a point where it's just
skirting The Event Horizon and then that
laser beam skirts around it comes back
now the laser beam wants to do a graphic
I mean it is doing a gravitational
slingshot but laser I mean light photons
can't speed up unlike in like the
spaceship case so instead of speeding up
the way they steal energy is they they
increase their frequency so they become
higher energy Photon packets essentially
and they get blue shifted so that you
send maybe a red laser beam that comes
back blue it's got more energy in it and
because
um photons carry momentum which is
somewhat unintuitive in everyday
experience but they do that's how solar
cells work they can't momentum they push
things you can even use them as laser
tweezers and things to pick things up
um because they push the Met it comes
back with momentum than it left
so you get an acceleration force from
this and again you're just seeing energy
from the black hole to do this so you
can get up to the same speed it's
basically the same idea as Freeman Dyson
but doing it from a safer distance and
there should be a border of you know a
million or so or 10 million black holes
in the Milky Way galaxy
some of them would be even as close as
sort of 10 to 20 light years when you do
the occurrence rate statistics of how
close you might expect feasibly want to
be they're of course difficult to detect
because they're black and so they're
inherently hard to see but statistically
there should be plenty out there in the
Milky Way and so these objects would be
natural Waypoint stations you could use
them to both accelerate away and to
break and slow down
oh and on top of all this you know
there's we've been talking about
astronomy and cosmology there's been a
lot of exciting uh breakthroughs in
detection and exploration of uh black
holes so the the boomerang boomeranging
photons that you're talking about
there's been a lot of work on photon
rings and just all the fun stuff going
on outside the black holes yeah
um so all the the garbage outside is
actually might be the thing that holds a
key to understanding what's going on
inside and there's the Hawking radiation
there's all kinds of fascinating stuff
like uh I mean they're just trippy stuff
about black holes that I can't even well
most people don't understand I mean the
holographic
principle with the plate and the
information being stored potentially
outside of the black hole
I don't even I can't even comprehend how
you can project a three-dimensional
object up to 2D and some hostile
information where it doesn't destroy it
and if it does destroy it uh challenging
all the physics all of this is very
uh interesting
especially for kind of more practical
applications of how the black hole could
be used for propulsion yeah I mean it
may be that black holes are used in all
sorts of ways um by Advanced
civilizations I think uh again it's been
a popular idea in science fiction or
science fiction Trope that Sagittarius A
star the supermassive black hole and the
certified Galaxy could be the best place
to look for intelligent life in the
universe because it is a giant uh engine
in a way you know a unique capability
for black hole is you can basically
throw matter into it and you can get
these jets that come out the accretion
discs and the jets that fly out and so
you can more or less use them to convert
Mata into energy V equals mc squared and
there's pretty much nothing else except
for you know Annihilation with and with
its own antiparticle as a way of doing
that
so they have some unique properties you
could perhaps power a civilization
registering garbage into a black hole
right and just throwing asteroids in and
how your civilization with as much
energy as you really would ever
plausibly need and you could also use
them to accelerate away Across the
Universe and you can even imagine using
small artificial black holes as thermal
generators right so the Hawking
radiation from them kind of
exponentially increases as they get
smaller and smaller in size and so a
very small black hole one you can almost
imagine like holding in your hand would
be a fairly significant heat Source
um and so that raises all sorts of
prospects about how you might use that
in an engineering context to power your
civilization as well
uh you have a video on becoming a
Kardashian type one civilization what
what's our hope for doing that we're a
few orders of magnitude away from that
yeah it is surprising I think people
tend to think that we're close to this
this scale the the kardashev type one is
defined as a civilization which is using
as much energy as is essentially insulin
upon the planet from the Star
um so that's a border I think for the
Earth of something like 10 to the five
tarot so 10 to the seven terrorists is a
gigantic amount of energy and we're
using a tiny tiny tiny fraction of that
right now so um you know if you became a
color Chef type 1 civilization which is
seen not necessarily as a goal into
itself I think people think why why are
we aspiring to become this energy hungry
civilization you know surely
um our energy needs might become you
know might improve our efficiency or
something as time goes on but ultimately
the more energy you have access to the
greater your capabilities will be I mean
if you want to lift Mount Everest into
space there is just a calculable amount
of potential energy change that that's
going to take in order to accomplish
that and the more energy you have access
to a civilization then include the
easier that energy achievement is going
to be so depends on what your
aspirations are as a civilization it
might not be something you want to ever
do but well but we should make clear
that lifting heavy things isn't the only
thing it's uh it's just doing work so
yeah it could be computation it could be
right it could be more and more and more
and more sophisticated and larger and
larger larger computation which is it
does seem where we're headed with the uh
very fast increase
and um
the the scale and the quality of our
computation outside the human brain yeah
artificial computation yeah I mean
computation is a great example of I mean
already I think it's about 10 of us
power electricity use is going towards
the super Computing centers so there's a
there's a vast amount of uh current
engine needs which are already going
towards Computing surely only increase
over time
um if we start ever doing anything like
mind uploading or creating simulated
realities that that cost will surely
become almost a dominant source of our
energy requirements at that point if
civilization completely moves over to
this kind of post-humanism stage and so
it's not unreasonable that our engine
needs would continue to grow certainly
historically they always have at about
two percent per year and so if that
continues there is going to be a certain
point
um where you're running up against the
amount of energy which you can Harvest
because it's you're using every even if
you cover the entire planet and solar
panels there's no more energy to be had
um and so this is a you know there's a
few ways of achieving this I sort of
talked about in the video how there were
several renewable energy sources that
were excited about like geothermal wind
power waves but pretty much all of those
don't really scratch the surface or
don't really scratch the itch of getting
to a kardashev type one civilization
they're meaningful now I would never
tell anybody don't do wind power now
because it's it's clearly used for our
current stage of civilization but it's
not it's going to be a pretty negligible
fraction of our energy requirements if
we got to that stage of development and
so there has to be a breakthrough in
either our ability to harvest solar
energy which would require maybe
something like a space array of solar
panels of beaming the energy back down
or some developments and Innovations in
nuclear fusion that would allow us to
essentially reproduce the same process
of what's producing the solar photons
but here on Earth but even that comes
with some consequences if you're
generating the energy here on Earth and
you're doing work on it on Earth then
that work is going to produce waste heat
and that waste heat is going to increase
the ambient temperature of the planet
and so you whether even if this isn't
really a greenhouse effect that you're
increasing the temperature of the planet
this is just the amount of computers
that are churning you put your hand to a
computer you can feel the warmth coming
off them if you do them at work of
literally in you know the entire instant
energy of the planet is doing that work
the player is going to warm up
significantly as a result of that and so
you know that's uh it that clearly
indicates that this is not a sustainable
path that civilizations as they approach
color Chef type 1 are going to have to
leave planet Earth which is really the
point of that video to show that it's
a color Chef type 1 civilization even
though it's defined as instant energy
upon a planet that is not a species that
is going to still be living on their
Planet at least
um in isolation they will have to be
harvesting energy from afar there will
have to be you doing work on that energy
outside of their Planet because
otherwise you're going to dramatically
change the environment in which you live
well yeah so the the it's uh
the more energy you create the more
energy you use the more the higher the
imperative to expand out into the
universe but also not just imperative
but the uh the capabilities and you're
you've kind of as a side on your lab
page mentioned that you're sometimes
interested in Astro engineering
uh so what what kind of uh space
architectures do you think we can build
to house humans or interesting things
outside of Earth
yeah I mean there's there's a lot of fun
ideas here um one of the classic ideas
is only or cylinder or a Stanford Taurus
these are like two rotating structures
that were devised in space they're
basically
using the centrifugal force as
artificial gravity and so these are
structures which tend to be many
kilometers across that you're building
in space but could potentially habitat
um millions of people in in orbit of the
earth
um of course you could imagine pulling
them if you you know the expanse does a
pretty good job I think of exploring the
idea of human exploration of the solar
system and having uh many objects many
of the small near-earth objects and
asteroids inhabited by mining colonies
um one of the ideas we've played around
with our group is this technology called
a quasite a quasite is
um an extension again we always tend to
extend previous ideas ideas build upon
ideas but an extensional idea called a
star type A statite was an idea proposed
I think by Ron forward in the 1970s
1970s seemed to have all sorts of wacky
ideas I don't know what's going on then
I think it's time for Taurus the O'Neill
cylinder status
um the the gravitational lens people
were really having fun with dreaming
about space in the 70s the starter is is
basically a solar Sail but it's such an
efficient solar sail that the outward
force of radiation pressure equals the
inward force of gravity from the Sun and
so it doesn't need to orbit normally you
avoid the sun is pulling us right now
through a force of gravity but we are
not we are not getting closer towards
the sun even though we are Falling
Towards the sun because we're in orbit
which means our translational speed is
just enough to keep us at the same
altitude essentially from the Sun and so
you're in orbit and that's how you
maintain distance a star type doesn't
need to do that it could be basically
you know completely static in inertial
space but it's just balancing the two
forces of radiation pressure and inward
gravitational pressure a quasite is the
in-between of those two states so it's
it has some significant outward pressure
but not enough to resist fully falling
into the star and so it compensates for
that by having some translational motion
so it's in between an orbit and a
statite and so what that allows you to
do is maintain artificial orbits so
normally you you know if you want to
calculate your orbital speed of
something at say half an au you would
use Kepler's Third Law and go through
that and you say okay you know if it's
at half an au I can calculate the period
by P squares proportional to a cubed and
go through that but for a a quasi you
can basically have any speed you want
it's just a matter of how much uh how
much of the gravitational force are you
balancing out you effectively enter an
orbit where you're making the mass of
the star be less massive than it really
is so it's as if you're orbiting a 0.1
solar mass star or 0.2 solar mass star
or whatever you want and so that means
that Mercury orbits with a pretty fast
gravitation a pretty fast orbital speed
around the sun because it's closer to
the Sun than we are but we could put
something in Mercury's orbit that would
have a slower speed and so it would
co-track with the Earth and so we would
always be aligned with them at all times
and so this could be useful if you
wanted to have a
um either a chain of colonies or
something that were able to easily
communicate and Tran and uh and move
between one another between these
different bases you'd probably use
something like this to maintain that uh
easy transferability or you could even
use it as a a space weather monitoring
system which was actually proposed in
the paper
we know that uh major events like the
Carrington event that happen you know
can knock out all of electromagnetic
systems quite easily a major solar flare
could do that a geometric storm but if
we had the ability to detect those uh
higher elevated activity Cycles in
advance
um the problem is they travel obviously
pretty fast and so it's hard to get
ahead of them but you could have a
station which is basically sampling
solar flares very close to the surface
of the Earth and as soon as it detects
anything suspicious
magnetically it could then send that
information straight back at the speed
of light to your Earth and give you
maybe a half an hour warning or
something that's something you know
something bad was coming you should shut
off all your systems or get in your
Faraday cage now and protect yourself
and so these These cryosites are kind of
a cool trick of again kind of hacking
the laws of physics it's like another
one of these exploits that the Universe
seems to allow us to do to potentially
manifest these artificial systems that
would otherwise be be difficult to to
produce so leveraging natural phenomena
yeah
that's always the key is is to work in
my mind is to work with nature that's
how I see Astro engineering rather than
against it you're not trying to force it
to do something you know it that's why
you always think solar energy is so
powerful because in the battle against
nuclear fusion nuclear fusion you're
really fighting a battle where you're
trying to confine plasma into this
extremely tight space or
um it's the sun does this for free it
has gravitation and so
that's the the arson Essence what a
solar panel does it's exp it is a
nuclear fusion reactor fueled Energy
System but it's just using gravitation
for the confinement and having a huge
standoff distance for its energy
collection and so
um there are tricks like that it's very
naive simple trick in that case where we
can rather have to reinvent the wheel we
can use the space infrastructure if you
like the astrophysical infrastructure
that's already there to our benefit yeah
I think in the long Arc of human history
probably natural phenomena is the right
Solution that's the simple that's the
elegant solution because all the power
is already there that's why it Dyson
Sphere in the long
sort of
but you don't know what a dices field
would look like but some kind of thing
that leverages the power the energy
that's already in the sun is is better
than creating artificial nuclear uh
fusion reaction but then again
that brings us to the topic of AI how
much of this
if we're traveling out there
Interstellar travel or um
doing some of the interesting things
we'll be talking about how much
of those ships would be occupied by AI
systems do you think
what would the
what would be the living organisms
occupying those ships
yeah it it's depressing to think about
AI in the search for life because
they had I mean I've been thinking about
this over the last few weeks with
playing around with chat gbt3 like many
of us and being astonished with its
capabilities and you see that it that
our society
is undergoing a change that seems
significant in terms of the development
of artificiality we've been promised
this revolution this Singularity for a
long time but it really seems to be
stepping up its uh its pace of
development at this point and so that's
interesting because as someone who looks
freely in life out there in the universe
um it sort of implies that our current
stage development is highly transitional
and that
you know you go back for the last four
and a half billion years the the planet
was dumb essentially if you go back uh
that's a few thousand years there was a
civilization but it wasn't really
producing any technical signatures and
then over the last maybe 100 years
there's been something that might be
detectable from afar
but we're approaching this cusp where we
might imagine it I mean we're thinking
of like maybe years and decades with AI
development typically when we talk about
this but as an astronomer I have to
think about much longer time scares of
centuries Millennia millions of years
and so if this
if this wave continues over that time
scale which is still the blink of an eye
on a cosmic time scale
that implies that
everything will be AI essentially out
there if this is a common behavior and
so that's intriguing because it sort of
implies that we are
uh special in in terms of Our Moment In
Time as a civilization
which it normally is
um
something we're averse to as astronomers
we we normally like this mediocrity
principle we're not special we're a
typical part of the universe sometimes
another cosmological principle but in a
temporal sense we may be in a unique
location and perhaps that is part of the
solution to the Fermi Paradox in fact
that if it is true that plants tend to
go through basically three phases dumb
life for the vast majority a brief
period of biological intelligence and
then an extended period of artificial
intelligence that they transition to
then we would be in a unique and special
moment in Galactic history that would be
of particular interest for any
anthropologists out there in the galaxy
right this would be the time that you
would want to study a civilization very
carefully you wouldn't want to interfere
with it you would just want to see how
it plays out kind of similar to the
ancestor simulations I sometimes talked
about the simulation argument that you
are able to observe perhaps your own
Origins and study how the transformation
happens and so yeah that has for me
recently been destroying the foaming
Paradox a bit on his head and this idea
of the the zoo hypothesis that would
maybe monitored which has for a long
time been sort of
seen as a fringe idea even amongst the
seti community but
if we live in this truly transitional
period it lets it adds a lot of impetus
to that idea I think well even AI itself
would
but it's very nature would be observing
us
by you know it's like uh human there
used to be this concept of human
computation which is actually exactly
what's feeding the current chat uh
language models which is leveraging all
the busy stuff we're doing
to do the hard work of learning so like
uh the language models are trained on
human
interaction in human language on the
internet and so it would AI feeds on the
output of brain power from humans and so
like it would be observing and observing
and it gets stronger as it observes so
it actually gets extremely good at
observing humans and one of the
interesting philosophical questions that
starts
percolating is what makes us what is the
interesting thing that makes us human
we tend to think of it uh and you say
like there's three phases what's the
thing that's hard to come by in phase
three
is it something like scarcity which is
limited resources is it something like
Consciousness is that the thing that's
very what uh that emerged The
evolutionary process
in biological systems that are operating
under constrained resources
this thing that feels that it feels like
something to experience the world which
we think of as Consciousness is that
really difficult to replicate is in in
artificial systems is that the thing
that makes us fundamentally human
or is it just a side effect
that we attribute way too much
importance to Would You Do you have do
you have a sense
if you look out into the future and AI
systems are the ones that are traveling
out there
and to Alpha Centauri and Beyond
do you think they have to carry the the
flame of Consciousness with them
no not necessarily
um they may do but they may it may not
be
unnecessarily
I mean there's I guess we're talking
about the difference here between sort
of an AGI artificial general
intelligence or Consciousness which are
distinct ideas and you can certainly
have one without the other so I couldn't
imagine I would I would disagree with
this certainly in that statement okay
okay I I think it's very possible in
order to have intelligence you have to
have consciousness
okay well I mean to a certain degree
chat gbt3 has a level of intelligence
already it's not a general intelligence
but it displays properties of
intelligence with with no consciousness
so again I would disagree okay okay well
I I don't I don't I don't know because
you said it's very nasty you said it
displays properties of intelligence in
the same way displaced properties of
intelligence I would say it's starting
to display properties of Consciousness
it certainly could fool you that it's
conscious
correct yeah there's I guess like a a
Turing test problem like if it's
displaying all those properties
if it quacks like a parent looks like a
parent or cracks like a duck things like
isn't it basically a duck at that point
so yeah I can see that argument
um it probably
it I mean certainly isn't it I tried to
think about it from the observer's point
of view as an astronomer what am I
looking for whether that intelligence is
conscious or not has little bearing I
think as to what I should be looking for
when I'm trying to detect evidence of
them
it would maybe affect their behavior in
ways that I can't predict
um but that's again getting into the
game of what I would cause you know
psychology of trying to make projections
about the motivations of an alien
species is incredibly difficult
and simile for any kind of artificial
intelligence it's unfathomable what its
intentions may be I mean I would sort of
question whether it would even be
interested in traveling between the
stars at all
if its primary goal is computation
computation for the sake of computation
then it's probably going to have a
different
way of you know it's going to be
engineering its solar system and the
nearby material around it for for a
different goal if it's just simply
trying to increase computer substrate
Across the Universe
and that of course if that is its
principal intention to just essentially
convert dumb matter into smart matter as
it goes then
I think that would come into conflict
with our observations of the universe
right because
the the Earth shouldn't be here if that
were true the Earth should have been
transformed into computer substrate by
this point there has been plenty of time
yeah in the history of the Galaxy for
that to have happened
um so I'm skeptical
that we can uh
I'm skeptical in the part that that's a
behavior that AI or any civilization
really engages in but I also find it
difficult to find a way out of it
to explain why that would never happen
in the entire history of the Galaxy
amongst potentially if life is common
Millions maybe even billions of instant
instantiations of AI could have occurred
across the Galaxy
um and so that seems to be a knock
against the idea that there is life else
or intelligent life elsewhere in the in
the Galaxy the fact that that hasn't
occurred in our history is maybe the
only solid data point we really have
about the activities of other
civilizations
of course the scary one could be that um
we just at this stage intelligent alien
civilizations just started destroying
themselves
hey because it becomes too powerful
everything's just too many weapons too
many nuclear weapons too many nuclear
weapons style systems that just
from mistake to aggression to like the
probability of self-destruction is too
high relative to the challenge of of
avoiding
the technological challenges of avoiding
self-destruction
you mean the the AI destroys itself oh
no prior to the Advent of air as we give
a smarter and smarter AI
um either AI destroys us or other there
could be just a million like AI is
correlated the development of AI is
correlated where all these other
technological innovation uh genetic
genetic engineering like all kinds of
engineering at the nanoscale
it's a mass manufacturer of things that
could destroy us or cracking physics
enough to have very powerful weapons
nuclear weapons all of it just too much
physics enables way too many things that
can destroy us
before it enables the um
the propulsion systems that allow us to
fly far enough away before we destroy
ourselves so maybe that's what happens
to the other alien civilizations is that
your resolution because I mean I think
Us in the signature community in the
Australian Community aren't thinking
about this problem seriously enough in
my opinion we should we should be
thinking about the what AI is is doing
to our society and the implications of
what we're looking for and so the only I
think part of this thinking has to
involve people like yourself who are
more intimate with the machine learning
and artificial intelligence world is
your how do you reconcile in your mind
you said earlier that you think you
can't imagine a Galaxy where life and
intelligence is not all over the place
and if artificial intelligence is a
natural progression for civilizations
how do you reconcile that with
with the absence of any information
around us or any clues or hints of
artificial Behavior artificially
engineered stars or colonization
computer substrate transformed planets
anything like that it's it's uh
extremely difficult for me it's the the
Fermi Paradox broadly defined as
extremely difficult for me and the the
terrifying thing is one thing I suspect
is that we keep destroying ourselves the
probability of self-destruction with
with advanced technology is just
extremely high that's why we're not
seeing it
but then again my intuition about about
why we haven't blown ourselves up with
nuclear weapons
it's very surprising to me from a
scientific perspective
but yeah it doesn't given all the
cruelty I've seen in the world
um given the the the power that nuclear
weapons place in the hands a very small
number of individuals
it's very surprising to destroy
ourselves and it seems to be a very low
probability situation with Happening
Here
um
but and then the other explanation is
the is the zoo is the observation that
we're just being observed
that's that's the only other thing it's
just it's so difficult for me
of course all of science everything is
very humbling it would be very humbling
for me to learn
that we're alone in the universe
it would change
uh I you know what it maybe I do want
that to be true because you want us to
be special that's why I'm resisting that
thought maybe there's no way we're that
special there's no way we're that
special that's that's that's where my
resistance comes from I would just say
you know
the specialness is something we we in
implicitly in that statement there's
kind of an assumption that we are
something positive like we're a gift to
this planet or something and that makes
it special but you know it may be that
intelligence is more often is like we
like rats or cockroaches we're an
infestation of this planet we're not
we're not some benevolent property that
the planet would apply would ideally
like to if they have if you can even say
such a thing but we we may be not only a
generally a negative Force for a plant's
biosphere and its own survivability
which I think you can make a strong
argument about but we may also be a very
persistent infestation that may even in
you know interesting thoughts in this in
the wake of a nuclear war
would that be an absolute eradication of
every human being which would be a
fairly extreme event or would the kind
of like Consciousness as you might call
it the flame of Consciousness continue
with some small Pockets that would maybe
in ten thousand years a hundred thousand
years we'd see civilization re-emerge
and play out the same thing over again
yeah that's certainly but nuclear
weapons aren't powerful enough yet but
yes the uh but to sort of push back on
the infestation sure but the word
special doesn't have to be positive
I just mean
I think it tends to imply but I take
your point yeah but maybe
um
just maybe extremely rare maybe yeah and
that to me it just it's very strange
for me to be
cosmically unique
it's just very strange I I
mean that word the only thing
of this level of complexity in the
Galaxy just seems very strange to me I
would just yeah I I said I do think it
depends on this classification I think
there is sort of again it's kind of
buried within there as a subtext but
there was a a classification that we're
doing here that what we are is a
distinct category of of life let's say
in this case we're talking about
intelligence we have something that can
be separated
um but of course we see intelligence
across the Animal Kingdom in you know
Dolphins humpback whales
um octopuses crows Ravens and so it's
quite possible that
um
that these are all manifestations of
this same thing and we are not uh we are
not a particularly distinct class except
for the fact we make technology that's
really any difference to our
intelligence and we we classify that
separately but from a biological
perspective to some degree it's really
just all part of a Continuum and so
that's why I
when we talk about unique you're you're
you are putting yourself in a box which
is distinct and saying this is the only
example of things that fall into this
box but that but the wars of that box
May themselves be a construct of our own
arrogance that we are something distinct
and uh but I was also speaking broadly
for us meaning all life on Earth
that but then it's possible that there's
all kinds of
living
ecosystems in on other planets and other
moons that just don't have interest in
technological development and maybe
maybe technological development is the
the
parasitic thing it destroys the organism
broadly and then
maybe that's actually one of the
fundamental realities whatever broad way
to categorize technological development
that's that's just a parasitic thing
that just destroys itself yeah it's a
cancer you know like floating around
sorry to interrupt it we're floating
around this idea of the great filter a
little bit here so we'll be asking where
is this does it lie ahead of us nuclear
war maybe imminent that would be a
filter that's ahead of us or could it be
behind us and it's the Advent of
technology that is genuinely a rare
occurrence in the universe and that
explains the Fermi Paradox um
and so that's uh that's something that
obviously people have debated and gone
argued about in seti for decades and
decades but it remains a persistent
people argue oh that should be really
quite a paradox or not but it remains a
consistent apparent contradiction that
you can make a very cogent argument as
to why you expect life and intelligence
to be common in the universe and yet
everything everything we know about the
universe is fully compatible with just
us being here and that's
a haunting thought but
um I'm not I have no preference or
desire for that to be true I'm not
trying to impose that view on anyone but
I do ask that we remain open-minded
until evidence has been collected either
way well the thing is
it's
one of if not the probably I would argue
is the most important question facing
human civilization or the most
interesting yeah I think
scientifically speaking like what
question is more important
then um somehow
you know there could be other ways to
sneak up to it but it gets to the
essence of
what we are
what these living organisms are is
somehow seeing another kind
yeah helps us understand it speaks to
The Human Condition helps us understand
what it is to be human to some degree
um I think you know I I have tried to
mean remain very agnostic about the idea
of life and intelligence one thing I try
to be more optimistic about and I've
been thinking a lot with our searches
for life in the universe is life in the
past
you can I think it's actually not that
hard to imagine we are the only
civilization in the Galaxy right now
living yeah this this current extent but
there may be very many extinct
civilizations if each civilization has a
typical lifetime comparable to let's say
AI is the demise of our own that's only
a few hundred years of technological
development or maybe 10 000 years if you
go back to the nearest Revolution I
don't have agriculture you know hardly
anything can Cosmic time span
um that that's nothing that's the blink
of an eye and so it's not surprising at
all that we would happen not to coexist
with anyone else but that doesn't mean
nobody else was ever here
and if other civilizations come to that
same conclusion and realization maybe
they scour the Galaxy around them don't
find any evidence for intelligence
then they have two options they can
either give up on communication and just
say well it's never going to happen uh
we just may as well just you know worry
about what's Happening Here on our own
planet or they could attempt
communication but communication is
through time and that's that's almost
um the most selfless Act of
communication because there's no hope of
getting anything back it's
um a philanthropic a gift almost to that
other civilization that you can maybe
maybe might just be nothing more than a
monument which the pyramids essentially
are a monument of their existence that
these are the things they achieve this
is their you know the things they
believed in their language their culture
or
um it could be maybe something more than
that it could be sort of lessons from
what they learned in their own history
and so
I've been thinking a lot recently about
how would we send a message to other
civilizations in the future
because that act of thinking seriously
about the engineering of how you design
that would inform us about what we
should be looking for
and also perhaps be our best chance
quite frankly of ever making contact it
might not be the contact we dream of
but it's still contact they would there
would still be a record of our existence
as pitiful as it might be compared to a
two-way communication
and I love the humility behind that
project that Universal project
yeah it's a sort of it's humble in the
it uh humbles you to the the vast
temporal landscape of the universe just
realizing our like day-to-day lives they
all of us will be forgotten it's nice to
think about something that sends a
signal out to other
um yeah it was almost like a humility of
acceptance as well of like knowing that
you have a terminal disease but your
impact on the earth doesn't have to end
with your death that it could go on
Beyond with what you leave behind for
others to discover with maybe the books
you write or what you leave in the
literature do you think launching the
Roadster vehicle out in space yeah the
Roadster
um I'm not sure what someone would make
of that if they've
yeah that's true um I mean there have
been quasi-attempts at it be on the
Roadster I mean there's like plaques on
there's the Pioneer plaques
um there's the Voyager 2 golden record
um it's pretty unlikely anybody's going
to discover those uh because they're
just adrift in space and they they they
will eventually mechanically die and not
produce any signal for anyone to spot so
you'd have to be extremely lucky to come
across them I've often said to my
colleagues I think the best place is the
Moon
the moon unlike the Earth has no
significant weathering the you know that
how long will the Apollo descent stages
which are still sun on the lunar surface
last for the the only real effect is
micrometeorites which are slowly like
dust smashing against them pretty much
um but that's going to take Millions
potentially billions of years to erode
that down and so we have an opportunity
and that's on the surface if you put
something just a few meters beneath the
surface it would have even greater
protection and so it raises the prospect
of that if we wanted to
send something a significant amount of
information to a future Galactic
spanning Civilization that maybe cracks
the interstellar proportion problem
the moon's going to be there for five
billion years that's a long time for
somebody to come by and detect maybe a
strange pattern that we draw on the sand
for them to you know big Arrow big cross
like look under here and we could have a
tomb of knowledge of some record of our
civilization and so I think it's uh when
you think like that what that implies to
us well okay the Galaxy's 13 billion
years old the Moon is already 4 billion
years old there may be places
familiar to Us nearby to us that we
should be seriously considering
as places we should look for life and
intelligent life or evidence of relics
that they might leave behind for us so
that thinking like that will help us
find such relics and it's like uh it's a
like a beneficial cycle that happens yes
yeah exactly that enables the science of
said you better like of of searching for
bios and Tech signatures and so on yeah
and it's inspiring I mean it's it's it's
it's
it's also inspiring in that we want to
leave
a legacy behind as an entire
civilization not just in the symbols but
broadly speaking Yeah that's the last
thing somehow yeah and I'm part of a
team that's trying to
re-re repeat the golden record
experiment uh we're trying to create
like an open source version of the
golden record the future spacecraft are
able to download and basically put a
little hard drive so they can carry
around with them and you know get these
distributed hopefully across the solar
system eventually and it's going to be
called The Hitchhiker's Guide to the
Galaxy yeah it could be that's a good
name for it we've we've been talking a
little bit with the name but I think
probably just be golden record at this
point I've got record version two or
something but
um I think uh I think another benefit
that I see of this activity
is that it forces us as a species
to ask those questions about what it is
that we want under the civilization to
know about us the god record was kind of
funny because it had photos on it and it
had photos of people eating for instance
um but it had no photos of people
defecating and so I always thought that
was kind of funny because of her post
if I was an alien yeah or if I was
studying an alien if I saw images from
an alien I wouldn't I'm not trying to be
like a perv or anything but I would want
to see the full Bible I want to
understand the biology of that alien and
so we we always censor what we what we
show
um and which was just show the whole
actual natural process and then also say
we humans tend to censor these things we
tend to not like to walk around naked we
tend to not to talk about uh some of the
natural biological phenomena and talk a
lot about others yeah and and actually
just be very uh like the way you would
be to a therapist or something very
transparent about the way we actually
operate yeah I mean and Sagan had that
has second had that with the golden
record I think he he originally uh
there's a there's a male and a female
figure depicts on the golden record
and the the woman had a genitalia
originally drawn and uh there was a lot
of pushback from I think a lot of
Christian groups who were not happy
about the idea of throwing this into
space And So eventually they had to
remove that and so it's it would be
confusing biologically if you're you
know trying to study xenobiology of this
alien that apparently has no genitalia
or demanders but for some reason the
woman doesn't you know and that's our
that's our own societal and cultural uh
imprint happening into that information
that's to be fair
just even having
two Sexes and predators and prey just a
whole that could be just a very unique
Earth-like thing so they might be
confused about why there's like pairs of
things like why are you like why why is
there a man and a woman in general like
they they could be I mean they could be
confused about a lot of things in
general I don't I don't think the I
don't even know which way to hold the
pigs
or there's the picture they don't they
might not need they might have very
different sensory devices to even
interpret them if they only you know
have uh sound is our only way of
navigating the world it's kind of lost
to send any kind of you know there's
been a lot of conversation about sending
video and uh audio and uh video and
pictures and I've that's one of the
things I've been a little bit resistant
about in the team that I've been
thinking well
they might have eyes and so if you lived
in um on the Europa surface having eyes
wouldn't be very useful
um if you lived in a on a very dark
planet on the Tidy locked night side of
an exoplanet having eyes would be
particularly useful so it's kind of a
presumption of us to think that video is
a useful form of communication
do you hope we become a multi-planetary
species so we almost sneaking up to that
but um you know the efforts of SpaceX of
Elon maybe in general what your thoughts
are about those efforts so you already
mentioned Starship will be very
interesting for astronomy for for
science in general just getting stuff
out into space
but what about the longer term goal of
actually colonizing of building
civilizations on other surfaces on moons
on planets it seems like an a fairly
obvious thing to do for our survival
right there's a high risk if if we are
committed to trying to keep this human
experiment going
um putting all of our eggs in one basket
is always going to be a risky strategy
to pursue it's a nice basket though but
yeah it is a beautiful basket I wouldn't
want to I personally have no interest in
living on mars or the moon I would like
to visit but I would definitely not want
to spend the rest of my life and die on
Mars it's a it means a hell hole Mars is
a very very diff I think the idea this
is going to happen in the next you know
10 20 years is seems to me very
optimistic
um not that it's insurmountable but the
the challenges are extreme to survive on
a planet like Mars which is you know
like a dry Frozen desert
um with a high radiation environment
it's it's a challenge of a type we've
never faced before so it's I'm sure
human Ingenuity can tackle it but I'm
skeptical that we'll have thousands of
people living on Mars in my lifetime but
I would I would would relish that
opportunity to maybe one day visit such
a settlement and you know do scientific
experiments on mars or experience Mars
do astronomy from you know all sorts of
cool stuff you could do
um you know sometimes you see these
dreams of outer solar system exploration
and you can like fly through the clouds
of Venus or you could just do these
enormous jumps on like these small moons
where you can essentially jump as high
as a skyscraper and Traverse them so
there's all sorts of you know Wonderful
ice skating on Europa it might be fun so
don't get me wrong I love the idea of us
becoming into planetary I think it's
um
it's just a question of uh time our own
our own destructive Tendencies uh as you
said earlier are add-ons with our
emerging capability to become
interplanetary and the question is will
we get out of the nest before we burn it
down and I don't know I obviously I hope
that we do but I I don't have any
special Insight that
there is a prop there is somewhat of a
gnoring intellectual itch I have with
the so-called doomsday argument which
um I try not to treat too seriously but
there is some element of it that bothers
me uh the Dooms argument basically
suggests that
you know you're typically the mediocrity
principal you're not special that you're
probably going to be born somewhere in
the middle of all human beings will ever
be born you're unlikely to be one of the
first one percent of human beings that
ever lived and then one of the last ones
and similarly the last one percent of
human beings because you'd be very
unique and special if that were true
and so by this logic you can sort of
calculate um how many generations of
humans you might expect so if there's
been let's say 100 billion human beings
that have ever lived on this planet then
you could say to 95 confidence so you
divide by five percent so a hundred
billion divided by 0.05 would give you 2
trillion human beings that would ever
live
you'd expect by this argument and so if
each
um if let's say each each planet in
general the planet has a 10 billion
population so that would be 200
generations of humans we would expect
ahead of us and if each one has an
average lifetime let's say 100 years
then that would be about 20 000 years so
there's 20 000 years left in the clock
there's like a typical doomsday argument
type
that's how they typically lay it out
um now you can argue a lot of the
criticisms that doomsday argument come
down to well what are you really
counting you're counting humans there
but maybe you should be counting years
or maybe you should be counting human
hours you know how what are you because
what you count makes a big difference to
what you get out on the other ends this
is called the reference class
um and so that's when the big questions
the Dooms I like men but I do think it
has a compelling point that it would be
surprising if our future is to one day
Blossom and become a Galactic spanning
Empire trillions upon trillions upon
trillions of human beings will one day
live across the stars for essentially as
long as the Galaxy exists and the Stars
Burn
we would live at an incredibly special
point in that story we would be right at
the very very very beginning and that's
not impossible but it's just somewhat
improbable and so there's part of that
sort of um irks against me but it also
almost feels like a philosophical
argument because you're sort of talking
about
Souls being drawn from this Cosmic pool
um so it's it's not an argument that I
lose sleep about for our fate of the
Doomsday but it is
um
somewhat intellectually annoying that
that there is a slight contradiction now
it feels like with the idea of a
Galactic spanning Empire
and but of course there's so many
unknowns
I I for one would love to visit even
space but Mars just imagine standing on
Mars and looking back at Earth
yeah I mean
um be incredible so
it would give you such a
fresh perspective as to your entire
existence and wanted to be human yeah
and then come back to earth and it would
give you
and give you a heck of a perspective
plus this the sunset on Mars is supposed
to be nice I loved what William Shatner
said after his flight
um his words really moved me when he
came down and I think uh
it really captured the idea that we
shouldn't really be sending uh Engineers
our scientists into space we should be
sending out poets because those are the
people when they come down who can who
can truly make a difference with when
they describe their experiences in space
and I found it very moving reading what
he what he said
yeah when you talk to astronauts when
they when they describe what they see
it's like this
like they've discovered a whole new
thing that they can't possibly convert
back into words yeah
um yeah it's it's beautiful to see just
as a quick before I forget I have to ask
you
um can you summarize your argument
against the hypothesis that we live in a
simulation
is it similar to our discussion about uh
the Doomsday Clock
um no it's actually probably more
similar to my
um agnosticism about life in the
universe and it's just sort of remaining
agnostic about all possibilities
um the simulation argument
sometimes it gets
um
mix there's kind of two distinct things
that we need to consider one is the
probability that we live in so-called
base reality that we're not living in a
simulated reality itself and another
probability to consider is the
probability that that technology is
viable possible and something we will
ultimately choose to one day do those
are two distinct things they're probably
quite similar numbers to each other but
they are distinct probabilities so my in
my paper I I wrote about this I just
tried to work through the problem I
teach asteroid statistics actually
teaching me this morning
and so it just seemed like a fun case
study of working through a Bayesian
calculation Fred
um Bayesian calculations work on
conditionals and so when you hear any
what kind of inspired this project was
when I heard musk said was like a
billion to one chance that we don't live
in a simulation
um
he's right if you add the Bayesian
conditional and the basic additional is
a conditioned upon the fact that we
eventually develop that technology and
choose to use it or it's it's chosen to
be used by such species both
civilizations that's the conditional and
you have to add that in because that
conditional isn't guaranteed
and so um in a Bayesian framework you
can kind of Make That explicit you see
mathematically explicitly that's a
condition on your equation and the the
opposite side of the coin is basically
um in the trilemma that Bostrom
originally put forward it's options one
and two assumption one is that you
basically never developed the ability to
do that option two is you never choose
to execute that so we kind of group
those together as sort of the uh the
non-simulation uh scenario let's call it
and so you've got non-simulation
scenario and simulation scenario and
agnostically we really have to give
though you know how do you assess the
model that April and model probability
of those two scenarios
um it's very difficult and we can I
think people would probably argue about
how you assign those prayers in the
paper we just assigned 50 50. we just
said we this hasn't been demonstrated
yet there's no evidence that this is
actually technically possible but nor is
that it's not technically possible so
we're just going to assign 50 50
probability these two hypotheses and
then in the hypothesis where you have a
simulated reality you have a base
reality cell at the top so there is even
in the simulated hypothesis there's a
probability you still live in base
reality and then there's a whole Myriad
of universes beneath that which are all
simulated and so you have a very you
have a very slim probability of being in
base reality if this is true and you
have a 100 probability of living base
reality on the other hand if it's not
true and we never develop that ability
or choose never to use it and so then
you apply this technique called bazing
averaging which is where you propagate
the uncertainty of your two models to
get a final estimate and because of that
one base reality that lives in the
simulated scenario you end up counting
this up and getting that it always has
to be less than 50 so the probability
you live in this in in a simulated
reality versus base reality has to be
slightly less than 50 percent
um now that really comes down to that
statement of giving it 50 50 odds to
begin with
and on the one hand you might say look
David I'm you know I work in artificial
church I'm very confident that this is
going to happen just of extrapolating of
current trends or on the other hand the
statistician would say
um you're giving way too much weight to
the simulation hypothesis because it's
an intrinsically highly complicated
model you have a whole hierarchy of
realities within realities within
realities it's like the Inception style
thing right and so this requires
hundreds thousands millions of
parameterizations to describe and by
Occam's razor we would always normally
penalize inherently complicated models
as being disfavored so I think you could
argue on being too generous or too kind
with that but I sort of want to develop
the the rigorous mathematical tools to
explore it and ultimately it's up to you
to decide what you think that 50 50 odds
should be but you can use my formula to
plug in whatever you want and get the
answer and I use 50 50. so and but when
in that first pile with the first two
parts of the the the the the the
bathroom talks about it seems like
connected to that is the question we've
been talking about which is the number
of times at bat you get which is the
number of intelligent civilizations that
are out there that can uh build such
simulations that's it seems like very
closely connected because if we're the
only ones that are here and it could
build such things that changes things
yeah yeah I mean
this yeah this image complexes has all
sorts of implications like that
um I've always loved showing PowerPoints
about a really interesting contradiction
apparently with the simulation
hypothesis that I speak about a little
bit in the paper
but he showed that um or pointed out
that in this hierarchy of realities
which then developed their own AIS
within the realities and then they just
or really ancestor simulations I should
say rather than AI they develop their
own capability to simulate realities you
get this hierarchy until eventually
there'll be a bottom layer
um which I often call the sewer of
reality it's like the worst layer where
it's the most pixelated it could
possibly be right so because each layer
is necessarily going to have less
computational power than the layer above
it because not only are you stimulating
that entire planet but also some of
that's being used for the computers
themselves so those are simulated and so
that base reality also about the suit of
reality is a is a is a reality where
they are simply unable to produce
ancestor simulations because the
Fidelity the simulation is not
sufficient and so from that point of
view it might not be obvious the
universe is pixelated but they would
just never be able to manifest that
capability what if they're constantly
simulating
uh because it in order to uh appreciate
the limits of the Fidelity you have to
have an observer what if they're always
simulating a dumber and dumber Observer
yeah what if the sewer has very dumb
observers that can't like scientists
that are the dumbest possible scientists
so like it's it's very pixelated but the
scientists are too dumb to even see the
the pixelations right like that that's
like built into the universe always has
to be a limitation on the cognitive
capabilities of the complex systems that
are within it yeah so that through a
reality they would still presumably be
able to have a very impressive
computational capabilities they'll
probably be able to simulate Galactic
formation or this kind of impressive
stuff but they would be just short of
the ability to however you define it
credit truly sentient conscious
experience in a computer that would just
be just beyond their capabilities and so
uh Carol points out that if you add up
all the you know you count up how many
realities there should be
probabilistically if this is true over
here the simulation uh hypothesis or
scenario then you're most likely to find
yourself in the sewer because there's
just far more of them than there are of
any of the higher levels oh and so that
sort of sets up a contradiction because
then you live in a reality which is
inherently incapable of ever producing
ancestor simulations
but the premise of the entire argument
is that ancestor simulations are
possible so there's there's a
contradiction does that is that old
quote we're all living in the sewer but
some of us are looking up at the stars
this is maybe more true than we think
uh but to me so there's of course
physics and computational uh fascinating
questions here but to me there's a
practical psychological question which
is you know how do you create a virtual
reality world
that is as compelling and not
necessarily even as realistic but
almost as realistic
but as compelling or more compelling
Than Physical reality
because something tells me it's not it's
not very difficult in a in a
full history of human civilization that
that is an interesting
kind of simulation to me because that
feels like it's doable in the next 100
years creating a world where we're all
prefer to live in the digital world and
not like a visit but like
it's
like you're seen as insane no like
you're required it's unsafe to live
outside of the virtual world and uh it's
interesting to me from an engineering
perspective how to build that because
I'm somebody that sort of loves video
games and it seems like you can create
incredible worlds there and stay there
and uh that's a it's a different
question then creating a ultra high
resolution High Fidelity simulation of
physics but if that world inside a video
game is
as consistent as the physics of our
reality that you can have your own
scientists in that world that trying to
understand that physics World it might
look different
that eventually forget you know give it
give it long enough they might forget
about their origins of being once
biological and assume this is their only
reality especially if you're now born
you know uh well certainly if you're
born but even if you're eight years old
or something when you first started
wearing the headset
yeah or you could have a memory wipe
when you go in I mean it it also kind of
maybe speaks to this issue of like
neuralink and how do we keep up with AI
in our world
if you want to augment your intelligence
um perhaps one way of competing and the
one of your impetuses for going into
this digital reality would be to be
competitive intellectually with
um artificial intelligences that you
could trivially augment your reality if
your brain was itself artificial but
I mean one one skepticism I've always
had about that is is whether it's a
first tough question but how much is
that really you if you do a mind upload
is this just a duplicate of your
memories that thinks it's you versus
truly a transference of your contrast
stream into that reality and I think
when you uh
it's almost like the teleportation
device in Star Trek
um but with teleportation quantum
teleportation you can kind of rigorously
show that
um that you know all as long as all of
the quantum numbers are exactly
duplicated as you transfer over it truly
is from the University's perspective in
every way indistinguishable from what
was there before it really is in
principle of you and all the sense of
being you versus creating a duplicate
clone and uploading memories uh to that
human body or a computer that would
surely be a a discontinuation of that
conscious experience by virtue of the
fact you've multiplied it and so I
I would be hesitant about uploading for
that reason I would see it mostly as my
own killing myself and having some
um
AI duplicate of me that persists in this
world but is not truly my experience
typical
20th century human with an attachment to
this particular singular instantiation
of brain and body
how silly humans used to be used to have
rotary phones and
um
and and other silly things
you're an incredible human being you're
an educator you're a researcher uh you
have uh like an amazing uh YouTube
channel
looking to young people if you were to
give them advice
how can they have a career that maybe is
inspired by yours
um inspired by wandering curiosity a
career they can be proud of or a life
they can be proud of
what advice would you give
I certainly think in terms of a a career
in science one thing that I maybe
discovered late but has been
incredibly influential on me in terms of
my own happiness and my own
um productivity has been this Synergy of
doing two passions at once one passion
in science communication another passion
research and not surrendering either one
and I think
that tends to be seen as something
that's in either or you have to
completely dedicate your yourself to one
thing to gain Mastery in it that's a
conventional way of thinking about both
science and other disciplines and I have
found that both have been elevated by
practicing in each
um and I think that that's true in all
assets of life I mean if you want to
become the best researcher you possibly
can
you're pushing your intellect in a sense
your body to a high level
and so to me
I've always wanted to couple that with
training of my body training my mind in
other ways besides from just what I'm
doing when I'm in the lecture room or
I'm in my office you know calculating
something
um focusing on your own development
through whatever it is meditation for me
it's often running working out
um and pursuing multiple passions
provides this uh almost synergistic
lists of all of them together so often
I've had some of the best research ideas
from making a YouTube video and trying
to communicate an idea or interacting my
audience who've had a question that
sparked a whole trail of thought that
led down this wonderful intellectual
Rabbit Hole or maybe to a new
intellectual Discovery can go either way
sometimes with those things
um and so thinking broadly diversely
and always looking after yourself in
this in this highly competitive and
often extremely stressful world that we
live in
um
is the best advice I can offer anybody
and just try if you can to it's very
easy but if you can follow your passions
you'll always be happy
um trying to sell out for for the quick
cash out for the QuickBook out
um can be tempting in the short term
looking for EXO means was never was
never easy but I made a career not out
of discovering EXO moons but out of
learning how to communicate the
difficult problem and discovering all
sorts of things along the way you know
we shot for the sky and we discovered
all this stuff along the way we
discovered dozens of new planets using
all sorts of new techniques we push this
instrumentation to new places and I've
had an extremely productive uh research
career in this world I've had all sorts
of ideas working on techno signatures
it's it's
you know thinking innovatively pushes
you into all sorts of exciting
directions
um so
just just try to yeah it's hard to find
that passion but you you can sometimes
remember it when you're a kid what your
passions were and what what fascinated
you as a child for me as soon as I
picked up a space book when I was five
years old that was it I was hooked on
space and I almost betrayed my passion
at College I studied physics which I've
always been fascinated by physics as
well but I came back to astronomy
because it was my first love and I was
much happier doing research in astronomy
than I was in physics because it spoke
to that wonder I had as a child that
first was the spark of curiosity for me
in science
so Society will try to get you to look
at how Jupiter's yeah and the advice is
to look for the cool world instead uh
what do you think is the meaning of this
whole thing you ever ask yourself why
it's just a ride
that's right it's just a ride we're on a
roller coaster
and we have no purpose it's an accident
in my my perspective there's no meaning
to my life there's no objective uh deity
who is overwatching what I'm doing and
I'm I have some fate or destiny it's all
just riding on the roller coaster and
trying to have a good time and fun and
and contribute
to to other people's enjoyment of the
road yeah try to try to make it a happy
uh Happy accent yeah yeah I I see no
fundamental
um Providence in in my life or in the
nature of the universe and you just see
this universe as this beautiful Cosmic
accident of galaxies smashing together
Stars forging here and there and planets
occasionally spawning maybe life Across
the Universe
um and we are just one of those
instantiations and we should just enjoy
this very brief episode that we have and
I think trying to look at it much deeper
than that is um
is to me uh is not very so satisfying I
just think enjoy what you've got and
appreciate it it does seem noticing that
beauty
um helps make the ride
pretty fun yeah absolutely David you're
an incredible person I I haven't covered
most of the things I wanted to talk to
you about this was an incredible
conversation I I just I'm glad you exist
I'm glad you're doing everything you're
doing and I'm a huge fan thank you so
much for talking today this is amazing
thank you so much real honor thank you
thanks for listening to this
conversation with David Kipping to
support this podcast please check out
our sponsors in the description and now
let me leave you some words from Carl
Sagan perhaps the aliens are here
but are hiding because of some Lex
Galactica some ethic of non-interference
with emerging civilizations we can
imagine them curious and dispassionate
observing us as we would watch a
bacterial culture in a dish to determine
whether this year again would manage to
avoid self-destruction
thank you for listening and hope to see
you next time