and so our goal was a natural looking
gate it was real it was surprisingly
hard to get that to work
um and we but we did build an early
machine
uh we called it pet man prototype it was
the Prototype before the Pac-Man robot
and it had a really nice looking
gate where you know it would stick the
leg out it would do heel strike first
before it rolled onto the toe so you
didn't land with a flat foot you
extended your leg a little bit
um but even then it was hard to get the
robot to walk where when you're walking
that it fully extended its leg
and getting that all to work well
took such a long time in fact I I
probably didn't really see the nice
natural walking that I expected out of
our humanoids until maybe last year
and the team was developing on our newer
generation of Atlas you know some new
techniques
for developing a walking control
algorithm and they got that natural
looking motion as sort of a byproduct of
a just a different process that we're
applying to developing the control
so that probably took 15 years 10 to 15
years to sort of get that from from you
know
the Petman prototype was probably in
2008 and what was it 2022 last year that
I think I saw a good walking on Atlas
the following is a conversation with
Robert plater CEO of Boston Dynamics a
legendary robotics company that over 30
years has created some of the most
elegant dexterous and simply amazing
robots ever built including the humanoid
robot Atlas and the robot dog spot
one or both of whom you've probably seen
on the internet either dancing doing
backflips opening doors or uh throwing
around heavy objects
Robert has led both the development of
Boston Dynamics humanoid robots and
their physics-based simulation software
he has been with the company from the
very beginning including its roots at
MIT where he received his PhD in
Aeronautical Engineering this was in
1994 at the legendary MIT leg lab he
wrote his PhD thesis on robot gymnastics
as part of which he programmed a bipedal
robot to do the world's first 3D robotic
somersault
Robert is a great engineer robot
assistant leader and Boston Dynamics to
me as a roboticist is a truly inspiring
company this conversation was a big
honor and pleasure and I hope to do a
lot of great work with these robots in
the years to come
this is the Lex Freedom podcast to
support it please check out our sponsors
in the description and now dear friends
here's Robert plater
when did you first fall in love with
robotics
let's start with love and robots well
love is is relevant because I think the
the fascination the Deep Fascination is
really about movement
and uh
I was visiting MIT looking for a place
to get a PhD and I wanted to do some
laboratory work and one of my professors
at in the Aero Department said go see
this guy mark raber down in the basement
of the AI lab
and so I walked down there and saw him
he showed me his robots
and he showed me this robot doing a
somersault
and I just immediately went whoa you
know yeah robots can do that and because
of my own interest in in gymnastics
there was like this immediate connection
and um you know I was interested in I
was in an arrow Astro degree because you
know flight and movement was all so
fascinating to me and then it turned out
that you know robotics had this big
challenge how do you how do you balance
uh how do you how do you build a legged
robot that can really get around
and that just that was a Fascination and
it still exists today you're still
working on perfecting Motion in robots
what about the elegance and the beauty
of the movement itself is is there
something
maybe grounded in your appreciation of
uh movement from your gymnastics days
did you
was there something you just
fundamentally appreciate about the
elegance and beauty of movement you know
we had this concept in in gymnastics of
um
letting your body do what it wanted to
do when you get really good at
gymnastics
part of what you're doing is putting
your your body into a position where the
physics and the body's inertia and
momentum will kind of push you in the
right direction in a very natural and
organic way
and the thing that Mark was doing you
know in the basement of that laboratory
was trying to figure out how to build
machines to take advantage of those
ideas how do you build something so that
the physics of the machine just kind of
inherently wants to do what it wants to
do and he was building these springy
pogo stick type you know his first cut
at Lego Locomotion was a pogo stick
where it's bouncing and there's a spring
Mass
a system that's oscillating has its own
sort of natural frequency there and sort
of figuring out how to augment those
natural physics
with also intent how do you then control
that but not overpower it it's that
coordination that I think creates real
potential we could call it Beauty yeah
you could call it I don't know Synergy
that people have different words for it
but I think that that was inherent from
the beginning that was clear to me that
that's part of what Mark was trying to
do he asked me to do that in my research
work so
um you know that's where I got going so
part of the thing that I think I'm
calling elegance and Beauty in this case
which was there even with the pogo stick
is maybe the efficiency so letting the
body do what it wants to do
trying to discover the efficient
movement it's definitely more efficient
it also becomes easier to control in its
own way because the physics are solving
some of the problem itself it's not like
you have to do all this calculation and
overpower the physics the physics
naturally inherently want to do the
right thing
there can even be you know a feedback
mechanisms stabilizing mechanisms
that occur simply by virtue of the
physics of the body and it's you know
not all
not all in the computer or not even all
in your mind as a person and I there's
something interesting in that melding
you were with Mark for many many many
years but you were there in this kind of
legendary space
of leg lab and a my team in the basement
all great things happen in the basement
is there some memories uh is there some
money from that time
that you have because it's so it's such
Cutting Edge work
in in in robotics and artificial
intelligence
the memories the distinctive lessons I
would say I learned in that in that time
period
and um and that I think Mark was a great
teacher of
was it's okay to pursue your interest
your curiosity do something because you
love it
um you'll do it a lot better if you love
it
um
that that is a lasting lesson that I
think uh we apply at the company still
um and really is a core value so the
interesting thing is I got to um
uh with people like Ross Cedric and
um and others like the students that
work at those robotics labs are like
some of the happiest people I've ever
met
I don't know what that is I mean a lot
of PhD students a lot of them are kind
of broken by the wear and tear of the
process uh but roboticists are while
they work extremely hard and work a long
hours
there's a
there's a happiness there the only other
group of people I met like that are
people that Skydive a lot like for some
reason there's a deep fulfilling
happiness maybe from like a long period
of struggle to get a thing to work and
it works and there's a magic to it I
don't know exactly because it's so
fundamentally Hands-On and you're
bringing a thing to life I don't know
what it is but they're happy
we see you know our our attrition at the
company is really low people come and
they love the pursuit
and I think part of that is that there's
perhaps an external connection to it
it's a little bit easier to connect when
you have a robot that's moving around in
the world and part of your goal is to
make it move around in the world
you can identify with that and and this
is on a this is one of the unique things
about the kinds of robots we're building
is this physical interaction
lets you perhaps identify with it so I
think that is a source of happiness I
don't think it's Unique to robotics I
think anybody also who is just pursuing
something they love
it's easier to work hard at it and be
good at it and
um
not everybody gets to find that I I do
feel lucky in that way and I think we're
lucky as an organization that we've been
able to build a business around this and
that keeps people engaged
so if it's all right let's link on mark
for a little bit longer Mark raybert so
he's a legend
uh he's a legendary engineer Roboto says
what what have you learned about life
about Robotics and Mark through all the
many years you worked with him I think
the most important lesson which was you
know have the courage of your
convictions and and do what you think is
interesting
um
be willing to try to find big big
problems to go after and at the time you
know like at Locomotion
um especially in a dynamic machine
nobody had solved it and that felt like
a
multi-decade problem to go after
and so you know have the courage to go
after that because you're interested
don't worry if it's going to make money
you know that that's been a theme so
that that's really uh probably the most
uh important lesson I think that uh I
got from Mark how crazy is the effort of
doing legged
robotics at that time especially
you know Mark got some stuff to work uh
starting from the simple ideas oh so
maybe the other another important idea
that has really become a value of the
company is try to simplify a thing to
the Core Essence
and and while you know Mark was showing
videos of animals running across the
Savannah or uh uh climbing mountains
what he started with was a pogo stick
because he was trying to reduce the
problem to something that was manageable
and and getting the pogo stick to
balance had in it
the fundamental problems that if we
solve those you could eventually
extrapolate to something that galloped
like a horse
and so look for those simplifying
principles
um how tough is the job of simplifying a
robot so I I'd say in the early days the
the thing that made Boston
the researchers at Boston Dynamics
special
is that we we worked on under figuring
out what that that Central principle was
and then building software or machines
around that principle and that was not
easy in the early days and and it it
took
um real expertise in understanding the
Dynamics of motion and feedback control
principles and how to build and with
computers at the time how to build a
feedback control algorithm that was
simple enough that it could run in real
time at a thousand Hertz
and actually get that machine to work
um and that was not something everybody
was doing you know at that time
now the world's changing now and I I I
think the approach is to controlling
robots are going to change
um but uh and they're going to become
more broadly yet
um available
um but at the time there weren't many
groups who could really sort of work at
that principled level
with both the software and
and make the hardware work
and I'll and I'll say one other thing
about your sort of talking about what
are the special things the other thing
was it's okay it's good to break stuff
you know
um you know use the robots break them
repair them
um you know fix and repeat test fix and
repeat and that and that's also a core
principle that has become part of the
company
and it lets you be Fearless in your work
too often if you are working with a very
expensive robot maybe one that you
bought from somebody else or that you
don't know how to fix then you treat it
with kit gloves and you can't actually
make progress you have to be able to
break something and so I think that's a
been a a principle as well so just the
link on that psychologically how do you
deal with that because I remember I had
uh
uh I built a RC car
with that some
uh it had some custom stuff like compute
on it and all that kind of stuff cameras
and uh because I didn't sleep much the
code I wrote has an issue where it
didn't stop the car and then the car got
confused and at full speed at like 20 25
miles an hour slammed into a wall
and I just remember sitting there alone
in the deep sadness
um
sort of
full of regret I think almost anger
um
uh but also like sadness because you
think about well these robots especially
for autonomous vehicles like like you
should be taking safety very seriously
even in these kinds of things but just
no good feelings and made me more afraid
probably to do this kind of experiments
in the future perhaps the right way to
have seen that is positively
like it's it's too it depends if you
could have built that car or or just
gotten another one right that would have
been the approach
um I remember
um
when I got to grad school
um you know I got some training about uh
operating a lathe and a mill up in the
machine shop and I could start to make
my own parts and I remember breaking
some piece of equipment in the lab and
then realizing
because I maybe this was a unique part
and I couldn't go buy it and I realized
oh I can just go make it
that was an enabling feeling yeah then
you're not afraid yeah it might take
time it might take more work than you
thought it was going to be required to
get this thing done
but you can just go make it and that's
freeing in a way that nothing else is
you mentioned uh the the feedback
control the Dynamics sorry for the
Romantic question but is in the early
days and even now is the Dynamics
probably more appropriate for the early
days is it more art or science
there's a lot of science around it
and and trying to develop you know
scientific principles
that let you extrapolate from like one
legged machine to another
you know develop a core set of
principles like like a spring Mass
bouncing system and then figure out how
to apply that from a one-legged machine
to a two or a four-legged machine those
principles are really important and and
we're definitely a core part of our work
there's also
you know when we started to pursue
humanoid robots
um there was so much complexity in that
machine
that
you know one of the benefits of the
humanoid form is you have some intuition
about how it should look while it's
moving
and that's a little bit of an art I
think and now I'd say or maybe it's just
tapping into a knowledge that you have
deep in your body and then trying to
express that in the machine but that's
an intuition that's a little bit more on
the art side maybe it it predates your
knowledge you know before you have the
knowledge of how to control it you try
to work through the Art Channel and
humanoids sort of make that available to
you if it had been a different shape
maybe we wouldn't have had the same
intuition about it yeah so you're
knowledge about moving through the world
is not made explicit to you
so you just that's why it's art and it
might yeah it might be hard to actually
articulate exactly you know there's
something about
um and being a competitive uh athlete
there's something about
seeing a movement you know a coach one
of their greatest strengths a coach has
is being able to see you know some
little change in what the athlete is
doing and then being able to articulate
that to the athlete you know and then
maybe even trying to say and you should
try to feel this
um so there's something just in scene
and again you know sometimes it's hard
to articulate what it is you're seeing
but there's a
receiving the motion at a rate that is
again sometimes hard to put into words
yeah I
Wonder
how it is possible to achieve sort of
truly elegant movement you have a movie
like ex machina I'm not sure if you've
seen it but the main actress in that who
plays the AI robot I think is a
ballerina I mean just a natural
elegance and the I don't know eloquence
of movement
it's it's it looks efficient and easy
and just it looks right
it looks it looks right is sort of the
key yeah and then you you look at uh
especially early robots I mean they
they're so cautious in in the way they
move that
it's not it's not the caution that looks
wrong it's it's something about the
movement that looks wrong that feels
like it's very inefficient unnecessarily
so and it's hard to put that into words
exactly we think that and part of the
reason why people are attracted to the
machines we build
is because the inherent dynamics of
movement are are closer to right
um because we we try to use you know
walking Gates or we build a machine
around this gate where you're trying to
work with the Dynamics of the machine
instead of
to stop them you know some of the early
walking machines
you know you're essentially you're
really trying hard to not let them fall
over and so you're always stopping the
Tipping motion you know
and sort of the insight
of dynamic stability and a lighted
machine is to go with it you know let
the Tipping happen you know let yourself
fall but then catch her catch yourself
with that next foot and there's
something about getting those physics to
be expressed in the machine
that people interpret as
lifelike or or elegant or just natural
looking and so I think if you get the
physics right
it also ends up being more efficient
likely
there's a benefit that it probably ends
up being
more stable in the long run you know it
could it could walk stably over a wider
uh rain range of conditions
and it's uh and it's more beautiful and
attractive at the same time so how hard
is it to get the humanoid robot Atlas
to do some of the things that's recently
been doing let's forget the flips and
all of that let's just look at the
running
maybe you can correct me but there's
something about running I mean that's
not careful at all that's you're falling
forward
you're jumping forward and they're
falling so how hard is it to get that
right our first humanoid we needed to
deliver natural looking walking you know
we took a contract uh from the army they
wanted a robot that could walk naturally
they wanted to put a suit on the robot
and be able to test it in a gas
environment and so they wanted that the
motion to be natural
and so our goal was a natural looking
gate it was real it was surprisingly
hard to get that to work
and we but we did build an early machine
we called it pet man prototype it was
the Prototype before the Pac-Man robot
and it had a really nice looking
gate where you know it would stick the
leg out it would do heel strike first
before it rolled onto the toe so you
didn't land with a flat foot you
extended your leg a little bit
but even then it was hard to get the
robot to walk where when you're walking
that it fully extended its leg and
essentially landed on an extended leg
and if you watch closely how you walk
you probably land on an extended leg but
then you immediately flex your knee as
you start to make that contact
and getting that all to work well
took such a long time in fact I I
probably didn't really see the nice
natural walking that I expected out of
our humanoids until maybe last year
and the team was developing on our newer
generation of Atlas you know some new
techniques
um uh for developing a walking control
algorithm and they got that natural
looking motion as sort of a byproduct of
a just a different process they were
applying to developing the control
so that probably took 15 years 10 to 15
years to sort of get that from from you
know the Petman prototype was probably
in 2008 and what was it 2022 last year
that I think I saw a good walking on
Atlas if you could just like Linger on
it what are some challenges of getting
good walking so is it uh
is this is this partially like a
hardware like actuator problem is it the
control is it the artistic element of
just observing the whole system
operating in different conditions
together I mean is there some kind of
interesting
quirks or challenges you can speak to
like the heel strike yeah so one of the
things that makes the like this straight
leg uh a challenge is you're sort of up
against a singularity a mathematical
single Singularity where you know when
your leg is fully extended it can't go
further the other direction right
there's only you can only move in One
Direction and that makes all of the
calculations around how to produce
twerks at that joint or positions makes
it more complicated and so having all
the mathematics so it can deal with
these singular configurations is one of
many challenges uh that we face and I'd
say in in the
you know in those earlier days again we
were working with these really
simplified models
so we're trying to boil all the physics
of the complex human body into a simpler
subsystem that we can more easily
describe in mathematics and sometimes
those simpler subsystems don't have all
of that complexity of the straight leg
built into them and so what's happened
more recently is we're able to apply
techniques that let us take the full
physics of the robot into account and
and deal with some of those strange
situations like this like the straight
leg so is there a fundamental challenge
here that it's uh maybe you can correct
me but is it under actuated are you
falling under actuated is the right word
right you can't you can't uh push the
robot in any direction you want to right
and so that that is one of the hard
problems of of uh like at Locomotion and
you have to do that for natural movement
it's not necessarily required for
natural movement it's just required
you know we don't have you know a
gravity force that you can hook yourself
onto to apply uh an external force in
the direction you want at all times
right the only the only external forces
are being mediated through your feet and
how they get mediated depend on how you
place your feet and uh you know you
can't just uh you know God's hand can't
reach down and give and push in any
direction you want you know so is there
uh is there some extra challenge to the
fact that Alice is such a big robot
there is the humanoid form is um
attractive in many ways but it's also a
challenge in many ways
um
you have this big upper body that has a
lot of mass and inertia
um and throwing that inertia around
increases the complexity of maintaining
balance and as soon as you pick up
something heavy in your arms you've made
that problem even harder
and so uh in the early work in the leg
lab and in the early days at the company
and we were pursuing these quadruped
robots which had a a kind of built-in
simplification you had this big rigid
body and then really light legs so when
you swing the legs
the leg motion didn't impact the body
motion very much
all the mass and inertia was in the body
but when you have the humanoid that
doesn't work you have big heavy legs you
swing the legs it affects everything
else
and so
dealing with all of that interaction
does make the humanoid a much more
complicated platform
and I also saw that at least recently
you've been doing more explicit modeling
of the stuff you pick up yeah which is
very real
um really interesting so you have to
what model the shape
the weight distribution
[Music]
I don't know what like you have to under
like include that as part of the
modeling as part of the planning because
okay so for people who don't know
uh so Atlas at least in like a recent
video like throws a heavy bag throws a
bunch of stuff
so what what's involved in uh picking up
a thing a heavy thing
uh and when that thing is a bunch of
different non-standard things I think it
also picked up like a barbell
and to be able to throw in some cases
what are some interesting challenges
there
so we were definitely trying to show
that the robot and the techniques were
applying to the robe uh to Atlas let us
deal with heavy things in the world
because if the robot's going to be
useful it's actually got to move stuff
around yeah and that and that needs to
be significant stuff that's an
appreciable portion of the the body
weight of the robot
and we also think this differentiates us
from the other humanoid robot activities
that you're seeing out there mostly
they're not picking stuff up yet
and not heavy stuff anyway
um but just like you or me you know you
need to anticipate that moment you know
you're reaching out to pick something up
and as soon as you pick it up your
center of mass is going to shift
and if you're gonna you know turn in a
circle you have to take that inertia
into account and if you're gonna throw a
thing you know you've got all of that
has to be sort of included in in the
model of what you're trying to do so the
robot needs to have some idea or
expectation of what that weight is and
then and sort of predict you know think
a couple of seconds ahead how do I
manage my now my my body plus this big
heavy thing together to get and and
still maintain balance right and so um I
I uh that's a big change for us and I
think the tools we've built are really
allowing that to happen
um quickly now some of those motions
that you saw in that most recent video
we were able to create in a matter of
days it used to be it took six months to
do anything new you know on your robot
and and now we're starting to develop
the tools that let us do that in a
matter of days and so we think that's
really exciting it means that the
ability to create new behaviors for the
robot is going to be um
a quicker process so being able to
explicitly model
new things that it might need to pick up
new type of thing and you know to some
degree you don't you don't want to have
to pay too much attention to each
specific thing right
um there's sort of a generalization here
yeah
um obviously when you grab a thing you
have to conform your your hand your end
effector to the surface of that shape
but once it's in your hands it's
probably just the mass and inertia that
matter and the the shape may not be as
important yeah and so you know for some
in some ways you want to pay attention
to that detailed shape and in others you
want to generalize it and say uh well
all I really care about is the center of
mass of this thing especially if I'm
going to throw it up on that scaffolding
and it's easier if the body is rigid
what if it's there's some doesn't it
throw like a sandbag type thing that
tool bag you know you've had loose had
loose stuff in it yeah so it it managed
that there are harder things that we
haven't done yet you know we could have
had a big jointed thing or I don't know
a bunch of loose wire or rope what about
carrying another robot how about that
yeah we haven't we haven't done that yet
I guess we did a little bit of uh we did
a a little skit around Christmas where
we had two spots holding up another spot
that was trying to put you know a bow on
a tree so I guess we're doing that in a
small way
okay that's pretty good uh let me ask
the all-important question uh do you
know how much Atlas can curl goodbye
have you
I mean you know this for us humans
that's really one of the most
fundamental questions you can ask
another human being a bench it probably
can't curl as much as we can yet but a
metric that I think is interesting is um
you know another way of looking at that
strength
is you know the box jump so if how high
of a box can you jump onto question and
uh Alice I don't know the exact height
it was probably a meter high or
something like that it was a pretty
pretty tall jump that Atlas was able to
manage when we last tried to do this and
and I have video of my chief technical
officer
doing the same jump and he really
struggled you know the human but the
human getting all the way on top of this
box but then you know Atlas was able to
do it
um we're now thinking about the next
generation of Atlas and we're probably
going to be in the realm of a person
can't do it you know with this with the
Next Generation you know the robots the
actuators are going to get stronger
where there really is the case that at
least some of these joints some of these
motions will be stronger and to
understand how high it can jump you
probably had to do quite a bit of
testing oh yeah and there's lots of
videos of it trying and failing and
that's you know that's all you know we
don't always release those those videos
but they're a lot of fun to look at
uh so we'll talk a little bit about that
uh but if can you talk to the jumping
because you talked about the walking it
took a long time many many years to get
the walking to be natural but there's
also really natural looking
uh robust resilient jumping how hard is
it to do the jumping
well again this stuff has really evolved
rapidly in the last few years you know
the first time we did a somersault
um you know there's a lot of kind of
manual iteration
what is the trajectory you know how hard
do you throw it in fact in these early
days uh I actually would when I'd see
early experiments that the team was
doing I might make suggestions about how
to change the technique again kind of
borrowing from my own intuition about
how backflips work
um
but frankly they don't need that anymore
so in the early days you had to iterate
kind of in almost a manual way trying to
change these trajectories of the arms or
the legs to try to get you know a
successful backflip to happen
but more recently we're running
these model predictive uh control
techniques where we're able to the robot
essentially can think in advance for the
next second or two about how its motion
is going to transpire and you can you
know solve for optimal trajectories to
get from A to B so this is happening in
a much more natural way and we're really
seeing an acceleration happen in the
development of these behaviors again
partly due to these
optimization techniques uh sometimes
learning techniques
so it's there's it's hard in that
there's a lot of mathematics in behind
it but we're figuring that out so you
can do model predictive control for
uh I mean I don't even understand what
that looks like when the entire robot is
in the air flying and doing a back yeah
I mean but but that's the cool part
right so you know yeah you know the
physics we we can calculate physics
pretty well using you know Newton's laws
about how it's going to evolve over time
and the road you know this this the sick
trick which was a front somersault with
a half twist is a good example right
you saw the robot on various versions of
that trick I've seen it land in
different configurations and it still
manages to stabilize itself and so you
know what this model predictive control
means is again the in real time the
robot is projecting ahead you know a
second into the future and sort of
exploring options and if I if I move my
arm a little bit more this way how is
that going to affect the outcome and so
it can do these calculations many of
them you know uh and and basically solve
for you know given where I am now maybe
I took off a little bit screwy from how
I had planned I can adjust so you're
adjusting in there just on the fly so
the the model predictive control lets
you adjust on the Fly
and of course I think this is what you
know people adapt as well we when when
we do it even a gymnastics trick we try
to set it up so it's as close to the
same every time but we figured out how
to do some adjustment on the Fly and now
we're starting to figure out that the
robots can do this adjustment on the fly
as well using these techniques in the
air
and so I mean it just feels from a
robotics perspective just surreal well
that's sort of the you talked about
under actuated right so when you're when
you're in the air there's something
there's some things you can't change
right you can't change the momentum
while it's in the air because you can't
apply an external force or Torque and so
the momentum isn't going to change so
how do you work within the constraint of
that fixed momentum to still get from A
to B where you want to be that's really
unfortunate
you're in the air I mean you become a
drone for a brief moment of time no
you're not even a drone because you
can't can't ever you can't hover you're
gonna you're gonna impact soon be ready
yeah are you considered like a hover
type thing or no no it's too much weight
I mean it's just it's just incredible uh
and just even to have the guts to try
backflip with such a large body
that's wild but like uh we definitely
broke a few robots trying but that but
that's where the build it break it fix
it you know uh strategy comes in you
gotta be willing to break and what ends
up happening is you end up by breaking
the robot repeatedly you find the weak
points and then you end up redesigning
it so it doesn't break so easily next
time you know through the breaking
process you learn a lot like a lot of
lessons and you keep improving not just
how to make the backflip work but
everything and how to build the machine
better yeah yeah
I mean is there something about just the
guts that
come up with an idea of saying you know
what let's try to make it do a backflip
well I think the courage to do a
backflip in the first place and and to
not worry too much about the ridicule of
somebody saying why the heck are you
doing backflips with robots because a
lot of people have asked that you know
why why why are you doing this why go to
the moon in this decade and do the other
things JFK
[Laughter]
it's not because it's easy because it's
hard yeah exactly
don't ask questions okay so the uh the
jumping I mean it's just there's a lot
of incredible stuff if we can just
rewind a little bit to uh the DARPA
robotics challenge in 2015 I think which
was for people who are familiar with the
DARPA challenges
it uh was first with autonomous vehicles
and there's a lot of interesting
challenges around that and the DARPA
robotics challenge is when uh humanoid
robots were tasked to do all kinds of
uh you know manipulation walking driving
your car all these kinds of challenges
with if I remember correctly sort of
some slight capability to communicate
with humans but the communication was
very poor so it basically has to be
almost entirely autonomous you can have
periods where the communication was
entirely interrupted and the robot had
to be able to proceed yeah but you could
provide some high level guidance to the
robot basically load low bandwidth
Communications to steer it I watched
that challenge with kind of tears in my
eyes eating popcorn
but I wasn't personally losing uh you
know hundreds of thousands millions of
dollars and many years of incredible
hard work by some of the most brilliant
roboticists in the world so that was why
the tragic that's why tears came so
anyway what what have you uh just
looking back to that time what have you
learned from that experience
I mean maybe if you could describe what
it was uh sort of the setup for people
who haven't seen it well so there was a
contest where a bunch of different
um robots were asked to do a series of
tasks uh some of those that you
mentioned drive a vehicle get out open a
door go identify a vowel shutter valve
use a tool to maybe cut a hole in
um
a surface and then crawl over some
stairs and maybe some rough Terrain
so it was
the idea was have a general purpose
robot that could do lots of different
things
um it had to be mobility and
manipulation on board perception
and there was a contest which DARPA
likes at the time was running sort of
follow on to the
the Grand Challenge which was let's
let's try to push vehicle autonomy along
right they they encourage people to
build autonomous cars so they're trying
to basically push an industry forward
and
um
uh we were asked our role in this was to
build
um a humanoid at the time it was our
sort of first generation Atlas robot
and we built maybe 10 of them I don't
remember the exact number
and DARPA distributed those to various
teams
um that sort of won a contest showed
that they could you know program these
robots and then use them to compete
against each other and then other robots
were introduced as well some teams built
their own robots Carnegie
um melon for example built their own
robot and uh and all these robots
competed to see who could sort of get
through this this maze or the fastest
and again I think the purpose was to
kind of push the whole industry forward
we provided the robot and some baseline
software but we didn't we didn't
actually compete as a participant uh
where we were trying to uh you know
Drive the robot through this maze we
were just trying to support the other
teams
it was humbling because it was it was
really a hard task and honestly the
robots the tears were because mostly the
robots didn't do it you know they fell
down
you know repeatedly
um it was hard to get through this
contest uh some did and and you know
they were rewarded and won
but it was humbling because of just how
hard these tasks weren't all that hard a
person could have done it very easily
but it was really hard to get the robots
to do it you know the general nature of
it the variety of it the variety and
also that I don't know if the tasks were
sort of the task in themselves help us
understand what is difficult and what is
not I don't know if that was obvious
before the contest was designed so you
kind of tried to figure that out and I
think Atlas is really a general robot
platform and it's perhaps not best
suited for the specific tasks of that
contest like for just for example
probably the hardest task is not the
driving of the car but getting in and
out of the car and Atlas probably you
know if you were to design a robot that
can get into the car easily and get out
easily you probably would not make Atlas
that particular car yeah the robot was a
little bit big to get in and out of that
car right it doesn't fit yeah this is
the curse of a general purpose robot
that they're not perfect at any one
thing
but they might be able to do a wide
variety of things and and that is
that is the goal at the end of the day
you know I think we all want to build
general purpose robots that can be used
for lots of different activities
but it's hard and
um and the wisdom in in building
successful robots up until this point
have been go build a robot for a
specific task and it'll do it very well
and as long as you control that
environment it'll operate perfectly but
but robots need to be able to deal with
uncertainty if they're going to be
useful to us in the future
they need to be able to deal with
unexpected uh situations and that's sort
of the goal of a general purpose or
multi-purpose robot
and that's just darn hard and so some of
you know there's these curious little
failures like I remember one of the a
robot you know the first the first time
you start to try to push on the world
with a robot you you forget that the
world pushes back and and will push you
over if you're not ready for it and the
robot you know reached to grab the door
handle I think it missed the grasp of
the door handle was expecting that its
hand was on the door handle and so when
it tried to turn the knob it just threw
itself over it didn't realize oh I had
missed the door handle I didn't have I
didn't I was expecting a force back from
the door it wasn't there and then I lost
my balance so these little simple things
that you and I would take totally for
granted and deal with the robots don't
know how to deal with yet and so you
have to start to deal with all of those
uh circumstances well I think a lot of
us experience this in uh even when sober
but drunk too uh sort of you pick up a
thing and expect it to be
what is it heavy and it turns out to be
light yeah oh yeah and then so the same
and I'm sure if your depth perception
for whatever reason is screwed up if
you're if you're drunk or some other
reason and then you think you're putting
your hand on the table and you miss it I
mean it's the same kind of situation
yeah but
there's why you need to be able to
predict forward just a little bit and so
that's where this model predictive
control stuff comes in predict forward
what you think is going to happen
and then if and if that does happen
you're in good shape if something else
happens you better start predicting
again so if we like we re-uh regenerate
a plan yeah when you don't I mean that
um that also requires a very uh fast
feedback loop of updating
what your prediction how it matches to
the actual real world
yeah those things have to run pretty
quickly what's the challenge of running
things pretty quickly a thousand Hertz
of acting and sensing
quickly you know there's a few different
layers of that you you want at the
lowest level you like to run things
typically at around a thousand Hertz
which means that you know at each joint
of the robot you're measuring position
or force and then trying to control your
actuator whether it's a hydraulic or
electric motor trying to control the
force coming out of that actuator and
you want to do that really fast
something like a thousand Hertz and that
means you can't have too much
calculation going on at that joint
um but that's pretty manageable these
days and it's fairly common
and then there's another layer that
you're probably calculating you know
maybe at 100 Hertz maybe 10 times slower
which is now starting to look at the
overall body motion and thinking about
the the larger physics of of the uh of
the robot
um and then there's yet another loop
that's probably happening a little bit
slower which is where you start to bring
you know your perception and your vision
and things like that and so you need to
run all of these Loops sort of
simultaneously you do have to manage
your your computer time so that you can
squeeze in all the calculations you need
in real time in a very consistent way
and the amount of calculation we can do
is increasing as computers get better
which means we can start to do more
sophisticated calculations I can have a
more complex model
doing my forward prediction
and and that might allow me to do even
better predictions as I as I get better
and better and and it used to be again
we had
you know 10 years ago
we had to have pretty simple models
that we were running you know at those
fast rates because the computers weren't
as capable about calculating forward
with a sophisticated model but as as
computation gets better we can we can do
more of that what about the actual
pipeline of software engineering how
easy it is to keep updating Atlas like
Duke continuous development on it so how
many computers
are on there is there a nice pipeline
it's an important part of building a
team around it which means you know you
need to also have a software tools
simulation tools you know so
um we have always made strong use of
physics-based simulation tools to do uh
some of this calculation basically
tested in simulation before you put it
on the robot but you also want the same
code that you're running in simulation
to be the same code you're running on
the hardware and so even getting to the
point where it was the same code going
from one to the other
we probably didn't really get that
working until you know a few years
several years ago
um but that was a you know that was a
bit of a milestone and so you want to
work certainly work these pipelines so
that you can make it as easy as possible
and have a bunch of people working in
parallel especially when you know we
only have you know four of the atlas
robots the modern Atlas robots at the
company
and you know we probably have you know
40 developers there all trying to gain
access to it and so you need to share
resources and use some of these uh some
of the software pipeline well that's a
really exciting step to be able to run
the exact same code and simulation as on
the actual robot uh how hard is it to do
uh realistic simulation physics-based
simulation of of Atlas such that I mean
the dream is like if it works in
simulation works perfectly in reality
how hard is it to sort of keep workout
closing that Gap the root of some of our
physics-based simulation tools really
started at MIT and
um we built some some good physics-based
modeling tools there
the early days of the company we were
trying to develop those tools as a
commercial product so we continued to
develop them it wasn't a particularly
successful commercial product but we
ended up with some nice physics-based
simulation tools so that when we started
doing legged robotics again we had a
really nice tool to work with
and the things we paid attention to were
were things that weren't necessarily
handled very well in the commercial
tools you could buy off the shelf like
like interaction with the world like
foot ground contact so trying to model
those contact
um events well
in a way that captured the important
parts of the interaction
was a really important element uh to get
right and to also do in a way that was
computationally feasible
and could run fast because if you if
your simulation runs too slow you know
then your developers are sitting around
waiting for stuff to run and compile so
it's always about efficient uh a fast
operation as well so that's been a big
part of it you know I think developing
those tools in parallel to the
development of the the platform and
trying to scale them has has really been
essential I'd say to us being able to
assemble a team of people that could do
this yeah how to simulate contact
periods so flick ground contact but sort
of for manipulation
because don't you want to model all
kinds of surfaces yeah so it will be
even more complex with manipulation
because there's a lot more going on you
know and you need to capture I don't
know things slipping and moving you know
in in your in your hand
um it's a level of complexity that I
think goes above foot ground contact
when you really start doing dexterous
manipulation so there's challenges ahead
still so how far are we away from me
being able to walk with Atlas in the
sand along the beach and
us both drinking a beer
yeah maybe we can out of a kid maybe
Atlas could spill his beer because he's
got nowhere to put it
Alice could walk on the sand uh so can
it yeah uh yeah I mean you know have we
really had him out on the beach you know
we take them outside often you know
rocks Hills that sort of thing even just
around our lab in Waltham we probably
haven't been on the sand but I'm a salt
surface I don't doubt that we could deal
with it yeah we we might have to spend a
little bit of time to sort of make that
work but we did take uh we we had a had
to take
big dog to Thailand years ago and uh we
did this great video of the robot
walking in the sand walking into the
ocean up to I don't know its belly or
something like that and then turning
around and walking out all while playing
some cool beach music yeah great show
but then you know we didn't really clean
the robot off and the salt water was
really hard on it so you know we put it
in a box shipped it back by the time it
came back we had some problems with salt
it's the salt water it's not like old
stuff it's not like sand getting into
the components or something like this
but I'm sure if if this is a big
priority you can make it like waterproof
right that just wasn't our our goal at
the time well it's a personal goal of
mine to it walk along the beach but it's
a human problem too you get sand
everywhere it's it's just a jam mess
so soft surfaces are okay so I mean can
we just uh link on the the robotics
challenge there's a there's a pile of uh
like Rubble they had to walk over is
that's
um how difficult is that task
in the early days of developing big dog
the loose Rock was the epitome of the
hard walking surface because you step
down and then the Rock and you had these
little Point feet on the robot
and the rock and roll and and you have
to deal with that last minute you know
change in your foot placement yes so you
you step on the thing and that thing
responds to you stepping on it yeah and
and it moves where your point of support
is and so it's really that that became
kind of the essence of the test and so
that was the beginning of us starting to
build Rock piles in our parking lots and
and we would actually build boxes full
of rocks and bring them into the lab and
then we would have the robots walking
across these boxes of rocks because that
became the essential test
so you mentioned big dog can you can we
maybe take a stroll through the history
of Boston Dynamics uh so what and who's
Big Dog by the way is who
do you try not to anthropomorphize the
robots do you try not to
to try to remember that they're this is
like the division I have because I for
me it's impossible
for me there's a magic to the to the
being that is a robot it is not human
but it is
the same Magic
uh the living being has when it moves
about the world is there in the robot so
um I don't know what question I'm asking
but uh should I say what or who I guess
who is Big Dog what is big dog
well I'll say to address the medic
question
we don't try to draw hard lines around
it being an it or a him or a her
um it's okay right people I think part
of the magic of these kinds of machines
is by nature of their organic movement
of the of their Dynamics
we tend to want to identify with them we
tend to look at them and sort of
attribute
maybe feeling to that because we've only
seen things that move like this that
were alive
and so
um this is an opportunity it means that
you could have
feelings for a machine and you know
people have feelings for their cars you
know they get attracted to them attached
to them so that's inherently could be a
good thing as long as we manage what
that interaction is
so we don't put strong boundaries around
this and ultimately think it's a benefit
but it's also can be a bit of a curse
because I think people look at these
machines
and they attribute a level of
intelligence that the machines don't
have why because again they've seen
things move like this that we're living
beings
which are intelligent
and so they want to attribute
intelligence to the robots that isn't
appropriate yet even though they move
like an intelligent being but you try to
acknowledge that the
anthropomorphization is there and try to
first of all acknowledge that it's there
and have a little fun with it you know
our most recent video
it's just kind of fun you know to to
look at the robot we started off the the
video with Atlas
um kind of looking around for where the
bag of tools was because the guy up on
the scaffolding says send me some tools
Atlas has to kind of look around and see
where they are and there's a little
personality there that is fun it's
entertaining it makes our jobs
interesting and I think in the long run
can enhance interaction between humans
and robots that in a way that isn't
available to machines that don't move
that way this is something to me
personally is very interesting I've been
um
I happen to have a lot of legged robots
I hope uh to have a lot of spots in my
possession
um I'm interested in celebrating
Robotics and celebrating companies and I
also don't want to companies that do
incredible stuff like Boston Dynamics
and I there's a
you know I'm a little crazy and you say
you don't want to you you want to align
you want to help the company because I
ultimately want a company that busted an
image to succeed and part of that will
talk about you know success kind of
requires making money
and so the kind of stuff I'm
particularly interested in may not be
the thing that makes money in the short
term I can make an argument they will in
the long term but the kind of stuff I've
been playing with is a robust way of uh
having the quadruped though the robot
dogs communicate emotion with their body
movement the same kind of stuff you do
with it with a dog but not not
hard-coded uh but in a robust way and be
able to communicate excitement or fear
boredom all this kind of stuff and I
think as a base layer
of function of behavior to add on top of
a robot I think that's a really powerful
way uh to make the robot more usable for
humans for whatever application it's
going to be really important and um it's
a thing we're we're beginning to pay
attention to
um we really want to start a
differentiator for the company has
always been we really want the robot to
work we want it to be useful uh
making it work at first meant the the
legged Locomotion really works it can
really get around and it doesn't fall
down and
um but beyond that and now it needs to
be a useful tool and our customers are
for example Factory owners people who
are running a process manufacturing
facility and the robot needs to be able
to get through this complex facility in
a reliable way you know taking taking
measurements
we need for people who are operating
those robots to understand what the
robots are doing
if the robot gets into needs help or or
you know is in trouble or something it
needs to be able to communicate
and a physical indication of some sort
uh to so that a person looked at the
robot and goes oh I know what that's
that robot's doing the robot's going to
go take measurements of my vacuum pump
with its thermal camera
you know you want to be able to indicate
that and or even just the robots
um about to turn you know in front of
you and maybe indicate that it's going
to turn and so you sort of see and can
anticipate its motion so these this kind
of communication is going to become more
and more important it wasn't sort of our
starting point
um you know but now the the robots are
really out in the world and you know we
have about a thousand of them out with
with customers right now
this layer of physical indication I
think is going to become more and more
important we'll talk about where it goes
because there's a lot of interesting
possibilities but if you can return back
to the origins of Boston and Dynamics
with so that the more research the r d
side before we talk about how to build
robots at scale so big dog so um who's
Big Dog so the company started in 1992.
and in um probably uh uh 2003
I believe is when we uh took a contract
from darpto basically 10 years 11 years
um we weren't doing robotics we did a
little bit of Robotics with Sony they
had uh IBO the their IBO robot we were
developing some software for that that
kind of got us a little bit involved
with robotics again then there's this
opportunity to do a DARPA contract where
they wanted to build
a robot dog and uh we we won a contract
to build that and so that was the
Genesis of big dog
and it was a quadruped and it was the
first time we built a robot that had
everything on board that you could
actually take the robot out into the
wild and operate it so it had onboard
power plant it had onboard computers it
had
hydraulic actuators that needed to be
cooled so we had cooling systems built
in
everything integrated into the robot
and uh that was a pretty rough start
right it was it was 10 years that we
were not a robotics company we were a
simulation company and then we had to
build a robot in about a year so that
was a little bit of a rough transition
um
can you just comment on the roughness of
that transition because uh big dog I
mean this is just big
uh quadruped four legs robot rebuilt a
few different versions of them but the
first one you're the very earliest ones
you know it didn't work very well and we
would take them out and it was hard to
get you know uh
you know a go-kart engine driving a
hydraulic that's not what it was
and and you know uh having that all work
uh while trying to get you know the
robot to stabilize itself and so what
was the power plan what was the engine
it seemed like uh my vague direct
collection
I don't know it felt very loud and
aggressive and uh kind of thrown
together that's what it kind of oh it
absolutely was right we weren't trying
to design the best robot Hardware at the
time
and uh we wanted to buy an off-the-shelf
engine and so many of the early versions
of big dog had literally go-kart engines
or something like that usually yeah like
a yeah gas powered two-stroke engine
and the reason why it was two-stroke is
two-stroke engines are lighter weight
but they're also and we we generally
didn't put Mufflers on them because
we're trying to save the weight and we
didn't care about the noise and so these
things were horribly loud
um but we're trying to manage weight
because managing weight in a legged
robot is always important because it has
to carry everything
that said that thing was big well I've
seen the videos yeah I mean the the
early versions you know stood about I
don't know belly High chest High
um you know they probably weighed maybe
a couple of hundred pounds but you know
it over the course of probably five
years
we are able to get that robot
to really manage a remarkable level of
rough terrain so you know we started out
with just walking on the flat and then
we started walking on rocks and then
inclines and then mud and slippery mud
and you know by the end of that program
we were convinced that legged Locomotion
in a robot could actually work because
you know going into it we didn't we
didn't know that we had built quadrupeds
at at MIT
but they were they used a giant
hydraulic pump you know in the lab they
used a giant computer that was in the
lab they were always Tethered to the lab
this was the first time something that
was sort of self-contained you know
walked around in the world
and balance but and and the purpose was
to prove to ourselves that the legged
Locomotion could really work and so
um big dog really cut that open for us
and it was the beginning of what became
a whole series of robots so once once we
showed to darpan that you could make it
like a robot that could work
there was a period at DARPA where
robotics got really hot and there was
lots of different programs
and uh you know we were able to build
other robots we built other quadrupeds
to hand like LS3
designed to carry heavy loads we built
cheetah which was designed to explore
what are the limits to how fast you can
run
you know we began to build sort of a
portfolio
of machines and software that let us
build not just one robot but a whole
family everyone to push the limits in
all kinds of directions yeah and to
discover those principles you know you
asked earlier about the Art and Science
of a leg and locomotion
we it were able to develop principles of
legged Locomotion so that we knew how to
build
a small legged robot or a big one so
like like length you know was now a
parameter that we could play with
payload was a parameter we could play
with so we built the LS3 which was an
800 pound robot designed to carry a 400
pound payload
and we we learned the design rules
basically developed the design rules how
do you scale different robot systems to
you know their terrain to their walking
speed to their payload
so when uh was spot born
2000 and uh 12 or so so again almost 10
years into sort of a run with DARPA
where we built a bunch of different
quadrupeds we had a sort of a different
thread where we started building
humanoids
um we we saw that probably an end was
coming where the government was going to
kind of back off from a lot of Robotics
investment
and uh in order to maintain progress we
just deduced that well we probably need
to sell ourselves to somebody who wants
to continue to invest in this this area
and that was Google
and so
um at Google we would meet regularly
with Larry Page and Larry just started
asking us you know what's your product
going to be and you know the logical
thing the thing that we had the most
history with that we wanted to continue
developing was a quadruped but we knew
it needed to be smaller we knew it
couldn't have a gas engine we thought it
probably couldn't be hydraulically
actuated
so that began the process of exploring
if we could migrate to a smaller
electrically actuated
um robot and that was really the Genesis
of spot
so not a gas engine and the actuators
are electric yes so can you maybe
comment on what it's like
um my Google working with Larry Page
having those meetings and thinking of
what will a robot look like
that could be
built that scale what like starting to
think about a product
Larry always liked the the toothbrush
test he wanted products that you used
every day
um
what they really wanted was
you know a consumer level product
something that would work in your house
we didn't think that was the right next
thing to do because to be a consumer
level product cost is going to be very
important
probably need to cost a few thousand
dollars and we were we were building
these machines that cost hundreds of
thousands of dollars maybe a million
dollars to build of course we were only
building a two but
but we didn't see how to get all the way
to this consumer level product in a
short amount in a short amount of time
and he suggested that we we make the
robots really inexpensive
and part of our philosophy has always
been
build the best hardware you can
make make the machine operate well
so that you're trying to solve
you know discover the the hard problem
that you don't know about don't don't
make it harder by by building a crappy
machine basically you build the best
machine you can there's plenty of hard
problems to solve that are going to have
to do with you know under actuated
systems and balance
and so we wanted to build these high
quality machines still and we thought
that was important for us to continue
learning about really what was the
important parts of the make robots work
um and so there was a little bit of a
philosophical difference there that we
and and so ultimately that's why we're
building robots for the industrial
sector now because the industry can
afford a more expensive machine because
you know their productivity depends on
keeping their Factory going and so if
spot costs you know a hundred thousand
dollars or more that's not such a big
expense to them whereas at the consumer
level no one's going to buy a robot like
that and I think we might eventually get
to a consumer level product that will be
that cheap but I think the path to
getting there needs to go through these
really nice machines so we can then
learn how to simplify
so what can you say to the almost the
engineering challenge of bringing down
costs
of a robot so that presumably when you
try to build the robot at scale that
also comes into play when you're trying
to make money on a robot even in the
industrial setting but how interesting
how challenging
of of a thing is that in particular
probably new to an r d company yeah I'm
glad you brought that last part up the
transition from an r d company to a
commercial company
that's the thing you worry about you
know because you've got these Engineers
who love hard problems who want to
figure out how to make robots work and
you don't know if you have Engineers
that want to work on the quality and
reliability and costs that is ultimately
required
um and indeed you know we have brought
on a lot of new people who are inspired
by those problems
but but the big takeaway lesson for me
is
we have good people we have Engineers
who want to solve problems and and the
quality and cost and manufacturability
is just another kind of problem
and because they're so invested in what
we're doing they're interested in and
we'll go work on on those problems as
well and so I think we're managing that
transition very well in fact I'm really
pleased that
I mean uh it's a huge undertaking by the
way right so even having
to get reliability to where it needs to
be we have to have fleets of robots that
we're just operating 24 7 in our offices
to go find those rare failures and
eliminate them it's just a totally
different kind of activity than the
research activity where you get it to
work you know the one robot you have to
work in a repeatable way you know at the
at the high stakes demo it's just very
different
um but I think we're making remarkable
progress against it so one of the cool
things that got a chance to visit Boston
Dynamics and I mean
one of the things that's really cool is
to see a large number of robots moving
about
because I think one of the things you
notice in the research environment is
the MIT for example I don't think anyone
ever has a working robot for prolonged
exactly so like most robots are just
sitting there in a sad
state of despair waiting to be born
brought to life for a brief moment of
time but just to have I just I just
remember there's like a there's a spot
robot just I I had like a cowboy hat on
it was just walking randomly for
whatever reason I don't even know but
there's a kind of a sense of sentience
to it because it doesn't seem like
anybody was supervising it but it was
just doing it I'm gonna stop way short
of the sentience
um it is the case that if you come to
our office you know today and walk
around the hallways
um you're gonna see a dozen robots just
kind of walking around yes all the time
and that's really a reliability test for
us so we have these robots programmed to
do autonomous missions get up off their
charging dock walk around the building
collect data at a few different places
and go sit back down and we want that to
be a very reliable process because
that's what somebody who's running a a
brewery a factory that's what they need
the robot to do so we have to we have to
dog food our own robot we have to test
it in that way
and um so on a weekly basis we have
robots that are accruing something like
um 1500 or maybe 2 000 kilometers of
walking
and uh you know over a thousand hours of
operation every week and that's
something that almost I don't think
anybody else in the world can do because
hey you have to have a fleet of robots
to just accrue that much information
you have to be willing to dedicate it to
that test and uh so that's but that's
essential that's how you get the
reliability that's how you get it what
about some of the cost cutting from the
from the manufacturer side what what
have you learned from the manufacturer
side of the transition from r d and
we're still we're still learning a lot
there
um we're learning how to cast Parts in
Solo instead of Mill it all out of you
know Billet aluminum
um we're learning how to get plastic
molded parts for and we're learning
about how to control that process so
that you can build the same robot twice
in a row there's a lot to learn there
and we're only part way through that
process
um we've we've set up a manufacturing
facility in Waltham it's about a mile
from our headquarters and we're doing
final assembly and test of both spots
and stretches you know at that factory
and um
and it's hard because to be honest we're
still iterating on the design of the
robot as we find failures from these
reliability tests we need to go engineer
changes and those changes need to now be
propagated to the manufacturing line and
that's a hard process especially when
you want to move as fast as we do
and that's been challenging and it makes
it you know the folks who are working
supply chain who are trying to get the
cheapest parts for us kind of requires
that you buy a lot of them to make them
cheap and then we go change the design
from underneath them and they're like
what are you doing and so you know
getting everybody on the same page here
that it yep we still need to move fast
but we also need to try to figure out
how to reduce costs that's one of the
challenges of of this migration we're
going through and over the past few
years challenges to the supply chain I
mean imagine you've been a part of a
bunch of stressful meetings yeah things
got more expensive and harder to get and
yeah so it's it's all been a challenge
is there still room for simplification
oh yeah much more and you know these are
really just the first generation of
these machines we're already thinking
about what the next generation of spots
going to look like
spot was built as a platform so you
could put almost any sensor on it and we
provided data Communications mechanical
connections uh Power connections
and but for example in the applications
that we're excited about where you're
you're monitoring these factories for
their health
there's probably a simpler machine that
we could build that's really focused on
that use case and that's the difference
between the general purpose machine or
the platform versus the purpose-built
machine and so even though even in the
factory we'd still like the robot to do
lots of different tasks if it's if we
really knew on day one that we're going
to be operating in a factory with these
three sensors in it we would have it all
integrated in a package that would be
easier more less expensive and more
reliable so we're contemplating building
you know a next generation of that
machine so she mentioned that there's a
spot
for people who somehow are not familiar
uh so it's a yellow robotic dog
and
um has been featured in many Dance
videos it also has gained an arm
so what can you say about the arm that
spot has about the challenges of this
design
and the manufacture of it we think the
future of mobile robots is mobile
manipulation that's where
you know in the past 10 years
it was getting Mobility to work getting
the legged look emotional work if you
ask what's the hard problem in the next
10 years
it's getting a mobile robot to do useful
manipulation for you
and so we wanted spot to have an arm to
experiment with those problems
um and the arm is
um
almost as complex as the robot itself
you know and uh it's a it's an
attachable payload
um it has you know several Motors and
actuators and sensors it has a camera in
the end of its hand so you know you can
sort of see something
the and the robot will control the
motion of its hand to go pick it up
autonomously so in the same way the
robot walks and balances managing its
own foot placement to stay balanced we
want manipulation to be mostly
autonomous where the robot you indicate
okay go grab that bottle and then the
robot will just go do it using the
camera in its hand and then sort of
closing in on that um the grasp
but it's it's a whole nother complex
robot on top of a complex legged robot
and so and of course we made it the hand
look a little like a head you know
because again we want it to be sort of
identifiable in the last year a lot of
our sales have been people who already
have a robot now buying an arm to add to
that robot oh interesting and so the the
armor is for sale oh yeah oh yeah it's
an option what's the what's the
interface like to work with the arm like
is it pretty so are they designed
primarily I guess just ask that question
in general about robots from Boston
Dynamics is it designed to be
easily and efficiently operated remotely
by a human being or is there also the
capability to push towards autonomy we
want both
uh in the next version of the software
that we release uh which will be version
3.3 we're going to offer the ability of
if you have a autonomous mission for the
robot we're going to include the option
that it can go through a door which
means it's going to have to have an arm
and it's gonna have to use that arm to
open the door
and so that'll be an autonomous
manipulation task that just you can
program easily uh with the robot
strictly through you know we have a
tablet interface
and so on the tablet you know you sort
of see the The View that spot sees you
say there's the door handle you know the
hinges are on the left and it opens in
the rest is up to you take care oh so it
just takes care of everything yeah so we
we want in for a task like opening doors
you can automate most of that and we've
automated a few other tasks we had a
customer
who had a high-powered breaker switch
essentially it's an electric utility
Ontario power generation
and they have to when they're going to
disconnect you know their power supply
right that could be a gas generator
could be a nuclear power plant you know
from the grid you have to disconnect
this breaker switch as you can imagine
there's you know hundreds or thousands
of amps and volts involved in this
breaker switch
and it's a dangerous event because
occasionally you'll get what's called an
arc flash as you just do this disconnect
the power the Sparks jump across and
people die doing this
and so uh Ontario power generation used
our spot and and the arm through the
interface to to operate this this
disconnect
um that's right in an interactive way
and they showed it to us
and we were so excited about it and said
you know I bet we can automate that task
and so we we got some examples of that
breaker switch and I believe in the next
generation of the software now we're
going to deliver back to Ontario power
generation they're going to be able to
just point the robot
at that breaker so we have to indicate
that's the switch there's sort of two
actions you have to do you have to flip
up this little cover press a button then
get a ratchet stick it in to a socket
and literally unscrew this giant breaker
switch so there's a bunch of different
tasks and we basically automated them so
that the human says okay there's the
switch go do that part
that right there is the socket where
you're going to put your tool and you're
going to open it up and so you can
remotely sort of indicate this on the a
tablet and then the robot just does
everything in between and it does
everything all the coordinated movement
of all the different actuators that
include the body and it maintains its
balance it it walks itself you know into
position so it's within reach and the
arm is in a position where it can do the
whole task so it manages uh the whole
body so how does one become a big enough
customer to request features because I
personally want a robot that gets me
beer
I mean that has to be like one of the
most requests I suppose in the
industrial setting that's uh a
non-alcoholic beverage
um of picking up objects and bringing
the objects to you we love working with
customers who have challenging problems
like this and and this one in particular
because we felt like
what they were doing a it was a safety
feature B we saw that the robot could do
it because they they tele operated it
the first time probably took him an hour
to do it the first time right but the
robot was clearly capable and we thought
oh this is a great problem for us to
work on to figure out how to automate a
manipulation task and so we took it on
not not because we were going to make a
bunch of money from it and selling the
robot back to them but because it
motivated us to go solve what we saw as
the next logical step
but many of our customers in fact uh we
we try to our bigger customers who
typically ones who are going to run a
utility or a factory or something like
that
we take that kind of direction from them
and if they're especially if they're
going to buy 10 or 20 or 30 robots and
they say I really needed to do this well
that's exactly the right kind of problem
that we want to be working on and and so
note to self buy 10 spots
and aggressively pushed for beer
manipulation
I think it's fair to say it's
notoriously difficult to make a lot of
money as a robotics company
how can you make money as a robotics
company can you speak to that it seems
that a lot of Robotics companies fail
um it's difficult to build robots it's
difficult to build robots at a low
enough cost where customers even the
industrial setting want to purchase them
and it's difficult to build robots that
are useful sufficiently useful so what
can you speak to and Boston Dynamics has
been
uh successful for many years of finding
a way to make money well in the early
days of course you know the money we
made was from doing contract r d work
and we made money
but you know we weren't growing and we
weren't selling a product
and then we went through several owners
who
you know had a vision of not only
developing advanced technology but
eventually developing products and so
both you know Google and SoftBank and
now Hyundai
you know had that vision and were
willing to you know provide that in
investment
um now our discipline is that we need to
go find applications that are broad
enough that you could imagine selling
thousands of robots because it doesn't
work if you don't sell thousands or tens
of thousands of robots if you only sell
hundreds
you will commercially fail and that's
where most of the small robot companies
have died
um
and and that's a challenge because
you know a you need to field the robots
they need to start to become reli
reliable and as we as we've said that
takes time and investment to get there
and so it really does take Visionary
investment to get there but we we
believe that we are going to make money
in this uh industrial monitoring space
because
you know if uh if a chip Fab if the line
goes down because a vacuum pump failed
someplace that can be in a very
expensive process it can be a million
dollars a day in Lost production maybe
you have to throw away some of the
product along the way
and so the robot if you can prevent that
by inspecting the factory every single
day maybe every hour if you have to
There's real return on investment there
but there needs to be a critical mass of
this task and and we're focusing on a
few
that we believe are
ubiquitous in the industrial production
environment and that's using a thermal
camera to keep things from overheating
using an acoustic imager to find
compressed air leaks using visual
cameras to read gauges
measuring vibration these are standard
things that you do to prevent unintended
shutdown of a factory
and this this takes place in a beer
factory we're working with a B inbev it
takes place in chip Fabs you know we're
working with global foundries uh it
takes place in electric utilities and
nuclear power plants and so the same
robot
can be applied in all of these
industries
and and as I said we have about actually
it's 1100 spots out now to really get uh
you know profitability we need to be at
a thousand a year maybe maybe 1500 a
year you know for that sort of part of
the business so it still needs to grow
um but but we're on a good path so I
think that's totally achievable so the
application should require the crossing
that thousand robot barrier it really
should yeah I want to mention you know
our second robot uh stretch yeah tell me
about stretch what's stretch who stretch
stretch started differently than spot
you know spot we built because we had
Decades of experience building
quadrupeds we just we had it in our
blood we had to build a quadruped
product but we had to go figure out what
the application was and we actually
discovered this this Factory Patrol
application uh basically preventative
maintenance by seeing what our customers
did with it
stretch is very different we started
knowing that there was warehouses all
over the world there's shipping
containers moving all around the world
full of boxes that are mostly being
moved by hand
by some estimates we think there's a
trillion boxes cardboard boxes shipped
around the world each year and a lot of
it's done manually
it became clear early on
that there was an opportunity for a
mobile robot in here to move boxes
around
and the commercial experience has been
very different between stretch and with
spot
as soon as we started talking to
people or potential customers about what
stretch was going to be used for they
immediately started saying oh I'll buy
I'll buy that Roma you know in fact I'm
going to put in an order for for 20
right now we just started shipping the
robot in January
after you know several years of
development of this year this year so
our first deliveries of stretch to
customers were DHL and Maersk in January
we're delivering a gap right now and we
have about seven or eight other
customers all who've already agreed in
advance to buy between 10 and 20 robots
and so we've already got commitments for
you know a couple hundred of these
robots
this one's gonna go right it's so
obvious that there's a need and we're
not just going to unload trucks we're
going to do any box moving task in the
warehouse and so it too will be a
multi-purpose robot and we'll eventually
have it doing palletizing or
de-palletizing or loading trucks or
unloading trucks
there's definitely thousands of robots
there's probably tens of thousands of
robots of this in in the future so it's
going to be profitable can you describe
what stretch looks like it looks like a
big strong uh robot arm on a mobile base
the base is about the size of a pallet
and we want it to be the size of a
palette because that's what lives in
warehouses right pallets of goods
sitting everywhere so we needed to be
able to fit in that space it's not a
legged mobile not a legged robot so it
was our first
it was actually
um
a bit of a
uh commitment from us a challenge for us
to build a non-balancing robot
to do the much easier problem and to put
to do away well because it wasn't you
know it wasn't going to have this
balance problem and in fact the very
first version of the logistics robot we
build was a balancing robot and that's
called handle and there's that thing was
epic oh it's a beautiful machine it's an
incredible machine so it was uh
I mean it looks epic it looks like a out
of a uh I mean out of the sci-fi movie
of some sorts I mean just can you
actually just Linger on the like the
design of that thing because that's
another leap into something you probably
haven't done it's a different kind of
balancing yeah so let me I I'd love I
love talking about the history of how a
handle came about because it connects
all of our robots actually
so
um I'm going to start with Atlas when we
when we had Atlas getting fairly far
along we wanted to understand I was
telling you earlier the challenge of the
human form is you have this Mass up high
and balancing that inertia that mass up
high is its own unique Challenge and so
we started trying to get atlas to
balance standing on one foot like on a
balance beam using its arms like this
and yeah you can do this I'm sure I can
do this right like if you're walking a
tightrope
how do you do that balance
so that's sort of you know controlling
the inertia controlling the momentum of
the robot
we were starting to figure that out on
Atlas
and so our first concept of handle which
was a robot that was going to be on two
wheels so it had to balance
but it was going to have a big long arm
so it could reach a box at the top of a
truck
and it was gonna it needed yet another
counterbalance a big tail to help it
balance while it was using its arm
so the reason why this robot sort of
looks epic it some people said it looked
like an ostrich or maybe an ostrich
moving around
was the wheels the Le it has legs so it
can extend its legs
so it's wheels on legs we always wanted
to build wheels on legs it had a tail
and it had this arm and they're all
moving simultaneously and in
coordination to maintain balance because
we had figured out the mathematics of
doing this momentum control how to
maintain that balance and so part of the
reason why we built this two-legged
robot was we had figured this thing out
we wanted to see it in this kind of
machine and we thought maybe this kind
of machine would be good in a warehouse
and so we built it and it's a beautiful
machine it moves in a graceful way like
nothing else we've built but it wasn't
the right machine for a logistics
application we decided it was too slow
and couldn't pick boxes fast enough
basically and it was doing beautifully
with Elegance but it just wasn't
efficient enough uh so we let it go yeah
but I think we'll come back to that
machine eventually the fact that it's
possible the fact that he showed that
you could do so many things at the same
time in coordination that's so
beautifully there's something there yeah
that was a demonstration of what is
possible
basically we made a hard decision and
this was really kind of a hard-nosed
business decision it was it was it
indicated us
not doing it just for the beauty of the
mathematics or the Curiosity but no we
actually need to build a business that
that could make money in the long run
and so we ended up building stretch
which has a big heavy base with a giant
battery in the base of it that allows it
to run for two two shifts 16 hours worth
of operation
and that big battery is sort of helps it
stay balanced right so you can move a 50
pound box around with its arm and not
tip over um
it's omnidirectional it can move in any
direction so it has a nice suspension
built into it so it can deal with
you know gaps or things on the floor and
roll over it but it's a that it's not a
balancing robot it's a mobile robot arm
that can work to carry it or pick or
place a box up to 50 pounds anywhere in
the warehouse
from take a box from point A to point B
anywhere yeah palletize de-palletize
we're starting with unloading trucks
because there's so many trucks and
containers that where goods are shipped
and it's a brutal job you know in the
summer it can be 120 degrees inside that
container people don't want to do that
job
um and it's back breaking labor right
again these can be up to 50 pound boxes
um and so
we feel like this is a productivity
enhancer and for the people who used to
do that job unloading trucks
they're actually operating the robot now
and so by building robots that are easy
to control
and it doesn't take an advanced degree
to manage
you can become a robot operator and so
as we we've introduced these robots to
both DHL and mariskin Gap the warehouse
workers who were doing that that manual
labor are now the robot operators and so
we see this as ultimately a benefit to
them as well
can you say how much stretch cost
um not yet uh but I will say that uh we
when we engage with our customers
they'll be able to see a return on
investment in typically two years okay
so that's something you're constantly
thinking about how yeah and I suppose
you have to do the same kind of thinking
with spot so it seems like we've
stretched the application is
like directly obvious yeah to slam dunk
yeah and so you can you have a little
more flexibility well I think we know
the target we know what we're going
after yeah and with spot it took us a
while to figure out what we were going
after well let me return to that
question about uh
maybe the conversation you were having
a while ago with Larry Page maybe
looking to the longer future
of uh social robotics of using spot to
connect with human beings perhaps in the
home do you see a future there if we
were to sort of
hypothesize or dream about a future
where a spot like robots are in the home
as pets a social robot we definitely
think about it and and we would like to
get there
uh we think the pathway to getting there
is you know likely through these
industrial applications
and then Mass manufacturing you know
let's figure out what how to melt how to
build the robots how to make the
software so they can really do a broad
set of skills that's going to take
real investment to get there performance
first right the principle of the company
has always been really make the robots
do useful stuff
and so you know the the
social robot companies that tried to
start Someplace Else by just making a
cute interaction mostly they haven't
survived
and so we think the utility
really needs to come first and that
means you have to Heart solve some of
these hard problems and so to get there
we're going to go through the design and
software development in industrial and
then that's eventually going to let you
reach a scale that could then be
addressed to a commercial a consumer
level Market
and so yeah maybe we'll be able to build
a smaller spot with an arm that could
really go get your beer for you
but there's things we need to figure out
still how to safely really safely if
you're going to be interacting with
children you better be safe and right
now we we count on a little bit of
standoff distance between the robot and
people so that you don't pinch a finger
you know in the robot
so you've got a lot of things you need
to go solve before you jump to that
consumer level product well there's a
kind of trade-off in safety because it
feels like in the home
you can fall
like you're you don't have to be as good
at like you're allowed to fail in
different ways in more ways as long as
it's safe for the humans so it just
feels like an easier problem to solve
because it feels like in the factory
you're not allowed to fail
that may be true
um but I also think the variety of
things a consumer level robot would be
expected to do will also be quite broad
yeah and they're going to want to get
the beer and know the difference between
the beer and a Coca-Cola or my snack
and or you know they're all going to
want to clean up the dishes
uh you know from the table without
breaking them
those are pretty complex tasks and so
there's there's still work to be done
there so to push back on that here's
what application I think they'll be very
interesting I think the application of
being a pet a friend so like no tasks
foreign
just be cute because I not cute not cute
like that dog is more a dog is more than
just cute a dog is a friend is a
companion there's something about just
having interacted with them and maybe
because I'm hanging out alone with robot
dogs a little too much but like there's
a
there's a connection there and it feels
like that connection is not
should not be disregarded No it should
not be disregarded
robots that can somehow communicate
through their physical gestures are
you're going to be more attached to in
the long run do you remember IBO the
Sony IBO yeah they sold over a hundred
thousand of those maybe 150 000.
you know what probably wasn't considered
a
successful product for them
they suspended that eventually and then
they brought it back so he brought it
back
and people definitely you know treated
this as a as a pet as a as a companion
um and I think that will come around
again
um will you get away without having any
other utility
maybe in a world where we can really
talk to our simple little pet because
you know chat GPT or some other
generative AI has made it possible for
you to really talk and what seems like a
meaningful way maybe that'll open the
social robot
up again
um
that's probably not a path we're going
to go down because again we're so
focused on performance and utility
we can add those other things also but
we really want to start from that
Foundation of utility I think yeah but I
I also want to predict that you're wrong
on that so which is that the very path
you're taking which is creating a great
robot platform will very easily take a
leap to adding uh
capability maybe gpt5 and there's just
so many open source Alternatives you
could just plop that on top of spot and
because you have this robust platform
and you're figuring out how to mass
manufacture it and how to drive the cost
down and how to make it you know
reliable all those kinds of things it'll
be a natural transition to where just
adding tragic Beauty all right I do
think that
being able to verbally Converse or even
Converse through through gestures you
know part of part of these learning
models is that you know you can now Look
at video and image imagery and Associate
you know intent with that those will all
help in the communication between robots
and people for sure and that's going to
happen obviously more quickly than any
of us were expecting I mean what else do
you want from life
should be here
and then just talk about this the
state of the world
I mean there's a deep loneliness within
all of us and I think
uh a beer and a good chat solves so much
of it or take takes us a long way to
solving uh it'll be interesting to see
um you know when
when a generative AI can give you that
warm feeling that you connected
you know and that oh yeah you remember
me you're my friend you know we have a
history
you know that history matters right
memory of joint like memory of yeah
having witnessed I mean that's what
friendship that's what connection that's
what love is in in many cases some of
the deepest friendships you have is
having gone through a difficult time
together and having a shared memory of
an amazing time or a difficult time
and kind of
that memory creating this like
Foundation based on which you can then
experience the world together the silly
the mundane stuff of day-to-day is
somehow built on a foundation of having
gone through some in the past and
the the current systems are not
personalized in that way but I think
that's a technical problem not uh some
kind of fundamental limitation so I'll
combine that with an embodied robot like
spot which already has magic in its
movement I think uh it's a very
interesting possibility of what where
that takes us but of course you have to
build that on top of a company that's
making money
with real application with real
customers and with robots that are safe
and at work and reliable and uh in
manufactured scale
and I think we're in a unique position
in that uh because of our investors
primarily Hyundai but also SoftBank
still owns 20 of us
um they don't they're not totally
fixated on
driving us to profitability as soon as
possible that's not the goal the goal
really is a longer term vision of
creating
you know what does mobility mean in the
future what are how is this mobile robot
technology going to influence
um us can we and can we shape that and
they want both and so I we are as a
company are trying to strike that
balance between let's build a business
that makes money
I've been describing that to my own team
as
uh self-destination if I want to if I
want to drive my own ship we need to
have a business that's profitable in the
end otherwise somebody else is going to
drive the ship for us
so that's really important
but we're going to retain
the aspiration that we're going to build
the next generation of Technology at the
same time and the real trick will be if
we can do both
uh speaking of ships
uh let me ask you about a competitor
and somebody's become a friend
so Elon Musk Contessa have announced
have been in the early days of building
a humanoid robot how does that change
the landscape of
of your work so so there's sort of from
the outside perspective it seems like
well from a fan as a fan of Robotics it
just seems exciting all right very
exciting right when when Elon speaks
people listen
and so uh it suddenly brought a bright
light onto the work that we've been
doing you know for over a decade
and
um and I think that's only going to help
and in fact what we've seen is that uh
in addition to Tesla uh we're seeing a
proliferation of uh robotic companies
arise including humanoid yes oh well
yeah so and um interestingly many of
them uh as they're you know raising
money for example will claim whether or
not they have a former Boston Dynamics
employee on their staff as a criteria
yeah that's true that's uh I I I would
do that as a company yeah for sure yeah
so it shows you're legit yeah so you
know what it's bring it has brung a
tremendous validation to what we're
doing
and excitement uh competitive juices are
flowing you know the whole thing so uh
it's all good
Eli is also
kind of
stated
that uh
you know maybe he implied that the
problem is solvable in your term which
is a low-cost humanoid robot that's able
to do that's a relatively General use
case robot
so um I think Elon is known for sort of
setting these kinds of incredible
ambitious goals
um maybe missing deadlines but actually
pushing not just the particular team he
leads but the entire world
to like accomplishing those do you see
you see Boston Dynamics in the near
future being pushed in that kind of way
like this excitement of competition kind
of
um
pushing Atlas maybe to uh do more cool
stuff trying to drive the cost of Atlas
down perhaps or um I mean I guess I want
to I want to ask if there's
some kind of exciting
uh energy in Boston Dynamics uh due to
this a little bit of competition oh yeah
definitely
um
when we released our most recent video
of Atlas you know I think you'd seen it
the scaffolding and throwing the box of
Tools around and then doing the flip at
the end yeah we were trying to show the
world that not only can we do this
parkour Mobility thing but we can pick
up and move heavy things
because uh if you're going to work in a
manufacturing environment that's what
you got to be able to do and for the
reasons I explained to you earlier it's
not trivial to do so you know changing
the center of mass uh uh you know by
picking up a 50 pound
black you know for a robot that weighs
150 pounds
that's a lot to accommodate so we're
trying to show that we can do that and
um so it's totally been energizing you
know we see
the next phase of Atlas being more
dexterous hands that can manipulate and
grab more things that we're going to
start by moving big things around that
are heavy and that affect balance and
why is that well really tiny dexterous
things probably are going to be hard for
a while yet and you know maybe you could
go build a special purpose
robot arm you know for for stuffing you
know chips into Electronics boards but
we don't really want to do really fine
work like that I think more coursework
where you're using two hands to pick up
and balance an unwieldy thing maybe in a
manufacturing environment maybe in a
construction environment those are the
things that we think robots are going to
be able to do with the level of
dexterity that they're going to have in
the next few years and that's the that's
where we're headed and and I think and
you know Elon has seen the same thing
right he's talking about using the
robots in a manufacturing environment we
think there's something very interesting
there about having this two-armed robot
because when you have two arms you can
transfer a thing from one hand to the
other you can turn it around you know
you can you can reorient it in a way
that you can't do it if you just have
one hand on it and so there's a lot that
extra arm brings to the table so I think
in terms of mission
you you mentioned Boston and Amex really
wants to see what are the what's the
limits of what's possible and so the
cost comes second
or it's a component but first figure out
what are the limitations I think with
Elon he's really dragging the cost down
is there some inspiration some lessons
you see there
um of the challenge of driving the cost
down especially with Atlas with a
humanoid robot well I think the thing
that he's certainly been learning by
building car factories is what that
looks like in scaling
um by scaling you can get efficiencies
that drive costs down very well and uh
and the smart thing that you know they
have in their favor is that you know
they know how to manufacture they know
how to build electric motors they know
how to build uh you know computers and
vision systems so there's a lot of
overlap between modern
Automotive companies
and robots
but hey
we have a modern robotic I mean that
automotive company behind us as well
so uh bring it on who's doing pretty
well right the electric vehicles from
Hyundai are doing pretty well
I love it uh so how much so we've talked
about some of the low level controls
some of the incredible stuff that's
going on and basic perception
but how much do you see in currently in
the future of Boston Dynamics sort of
more higher level machine learning
applications do you see customers adding
on those capabilities or do you see
Boston Dynamics doing that in-house
some kinds of things we really believe
ought are probably going to be
more broadly available maybe even
commoditized
you know using a machine learning like a
vision algorithm so a robot can
recognize something in the environment
that ought to be something you can just
download like I'm going to a new
environment I have a new kind of door
handle or piece of equipment I want to
inspect you ought to be able to just
download that and I think people besides
Boston Dynamics will provide that and
we've actually built an API that lets
people add these uh Vision algorithms to
spot
and we're currently working with some
Partners who are providing that
um levitas is an example of a small
provider who's giving us software for
reading gauges
um and actually another partner in
Europe reply is doing the same thing
so we see that we see It ultimately uh
an ecosystem of providers doing stuff
like that I and I I think ultimately
you might even be able to do the same
thing with behaviors so this technology
will also be brought to bear on
controlling the robot the the Motions of
the robot and you know we're using
learning reinforcement learning to
develop
algorithms for both Locomotion and
manipulation
and ultimately this is going to mean you
can you can add new behaviors to a robot
you know quickly
and uh that could potentially be done
outside of Boston Dynamics right now
that's all internal to us I think I
think you need to understand
at a deep level you know
um the robot control to do that but
eventually that could be outside but
it's certainly a place where these these
approaches are going to be brought to
bear in robotics so reinforcement
learning is part of the process today so
you do use reinforcement learning yes
foreign
so there's uh increasing levels of
learning with these robots yes
and that's for both for uh for
Locomotion for manipulation and
for perception yes
well what do you think in general about
the all the exciting advancements of uh
Transformer uh neural networks
most
beautifully uh Illustrated through the
large language models like gpt4
like everybody else we're all you know
I'm I'm surprised at uh how much uh how
far they've come
um I'm a little bit nervous about the
there's anxiety around them obviously
for I think good reasons right
disinformation is a a curse that's a an
unintended consequence of social media
that could be
exacerbated with these tools so if you
use them to deploy this information it
could be a real risk
um but I also think that the risks
associated with these kinds of models
don't have a whole lot to do with the
way we're going to use them in our
robots if I'm using a robot
I'm building a robot to do you know a
manual task of some sort
um I can judge very easily is it doing
the task I asked it to is it doing it
correctly there's sort of a a built-in
mechanism for judging is that is it
doing the right thing did it
successfully do the task yeah physical
reality is a good verifier it's a good
verifier that's exactly it whereas if
you're asking for yeah I don't know
you're trying to ask a theoretical
question in chat GPT
it could be true or it may not be true
and it's hard to have that verifier what
what is that truth that you're comparing
against whereas in physical reality you
know the truth
and this is an important difference and
um so I'm not
I think there is reason to be a little
bit concerned about
um you know how these tools large
language models could be used but I'm
not very worried about how they're going
to be used
well how learning algorithms in general
are going to be used on robotics it's
it's really a different application
that has different ways of verifying
what's going on well the nice thing
about language models is that I
ultimately see
I'm really excited about the possibility
of having conversations with spot yeah
uh there's no I would say negative
consequences to that but just increasing
the bandwidth in the variety of ways you
can communicate with this uh particular
robot so you could communicate visually
you can communicate through some
interface and to be able to communicate
verbally again with the beer and so on
um I think that's really exciting to
make that much much easier we have this
partner levitas that's adding the vision
algorithms for daydreading for us they
just just this week I saw a demo where
they hooked up you know a language tool
to spot and they're talking a spot to
give example yeah can you tell me about
the Boston Dynamics AI Institute what is
it and what is its mission
so it's a separate organization uh the
Boston Amex artificial intelligence
Institute
and it's led by Mark Rayburn the founder
of Boston Dynamics and the former CEO
and my old advisor at MIT Mark has
always loved the research the pure
research without the confinement or
demands of commercialization
and uh he wanted to continue to you know
pursue that unadulterated research
and uh uh so uh suggested uh to Hyundai
that that he set up this institute and
they agree that it's worth additional
investment to kind of continue push
pushing this Forefront
and we expect to be working together
where you know Boston Dynamics is again
both commercialize and do research but
the sort of time Horizon of the research
we're going to do is you know in the
next let's say five years you know what
can we do in the next five years let's
work on those problems
and I think the goal of the AI Institute
is to work even further out
um certainly you know the analogy of of
legged Locomotion again when we started
that that was a multi-decade problem and
and so I think Mark wants to have the
freedom
uh to pursue really hard Over the
Horizon problems and that's that'll be
the goal of the Institute
so we mentioned uh some of the dangers
of uh some of the concerns about large
language models that said uh you know
there's been a long-running fear of
these embodied
robots uh why do you think people are
afraid of uh Lincoln robots yeah I
wanted to show you this this
so this this is a Wall Street Journal
and this is all about chat GPT right but
look at the picture yeah it's a humanoid
robot
that's saying I will say that looks
scary and it says I'm going to replace
you yeah and so the humanoid robot is
sort of is the embodiment of this chat
GPT tool that there's reason to be a
little bit nervous about how it gets
deployed yeah so I'm nervous about that
connection
um
it's unfortunate that they chose to use
a robot as that embodiment for as you
and I just said there's big differences
in in this
but uh people are afraid because we've
been
taught to be afraid for over a hundred
years so you know the word robot was
developed by a playwright named Carol
chapek in 1921 to check a playwright for
Awesome's Universal robots and in that
first depiction of a robot the robots
took over
the end of the story
and you know people love to be afraid
and so we've been entertained by these
stories for a hundred years
but I
and I think that's as much why people
are afraid as anything else as we've
been sort of taught that this is the
logical progression through fiction
um
I think it's fiction
I think uh what people more and more
will realize just like you said
that the threat like say you have a
super intelligent AI embodied in a robot
that's much less threatening because
it's visible it's verifiable it's right
there in physical reality and we humans
know how to deal with physical reality I
think it's much scarier when you have
arbitrary scaling of
intelligent AI systems in the digital
space
that they could uh pretend to be human
so robot spot is not going to be pretend
it could pretend it's human all at once
you can tell you you could put Chad gbt
on top of it but you're gonna know it's
not human because you have a contact
with physical reality and you're going
to know whether or not it's doing what
you asked it to do yeah like it's not
gonna like if it like I mean I'm sure
you can start just like a dog lies to
you it's like I didn't I wasn't part of
tearing up that couch
try to lie that like you know it
wasn't me that spilled that thing but
it's you're going to kind of figure it
out eventually it's but if it happens
multiple times you know
uh but I think that Humanity has figured
out how to make machines safe yeah and
there's you know there's regulatory
environments and certification uh
protocols that we've developed in order
to figure out how to make machines safe
we don't know we and don't have that
experience with software
that can be propagated worldwide in an
instant
and so I think we needed to develop
those protocols and those tools and so
uh
that's work to be done but I don't think
the fear of that and that work should
necessarily impede our ability to now
get robots out because again I think I
think we can judge when a robot's being
safe
so and again just like in that image
there's a fear that robots will take our
jobs I just um I took a ride I was in
San Francisco I know way more Vehicles
than autonomous vehicle and uh I've done
it several times they're they're doing
credible work over there uh but
uh people flicked it off the car so I
mean that's a long story of what the
psychology of that is it could be maybe
big Tech or what I I don't know exactly
what they're flicking off yeah but there
is an element of like these robots are
taking our jobs or or
irreversibly transforming Society such
that it will have economic impact and
the little guy will be uh would lose a
lot would lose their well-being is there
something to be said about
um
the fear that robots will take our jobs
you know at every
um significant technological
transformation uh there's been fear of
you know an automation anxiety yes that
uh it's it's going to have a broader
impact than than we expected
and there there will be uh
you know jobs will change
um sometime in the future we're going to
look back at people who manually
unloaded these boxes from trailers and
we're going to say why did we ever do
that manually but there's a lot of
people who are doing that job today
that it could be impacted
um but I think the reality is as I said
before we're going to build a
Technologies those very same people can
operate it and so I think there's a
pathway to upskilling and operating just
like look we used to farm with hand
tools and now we farm with machines and
nobody has really regretted that
transformation
and I think the same can be said for a
lot of manual labor that we're doing
today
and on top of that you know look we're
we're entering a new world where where
demographics are going to have a strong
impact on economic growth in the you
know the advanced uh the first world is
losing population quickly
um in Europe
they're worried about hiring enough
people just to keep the logistics supply
chain going
and you know part of this is the
response to covid and everybody's sort
of thinking back
what they really want to do with their
life but these jobs are getting harder
and harder to fill and I just I'm
hearing that over and over again
so I think frankly this is the right
technology at the right time
um where we're gonna need some of this
work to be done and we're going to want
tools to enhance that productivity and
the scary impact I think again uh gbt
comes to the rescue in terms of being
much more terrifying
um
the scary scary impact of basically so I
I'm a I guess a software person inside a
program a lot and the fact that people
like me could be easily replaced
uh by gbt
that's going to have a
well and a lot you know anyone who deals
with texts and writing a draft proposal
might be easily done with a chat GPT now
Consultants
journalists yeah
um everybody is sweating but on the
other hand you also want it to be right
and they don't know how to make it right
yet it but it might make a good starting
point for you to iterate boy do I have
to talk to you about modern journalism
that's another conversation altogether
but yes uh more right than the average
uh
um the the mean journalist yes
um
you spearheaded the NT weaponization
letter
uh Boston Dynamics has can you
describe uh what that letter States and
the general topic of the use of robots
in war
we
authored a letter and then got several
leading robotics companies around the
world including you know unitary and
China and
um agility here in the United States and
um animal and in Europe
and you know some others to co-sign a
letter that said we won't put weapons on
our robots
and part of the motivation there is you
know as these robots start to become
commercially available
you can see videos online of people
who've gotten a robot and strapped a gun
on it and shown that they can you know
operate the gun remotely while driving
the robot around
and so having a robot that has this
level of Mobility
and that can easily be configured in a
way that could harm somebody from a
remote operators
justifiably a scary thing
and so we felt like it was important to
draw a bright line there and say we're
not going to allow this
for
um
you know reasons that we think
ultimately it's better for the whole
industry if if it grows in a way where
uh the robots are ultimately going to
help us all and make our lives more
fulfilled and productive but by goodness
you're going to have to trust the
technology to let it in and if
and if you think the robot is going to
harm you that's gonna that's gonna hurt
and impede the growth of that industry
so we thought it was important to to
draw a bright line
and uh and then publicize that and and
our plan is to you know begin to engage
with
lawmakers and Regulators let's figure
out what the rules are going to be
around the use of this technology
um and use our position as leaders in
this industry and Technology
to help force that issue
and so we are in fact I have a policy
you know director at my company whose
job it is to engage with the public to
enjoy engage with interested parties and
including Regulators to sort of begin
these discussions
he has a really important topic and it's
an important topic for people that worry
about the impact of robots on our
society with autonomous weapon systems
so I'm glad you're sort of leading the
way in this uh
you are the CEO of Boston Dynamics uh
what's it take to be SEO of a robotics
company she started as a humble engineer
uh PhD
um just looking at your journey
what does it take to go from being
from building the thing
to Leading a company what are some of
the big challenges for you
uh courage I would I would put front and
center for multiple reasons I talked
earlier about the courage to tackle hard
problems
so I think there's courage required not
just of me but of of all of the people
who work at Boston Dynamics
um I also think we have a lot of really
smart people we have people who are way
smarter than I am
and I it takes a kind of courage to be
willing to lead them
and to trust that
you have something to offer to somebody
who probably is maybe a better engineer
than I am
um
adaptability you know part of the it's
been a great career for me I never would
have guessed I'd stayed in one place for
30 years
um and the job has always changed
um I didn't I didn't really aspire to be
CEO from the very beginning but it was
the natural progression of things there
was always a there always needed to be
some level of management that was needed
and so
you know when I saw
something that needed to be done that
wasn't being done I just stepped in to
go do it and oftentimes because we were
full of such uh strong Engineers
oftentimes that was in the management
direction or it was in the business
development direction or or
organizational hiring geez I was not I
was the main person hiring at Boston
Dynamics for probably 20 years so I was
the head of HR basically
so I you know just willingness to sort
of tackle any piece of the business that
that needs it and then and be willing to
shift is there something you could say
to what it takes to hire a great team
what uh
what's a good interview process how do
you know uh the guy or Gallery are going
to make a great member of uh of a
engineering team that's doing some of
the hardest work in the world
you know we developed an interview
process that I was quite fond of it's a
little bit of a hard interview process
because the best interviews you ask
somebody about what they're interested
in and what they're good at
and if if they can describe to you
something that they worked on and you
saw they really did the work they solved
the problems
and you saw their passion for it
um and you could ask but but what makes
that hard is you have to ask a probing
question about it you have to be smart
enough about what they're telling you
their expert at to ask a good question
and so it takes a pretty talented team
to do that
but if you can do that that's how you
tap into ah this person cares about
their work they really did the work
they're excited about it that's the kind
of person I want at my company
you know at Google they taught us about
their interview process
and it was a little bit different
um
you know
we we evolved the process at Boston
Dynamics where it didn't matter if you
were an engineer or you were an uh
administrative assistant or a financial
person or a technician
you gave us a presentation you came in
and you gave us a presentation you had
to stand up and talk in front of us
and I just thought that was great to tap
into those things I didn't subscribed to
you at Google they taught us and I think
I understand why you're right they're
hiring tens of thousands of people they
need a more standardized process so they
would sort of err on the other side
where they would ask you a standard
question I'm going to ask you a
programming question and I'm just going
to ask you to write code in front of me
that's a terrifying you know application
process yeah it does let you compare
candidates really well but it doesn't
necessarily let you tap in to who they
are yeah right because you're asking
them to answer your question instead of
you asking them about what they're
interested in
um but frankly that process is hard to
scale and even at Boston Dynamics
we're not doing that with everybody
anymore we're but we are still doing
that with you know the technical people
but we've because we too now need to
sort of increase our rate of hiring uh
not everybody's giving a presentation
anymore but you're still ultimately
trying to find that uh basic seed of
passion yeah into the world you know did
they really do it did they did they find
something interesting or curious you
know
um and do they care about it I think uh
somebody admires
um Jim Keller and he
he likes details
so one of the ways you could if you get
a person to talk about what they're
interested in how many details like how
much of the Whiteboard can you fill out
yeah well I think you figure out did
they really do the work if they know
some of the details yes and if they have
to wash over the details well then they
didn't do it especially with engineering
the work is in the details yeah
I have to go there briefly
just to get your kind of thoughts in the
long-term future of robotics
there's been discussions on the GPT side
on the large language model side of
whether there's Consciousness inside
these language models
and I think there's fear but I think
there's also excitement or at least the
wide world of opportunity and
possibility in embodied robots having
something like
let's start with emotion
love towards other human beings
and uh perhaps the display real or fake
of consciousness
is this something you think about in
terms of long long term future because
as you as we've talked about people do
anthropomorphize these robots uh it's
difficult not to project some level of I
use the word sentience some level of
sovereignty identity all the things we
think is human that's what
anthropomorphization is as we project
humanness onto mobile especially legged
robots
um is that something almost from a
science fiction perspective you think
about or do you try to avoid ever
you try to avoid the topic of
Consciousness altogether
I'm certainly not an expert in it and I
don't spend a lot of time thinking about
this right
um and I do think it's fairly remote for
the machines that that we're dealing
with
um
our robots you're right the people
Anthem warfies they they read into the
robot's intelligence and emotion that
isn't there because they see physical
gestures
that are similar to things they might
even see in people or animals
um I don't know much about how these
large language models really work I I
believe it's a kind of statistical
averaging of the most common responses
you know to a series of words right it's
it's sort of um
a very elaborate uh word completion
um and I'm dubious that that has
anything to do with consciousness
um and I I even wonder if that model of
sort of simulating Consciousness by by
stringing words together that are
statistically associated with one
another
um whether or not that kind of knowledge
if you want to call that knowledge
um would be the kind of knowledge that
allowed a sentient being to grow or
evolve it feels to me like there's
there's something about
truth or emotions
that's just a very different kind of
knowledge that is that is absolute like
a the interesting thing about truth is
it's absolute and it doesn't matter how
frequently it's represented in the world
wide web it
if you know it to be true it can only be
it may only be there once but by God
that's true
and I think emotions are a little bit
like that too you know something you
know and
and I just think that's a different kind
of knowledge than the way these large
language models uh derive sort of
simulated it does seem that intelligence
things that are true
um very well might be statistically well
represented on the on the internet
because the internet is made up of
humans
so I tend to suspect that large language
models are going to be able to simulate
Consciousness very effectively and I
actually believe that current gpt4 when
fine-tuned correctly would be able to do
just that and that's going to be a lot
of very complicated ethical questions
that have to be dealt with that have
nothing to do with robotics they have
and everything to do with there needs to
be some process of
labeling I think what is true
because because there is also
disinformation available on the web and
these models are going to consider that
kind of information as well
and again you can't average something
that's true and something that's untrue
and get something that's moderately true
it's either right or it's wrong and so
how how is that process and and this is
obviously something that
the purveyors of these Bard and chat gbt
that I'm sure this is what they're
working on well if you interact on some
controversial topics with these models
they're actually refreshingly nuanced
they present because there's there's
well you realize there's no one truth
you know uh what caused
the war in Ukraine right any
geopolitical conflict you can ask any
kind of question especially the ones
that are politically uh a a tense
divisive and so on GPT is very good at
presenting here's the like here's the
app it presents the different hypotheses
it presents calmly so the the amount of
evidence for each one it's very it's
really refreshing it makes you realize
that truth is nuanced and it does that
well and I think with consciousness
it would very uh accurately say Well it
sure as hell feels like I'm one of you
humans but where's my body I don't
understand like you're going to be
confused the cool thing about GPT
is it seems to be easily confused in the
way we are like you wake up in a new
room and you ask where am I it seems to
be able to do that extremely well it'll
tell you one thing like a fact about
when a war started and when you correct
it say well this isn't it's not
consistent it'll be confused it'd be
yeah you're right
it'll have that same element childlike
element with humility of trying to
figure out its way in the world and I
think
that's a really tricky area to uh to
sort of figure out with us humans of
what we want
um to allow AI systems to say to us
because then if there's elements of
sentience that are being on display you
can then start to manipulate human
emotion all that kind of stuff but I
think
that's that's something that's a really
serious and aggressive discussion that
needs to be had
on the software side
um I think again embodiment uh
Robotics are actually saving us from the
arbitrary scaling of software systems
versus uh creating more problems but
that said I I really believe in the that
connection between human and robot
there's magic there
and I think uh there's also I think a
lot of money to be made there and Boston
Dynamics is leading the world in
um the most elegant movement
done by robots
so I I can't wait thank you to uh what
maybe other people that built on top of
uh Boston Dynamics robots or boss or
Boston Dynamics by itself so you had uh
one wild career one place and one
set of problems but incredibly
successful can you give advice to Young
Folks today in high school maybe in
college looking out into this future
where
so much Robotics and AI seems to be
defining the trajectory of human
civilization can you give them advice on
how to have a career they can be proud
of
or how to have a life they can be proud
well I would say uh you know follow your
heart and your interest you know what
again this was an organizing principle I
think behind
the light Lab at MIT that that turned
into
a value at Boston Dynamics which was
follow your curiosity
love what you're doing
um you'll have a lot more fun and you'll
be a lot better at it as a result
um
I think it's hard to plan you know don't
get too hung up on planning too far
ahead find things that you like doing
and then see where it takes you you can
always change direction you will find
things that you know that wasn't a good
move I'm gonna back up and go do
something else
so when people are trying to plan a
career I always feel like yeah there's a
few happy mistakes that happen along the
way and just live with that it you know
but just
but make choices then so Avail
yourselves to these interesting
opportunities like when I happen to run
into mark down in the lab the basement
of the AI lab
but be willing to make it
a decision and then pivot if you see
something exciting to go at you know
because if you're out and about enough
you'll you'll find things like that that
get you excited so there was a feeling
when you first met Mark and saw the
robots that there's something
interesting oh boy I gotta go do this
there is no doubt
what do you think in the 100 years
what do you think Boston Dynamics is
doing what do you think is the role even
bigger what do you think is the role of
robots in society do you think we'll be
seeing
billions of robots
everywhere
do you think about that long-term vision
well I do think that um
I think the robots will be ubiquitous
and they will be out amongst us
um
and they'll be
certainly doing you know some of the
hard labor that we do today
I don't think people don't want to work
people want to work people need to work
to I think feel productive we we don't
want to offload all of the work to the
robots because I'm not sure if people
would know what to do with themselves
and I think just self-satisfaction and
feeling productive is such an ingrained
part of being human that we need to keep
doing this work so we're definitely
going to have to work in a complementary
fashion and I hope that the robots and
the computers don't end up being able to
do all the creative work right because
because that's the part that's you know
that's the rewarding the creative part
of solving a problem is the thing that
gives you
that serotonin Rush that you never
forget you know or that Adrenaline Rush
that you never forget and so you know
people need to be able to do that
creative work and and just feel
productive and sometimes that you can
feel productive over fairly simple work
it's just well done you know and then
you can see the result of
so I yeah you know there is a
I don't know there's a a cartoon was it
Wally where they had this big ship and
all the people were just
overweight lying on their best chairs
kind of sliding around on the deck of
the of the movie because they didn't do
anything anymore yeah well we definitely
don't want to be there you know we need
to work in some complimentary fashion
where we keep all of our faculties and
our physical health and we're doing some
labor right but in a complimentary
fashion somehow and I think a lot of
that has to do with the interaction the
collaboration with robots and with AI
systems I'm hoping there's a lot of
interesting possibilities I think that
could be really cool right if you can if
you can work in a comp internet
interaction and really be be helpful
robots you
you know you can ask a robot to do a job
you wouldn't ask a person to do and that
would be a real asset you wouldn't feel
guilty about it you know you'd say just
do it it's a machine I and I don't have
to have qualms about that you know the
ones that are machines I also hope to
see a future
and it is hope I do have optimism about
that future where some of the robots are
pets have an emotional connection to us
humans and uh because one of the
problems that humans have to solve is
this kind of a general loneliness um
the more love you have in your life the
more friends you have in your life I
think that makes a more enriching life
helps you grow and I don't fundamentally
see why some of those friends can't be
robots there's an interesting
long-running study maybe it's an Harvard
they just nice report article written
about it recently they've been studying
this group of a few thousand people now
for 70 or 80 years and the conclusion is
that
companionship and friendship are the
things that make for a better and
happier life
and
um
so I agree with you and I think that
could happen with a machine that is
probably you know simulating
intelligence I'm not convinced there
will ever be true intelligence in these
machines
sentience but they could simulate it and
they could collect your history and they
could you know I guess it remains to be
seen whether they can establish that
real deep you know when you sit with a
friend and they remember something about
you and bring that up and you feel that
connection it remains to be seen if a
machine's going to be able to do that
for you well I have to say it's inklings
of that already started happening for me
some of my best friends are robots
uh and I have you to thank for leading
the way in in the accessibility and the
ease of use of such robots and the
Elegance of their movement uh Robert
you're an incredible person Boston
Dynamics is an incredible company I've
just been a fan for many many years for
everything you stand for for everything
you do in the world if you're interested
in great engineering robotics go join
them build cool stuff I'll forever
celebrate the work you're doing and it's
just a big honor that he was sit with me
today and talk it means a lot so thank
you so much he's doing great work thank
you Lex I'm honored to be here and uh I
appreciate it was fun
thanks for listening to this
conversation with Robert later to
support this podcast please check out
our sponsors in the description and now
let me leave you some words from Alan
Turing in 1950 defining what is now
termed the Turing test
a computer would deserve to be called
intelligent if it could deceive a human
into believing that it was human
thank you for listening and hope to see
you next time