listen when it comes to romantic
relationships if it's not a hundred
percent in you
it ain't happening and I've never seen
a violation of that statement
where it's like it yeah it's mostly good
and they're this is like the
negotiations well already you're you're
it's doomed and that doesn't mean
someone has to be perfect the
relationship has to be perfect but it's
got to feel 100 inside like yes yes and
yes
the following is a conversation with my
dear friend Andrew huberman his fourth
time on this podcast it's my birthday so
this is a special birthday episode of
sorts Andrew flew down to Austin just to
wish me happy birthday and we decided to
do a podcast last second we literally
talked for hours beforehand in a long
time after late into the night he's one
of my favorite human beings brilliant
scientists incredible teacher and a
loyal friend I'm grateful for Andrew I'm
grateful for good friends for all the
support and love I've gotten over the
past few years
I'm truly grateful for this life for the
years the days the minutes the seconds
I've gotten to live on this beautiful
Earth of ours I really don't want to
leave just yet
I think I'd really like to stick around
I love you all
this is the last treatment podcast and
now dear friends here's Andrew
huberman
trying to uh
run a little bit more are you losing
weight I'm not trying to lose weight but
I always do the same Fitness routine
after like 30 years basically uh lift
three days a week run three days a week
um but one of the runs is the long run
one of them's medium one of them's a
Sprint type thing so
um what I've decided to do this year was
just extend the duration of the long run
and
um I like being a mobile I I never want
to be
um so heavy that I can't move like like
I want to be able to go out and run 10
miles if I have to so sometimes I do
um and I want to be able to Sprint if I
have to so sometimes I do and um lifting
in objects is feels good it feels good
to train like a lazy bear and just lift
heavy objects but I've also started
training with lighter weights and higher
repetitions and
um for three month cycles and it gives
your joints a rest and um yeah so
probably you know it I think it also is
interesting to see how training
differently changes your cognition
that's probably hormone related you know
hormones Downstream of training heavy
versus hormones Downstream of training a
little bit lighter
um I think my cognition is better when
I'm doing more cardio and when the
repetition ranges are a little bit
higher which is not to say that people
who lift heavy are dumb but there is a
because there's real value in lifting
heavy there's a lot of angry people
listening to this right now no no no but
lifting heavy and then taking three to
five minutes rest is Far and Away a
different
challenge than running hard for 90
minutes
that's a tough thing just like getting
in an ice bath people say oh well how is
that any different than working out
um well there are a lot of differences
but one of them is that it's very acute
stress within one second you're stressed
so I I think subjecting the body to a
bunch of different types of stressors in
space and time is really valuable so
yeah I've been playing with the
variables in a pretty systematic way
well I like long and slow
for like you said the impact it has on
my cognition yeah it it uh the
wordlessness of it
um the way it puts you in in a the way
it seems to
um clean out the Clutter yeah you know
um it can take away that hyper focus and
put you more in a relaxed
Focus for sure well for me it brings the
Clutter to the surface at first like all
these thoughts come in there and then
they dissipate you know I've been uh
because I got knee barred pretty hard
that's when somebody tries to break here
they try and break your knee yeah
because you tap so they yeah yeah yeah
so it's you know hyper extend they need
that direction the guy knee barred
pretty hard so um in ways I don't
understand it kind of hurts to run I
don't understand what's happening behind
there I need to investigate this
it basically this the hamstring Flex
like curling your leg hurts a little bit
okay and that results in this weird doll
but sometimes extremely sharp pain in
the back of the knee so I'm I'm working
I'm I'm working through this anyway but
walking doesn't hurt so I've been
playing around with walking recently
like for two hours and thinking because
I know a lot of like
smart people throughout history have
walked and thought you have to like you
know play with things that have worked
for others not just to exercise but to
like integrate this very light kind of
prolonged exercise into a productive
life so they do all their thinking while
they walk it's like a meditative type of
walking it's it's really interesting it
really works yeah the um the practice
I've been doing a lot more of lately as
I walk while reading a book in the yard
I'll just Pace back and forth or walk in
a circle audiobook are you talking no
hard copy where you just holding I
holding the book and I'm walking and I'm
reading yeah and I usually have a pen
and I'm underlining I have this whole
system like underlining Stars
exclamation points goes back to
University of what things I'll go back
to
um which things I export to notes and
that kind of thing
um but from the beginning when I opened
my lab at that time in San Diego before
I moved back to Stanford
um I would have meetings with my
students or postdocs by just walking in
the field behind the lab
um you know and I'd bring my Bulldog
Costello yeah Bulldog Mastiff at the
time and he was a slow Walker so these
were slow walks but I can think much
more clearly that way there's a Nobel
prize-winning uh professor at Columbia
University School of Medicine Richard
Axel who won the Nobel Prize co1 Nobel
Prize with Linda Buck for the discovery
of the molecular basis of olfaction and
um he walks in voice dictates his papers
and now with rev or these other maybe
there are better ones um than rev where
you can convert audio files into text
very quickly and then edit from there so
I I will often voice dictate
um first drafts and things like that and
um I totally agree on the long runs the
walks the integrating that with
cognitive work harder to do with Sprints
um and then the gym you know are you do
you weight train you just seem naturally
strong and like thicker jointed it's
true yeah it's true I when we did the
one very beginner because I'm a very
beginner of Jiu Jitsu class together
and um yeah as I mentioned then uh but
if people missed it uh Alexis freakishly
strong I think I was born genetically to
hug people oh like Costello yeah exactly
you guys have a certain similarity he
had wrists like you know it's like you
and Jocko and Costello have these like
wrists and and elbows that are super
thick you know and then when you look
around you see tremendous variation you
know some people have like the the
um wrist uh width of a whippet or Woody
Allen and then other people like you or
Jocko or you know there's this one uh
Jocko video or thing on GQ or something
Have you seen the comments on Jocko
these are the best
um the comments I love the comments on
YouTube because occasionally they're
funny
um the best is uh when shock was born
the doctor looked at his uh parents and
said it's a man
it's like Chuck Norris type comments
yeah yeah those are great um that's what
I miss about Rogan being on YouTube with
the full-length episodes oh that
comments so this is technically a
birthday podcast uh what do you love
most about getting older
it's like a it the confirmation
that comes from
getting more and more data which
basically says yeah the first time you
thought that thing it was actually right
because the second third and fourth and
fifth time
um it turned out the exact same way in
other words
um there have been a few times in my
life where
I did not feel
easy about something I did I felt
a signal for my body this is not good
um and I didn't trust it early on but I
knew it was there
and then
two or three
bad experiences later
I'm able to say ah every single time
there was a signal from the body
informing my mind
this is not good
now the reverse has also been true that
there have been a number of instances in
which I feel sort of immediate delight
and there's this kind of almost
astonishingly
simple experience of feeling comfortable
with somebody or at peace with something
or delighted at an experience and it
turns out all
literally all of those experiences and
people turned out to be experiences in
people that are still in my life and
that I
um still Delight in every day in other
words what's great about getting older
is that you stop questioning
the signals that come from the I think
deeper recesses of your nervous system
to say hey this is not good or hey this
is great more of this whereas I think in
my teens
my 20s my 30s I'm 40 almost 48 I'll be
48 next month
um
I I didn't trust I didn't listen I
actually put a lot of work into
overriding those signals and learning to
fight through them thinking that somehow
that was making me tougher or somehow
that was making me
um smarter when in fact in the end those
people that you meet that are you know
difficult or you know there are other
names for it you know it's like in here
like in the end you're like you're not a
person's piece of you know or
um this person is amazing and they're
really wonderful and I felt that from go
so you've learned to trust your gut
versus like the the influences of other
people's opinions um I've learned to
trust my gut versus the uh the forebrain
over analysis overriding the gut other
people often in my life have had great
Optics
right I've I've benefited tremendously
from an early age of being in a large
community of well it's been mostly guys
by some close female friends and always
have as well who will tell me that's a
bad decision where this person not so
good or be careful or they're great or
that's great so oftentimes my community
and the people around me have been more
aligned with the correct Choice than not
really yes really when you were younger
like like transparents and so on
I don't recall ever really listening to
my parents that much you know I grew up
in a you know we don't have to go back
to my childhood thing but my sense thank
you I learned that recently in a
psilocybin Journey
um my first my first high-dose
psilocybin Journey which was um welcome
back done with a clinician thank you
very much thank you I was worried there
for a second at one point in my not
coming back but in in any event
um yeah I grew up with some wild kids
you know I would say about a third of my
friends from childhood or dead or in
jail
um about a third have gone on to do
tremendously impressive things start
companies excellent athletes academics
um scientists and um and clinicians and
and then about a third are living their
lives has become more typical I just
mean um that they are happy family
people uh with jobs that they mainly
um serve the function to make money
they're not sort of career into their
career for career's sake but
um
so some of my friends early on gave me
some bad ideas
um but most of the time my bad ideas
came from
um
overriding the signals that I knew that
my body and I would say my body and
brain were telling me uh to obey and no
I say body and brain is that there's
this brain region the insula which um
that does many things but it represents
our sense of internal uh sensation in
terreception and I was talking to Paul
Conti about this you know as who as you
know
um I trim respect tremendously I think
he's one of the smartest people I've
ever met
um I think for different reasons he and
Mark Andreessen are some of the like
smartest people I've ever met but Paul's
level of insight into the human psyche
is is absolutely astounding and um and
um he
says the opposite of what most
people say about the brain which is most
people say oh the supercomputer of the
brain is the forebrain it's like a
monkey brain with a extra real estate
put on there and the forebrain is what
makes us human
um and gives us our our superpowers Paul
has said
um and he's done a whole series on
Mental Health that's coming out from our
uh podcast in September so this is not
an attempt to plug that but he'll
elaborate wait you're doing a thing with
fall we already did yeah so Paul oh nice
yeah so Paul Conte shot up uh we did it
he and I sat down he did a four episode
series on Mental Health this is not
mental illness mental health about how
to explore one's own subconscious
explore the self build and cultivate
um the generative Drive you'll learn
more about what that is from him he's
far more eloquent um and and clearer
than I am
um and he provides essentially a a set
of steps to explore the self that does
not require that you work with a
therapist this is self-exploration that
that is rooted in
Psychiatry it's rooted in neuroscience
and I don't think this information
exists anywhere else I'm not aware that
it exists anywhere else and um he
essentially distills it all down to one
uh eight and a half by eleven sheet
which we provide for people and
um
he says there I don't want to give too
much away because it I would detract
from what he does so beautifully but if
I tried and I want to accomplish it
anyway
um but he said and I believe that the
subconscious is the super computer of
the brain all the stuff working
underneath our conscious awareness
that's driving our feelings and our what
we think are the decisions that we've
thought through so carefully and that
only by exploring the subconscious and
understanding it a little bit
um can we actually uh
improve ourselves over time and I agree
I think that so that the mistake is to
think that thinking can override at all
it's a certain style of introspection
and thinking that um allows us to read
the signals from our body read the
signals from our brain integrate the the
knowledge that we're collecting about
ourselves and and to use all that in
ways that are really adaptive and
generative for us what do you think is
there in that subconscious well what do
you think of the younging as Shadow is
what what's there you know there's this
idea you're familiar with too I'm sure
that this jungian idea that there we all
have all things inside of us that all of
us have the capacity to be evil to be
good Etc but that some people Express
one or the other to a greater extent but
he also mentioned that there's a unique
category of people maybe two to five
percent of people that don't just have
all things inside of them but they
actually spend a lot of time exploring a
lot of those things the darker recesses
the Shadows their own Shadows
um
you know I'm somebody who's drawn to
goodness and to light into joy and all
those things like anybody else but I
think
um maybe it's part of how I grew up
maybe it was the crowd I was with
um
um maybe but then again you know even
when I started spending more time with
academics and scientists I mean
um you see shadows in other ways right
you see pure ambition with no passion I
I recall a colleague
um in San Diego who it was very clear to
me did not actually care about
understanding the brain but
understanding the brain was just his
Avenue to exercise ambition and if you
give him something else to work on he'd
work on that in fact he did he left and
he worked on something else I realized
he has no passion for understanding the
brain like all the I assumed all
scientists do certainly why I went into
it but some people it's just raw
ambition it's about winning it doesn't
even matter what they win to which to me
is crazy but I think that's a shadow
that some people explore not when I've
explored
um I think the shadow parts of us are
very important to come to understand and
look better to understand them and know
that they're there
and work with them then to not
acknowledge their presence and have them
surface in the form of addictions or
behaviors that um that damage Us in
other people so one of the processes for
achieving mental health is to bring
those things to the surface so fish the
subconscious mind yes and um and you
know he Paul describes 10 cupboards that
one can look into for exploring the self
there's the structure of self and the
function of self again this will all be
spelled out in the series in a lot of
detail also in terms of its relational
aspect between people how to pick good
partners and good relationship gets
really into this from a very different
perspective
um yeah fascinating stuff I was just
sitting there just I will say this that
that four episode series with Paul
is at least to date the most important
work I've ever been involved in
in all of my career because it's very
clear that we are not taught how to
explore our subconscious yeah and that
very few people actually understand how
to do that even most psychiatrists he
has a uh he mentioned something about
psychiatrists you know if you're a
cardiothoracic surgeon or something like
that and 50 of your patients die you're
considered a bad cardiothoracic surgeon
but with no disrespect to psychiatrists
there are there are some excellent
psychiatrists out there they're also a
lot of terrible psychiatrists out there
because unless all of those all of their
patients commit suicide or half commit
suicide they can treat for a long time
without it becoming visible that they're
not so good at their craft now he's
superb at his craft and
um I think he would say that yes
exploring some Shadows but also just
understanding the self like what what
you know really under understanding like
like who am I and and what's important
what are my ambitions what are my
striving again I'm lifting from some of
the things that that he'll describe
exactly how to do this
people do not spend enough time
addressing those questions and as a
consequence they discover what resides
in their subconscious through the
sometimes bad hopefully all also good
but um manifestations of their actions
they're we are driven by this huge
ninety percent of our real estate that
is not visible to our conscious
awareness and we we need to understand
that you know I've talked about this
before I've done therapy twice a week
since I was a kid I had to as a
condition of being let back in school
um I continue I found a way to either
through insurance or even when I didn't
have insurance I took an extra job
writing for Thrasher magazine when I was
a postdoc so I could pay for therapy at
a discount because I didn't make much
money as a postdoc I mean I think for me
it's as important as going to the gym
and people think it's just you know
ruminating on problems or getting
somewhere no no if you work with
somebody really good they're forcing you
to ask questions about who you really
are what you really want
um it's not just about support but there
should be support there should be
Rapport but then it's also
there should be Insight right most
people who get therapy they're getting
support there's rapport but Insight is
not easy to arrive at and a really good
psychologist or psychiatrist can help
you arrive at Deep insights that
transform your entire life well
sometimes when I look inside and I do
this often
you know exploring who you truly are you
come to this question
do I accept once you see parts do I
accept this or do I fix this is this a
is this who you are fundamentally
and it will always be this way or is
this a problem to be fixed like for
example one of the things
especially recently but in general over
time I've discovered about myself
probably has roots in childhood probably
has roots and a lot of things as I
deeply value loyalty
maybe more than the average person and
so when there's disloyalty it can be
painful to me and so this is who I am
and so do I have to
relax a bit
do I have to fix this part or is this
who you are and there's a million that's
one like little I think loyalty is a
good thing to cling to provided that
when loyalty is broken that it doesn't
um disrupt too many other areas of your
life but it depends also on who's
disrupting that loyalty if it's a
co-worker versus a romantic partner
versus your exclusive romantic partner
depending on the structure of your
romantic partner life you know I mean I
have always experienced extreme
um
joy and feelings of safety and Trust in
my friendships again mostly male
friendships what female friendships do
which is only to say that they were
mostly male friendships the female
friendships have also been very loyal
um let you know so getting backstabbed
is not something I'm familiar with
um and yeah I love being crewed up you
know yeah no for sure and I'm with you
and you know you and I are very much
have the same values on this but you
know that's one little thing and then
there's many other things like I'm
extremely self-critical and you look at
my you know I look at myself as I'm
regularly very self-critical there's a
self-critical engine in my brain and I
talked to actually Paul about this I
think on the podcast quite a bit and
he's saying this is a really bad thing
like you need to fix this you need to be
able to be regularly very uh positive
about yourself and I kept disagreeing
with them no this is like who I am like
you and it seems to work don't mess with
the thing that seems to be working it's
fine like I oscillate between being
really grateful and really self-critical
but then you have to like figure out
what is it maybe is there's a deeper
root thing there's maybe there's an
insecurity in there somewhere that has
to do with childhood and are you trying
to prove something to somebody from your
childhood this kind of thing well a
couple things that I think are
hopefully valuable for people here one
is
um
one way to destroy your life is to spend
time trying to control your or somebody
else's past
um so much of our destructive Behavior
and thinking comes from wanting
something that we saw or did or heard
to not be true
rather than really working with that and
getting close to what it really was and
you know sometimes those things are even
traumatic and we need to really get
close to them and and re for them to
move through us and and that you know
there are a bunch of different ways to
do that with support from others and
hopefully but sometimes on our own as
well I don't think we can rewire our
deep preferences and what we find
Despicable or joyful
I do think that
it's really a question of what allows us
peace like can you be at peace with the
fact that you're very self-critical and
enjoy that get some distance from it
have a sense of humor about it or is it
driving you in a way that's keeping you
awake at night and yeah um and forcing
you back to the table to do work in a
way that feels self-flagellating and
doesn't feel good
um you know can you get that humility
and awareness of how you're you know of
your one's flaws and I think that that
can create you know this word space
sounds very new age you like get space
from it you know you can have a sense of
humor about how how neurotic we can all
be I mean you know neurotic isn't
actually a bad term in the classic sense
of the psychologists and psychiatrists
the freudians said that you know the
best case is to be neurotic to actually
see one's own issues and work with them
whereas psychotic is the other is the
other way to be uh which is obviously
not good so I think um the question
whether or not to work on something or
to
um just accept it as part of ourselves I
think really depends if we feel like
it's holding us back or not and I I
think you're asking perhaps the most
profound question about being a human
which is you know what what do you do
with your body what do you do with your
mind I mean if you it's also a question
we started off talking about Fitness a
little bit we just for whatever reason
um you know
do I need to run an Ultra
you Marathon no I don't feel like I need
to
um David
Goggins does and and does a whole lot
more than that so that for him that's
important for me it's not important to
do that I don't think he does it just so
he can run the Ultras
um there's clearly something else in
there for him and guys like Kim Haynes
and and uh tremendous respect for for
what they do and how they do it
um
does one need to make their body more
muscular stronger more endurance more
flexibility do you need to read harder
books do you need to I think doing hard
things feels good
um I think it I know it feels good I
know that the worse I feel the worst way
to feel
is when I'm procrastinating and I don't
do something and then whenever I do
something and I complete it and I break
through that point where it was hard and
then I'm doing it at the end I actually
feel like I was infused with some sort
of
um super chemical and who knows if it's
probably a cocktail of endogenously made
chemicals but I think it is good to do
hard things but you have to be careful
not to destroy your body your mind in
the process and I think it's about
whether or not you can achieve peace can
you sleep well at night stress isn't bad
if you can sleep well at night you can
be stressed all day go go go go go go go
go and it'll optimize your focus but can
you fall asleep and stay deeply sleep at
night
um being in a hard relationship some
people say you know
that that's not good other people like
it can you be at peace in that and I
think uh we all you know I have
different RPM that you know we all kind
of idle at different RPM and
um some people are big mellow costellos
and others are kind of like you know
need more friction in order to to feel
at peace but I think ultimately what we
want is to feel at peace
I have um been through some really low
points over the past couple years and I
think
the reason could be boiled out
to the fact that I haven't been able to
find a place of peace a a place or
people or moments that give deep inner
peace
I yeah I you know
and I think you put it really
beautifully it's uh you have to figure
out given Who You Are
the various
um characteristics of your mind all the
things all the contents of the cupboards
uh how to how to get space from it and
ultimately one good representation of
that is to be able to laugh at all of it
whatever whatever's going on inside your
mind to be able to step back and just
kind of chuckle at the at the beauty and
the absurdity of the whole thing yeah
and keep going there's this beautiful uh
as I mentioned seems like every podcast
lately
um I'm a huge rancid fan mostly because
I just think Tim Armstrong's writing is
is pure poetry and whether or not you
like the music or not
um you know and he's written on music
for a lot of other people too he's not
doesn't advertise that much because he's
humble but I end up by the way I went to
a show of theirs like 20 years ago yeah
I'm going to see them in Boston in
September 18th I'm literally flying
there for for
um uh or I'll take the train up from New
York I'm gonna meet a friend of mine
named Jim thibo who's a big guy who owns
a lot of companies in skateboard
industry um we're meeting there like a
couple little kids to go see them play
amazing amazing people amazing music
music very intense very intense and but
embodies all the different emotions
that's why I love it right they have
some love songs they have some hate
songs they have some and um but you know
there's a going back to what you said I
think there's a there's a Psalm the
first song on the Indestructible album I
think it there's a
um it's sort of he's just talking about
like shock and disbelief of discovering
things about people that were close to
you and you know it's
um I won't I won't sing it but you know
nor I wouldn't dare but um but there's
this one lyric where that's really stuck
in my mind for for ever since that album
came out in 2003 which is
um you know
that nothing's what it seems so I just
sit here laughing I'm gonna keep going
on I can't get distracted there is this
piece of like you got to learn how to
push out the disturbing stuff sometimes
and go forward and I mean I remember
hearing that lyric and and then writing
it down and you know that was a time
where my undergraduate advisor who was
like a a mentor and a father to me you
know blew his head off in the bathtub
like three weeks before and then my
graduate advisor who I was working for
at that time who I loved and adored was
really like a mother to me I knew her
when she was pregnant with her two kids
died at 50. breast cancer and then my
postdoc advisor you know first day of
work at Stanford as a faculty member
sitting across the table like this from
him had a heart attack right in front of
me died of pancreatic cancer at the end
of 2017. I remember just thinking like
you know going back to that song lyric
over and over like and where people
would
um you know I haven't had many betrayals
in life I've had a few but just thinking
like we're seeing something or learning
something about something you just like
you can't believe it and I I I mentioned
that that lyric off that first song
Indestructible on that album because
it's this the emo like just the raw
emotion of like I can't believe this
what I just saw is so disturbing
but I have to just keep going forward
there are certain things that we really
do need to push not just into our
periphery but often to The Gutter and
keep going and that's a hard thing to
learn how to do but
if you're going to be functional in life
you have to and actually just to get at
this issue of do I change or do I
embrace this aspect of self
um about six months it was April
um
of this last year I did some intense
work around some things that were really
challenging to me and I did it alone and
it may have involved some medicine and I
expected to get peace through this I was
like I'm gonna let go of that and I
spent 11 hours just getting more and
more frustrated and angry about this
thing that I was trying to resolve and I
was so unbelievably disappointed that I
couldn't get that relief and I was like
what is this like this is not how this
is supposed to work
I'm supposed to be feel peace the clouds
are supposed to lift and so a week went
by
and then another half week went by and
then someone who I whose opinion I trust
very much I explained this to them
because I was getting a little concerned
like what's going on this is worse not
better and they said this is very simple
you have a giant blind spot
which is your sense of justice Andrew
and your sense of anger are linked like
an iron rod
and you need to relax it
and as they said that I felt the anger
dissipate and so there was something
that I think is it is true I have a very
strong sense of justice and my sense of
anger
then at least uh was very strongly
linked to it so it's great to have a
sense of justice right I hate to see
people wrong I absolutely do and I'm
human I'm sure I've wronged people in my
life I know I have they've told me I've
tried to apologize and reconcile where
possible still have a lot of work to do
um but
where I see Injustice it draws in my
sense of anger in a way that I think is
just eating me up and but it was only in
hearing that link that I wasn't aware of
before it was in my subconscious
obviously
um did I feel the relaxation it wasn't
there's no amount of plant medicine or
MDMA or any kind of you know chemical
you can take that's naturally just going
to dissipate what's hard for oneself it
needs if one Embraces that or if one
chooses to do it through just talk
therapy or journaling or friends or
introspection or all of the above there
needs to be an awareness of the things
that we're just not aware of so I think
the answer to your question do you
Embrace or do you fight these aspects of
self is
um I think you get in your subconscious
through good work with somebody skilled
or and sometimes that involves the tools
I just mentioned in various combinations
and you figure it out you figure out if
it's serving you obviously it was not
bringing me peace it was undermining my
my sense of justice was undermining my
sense of peace and so in understanding
this link be now I would say that the in
understanding this link between Justice
and anger now I think it's a little bit
more of like uh
you know it's not like a Twizzler stick
bendy but it's at least it's not like an
iron Rod like you know when I see
somebody wronged I mean it used to just
like like immediately but you're able to
step back now that's like to me the
ultimate place to reach
is laughter
I just sit here laughing exactly that's
that's the lyric I like I can't believe
it so I just sit here laughing like
can't get distracted just you just at
some point but the but the problem I
think in just laughing at something like
that gives you distance
but the question is
does do you stop engaging with it at
that point like I experienced this I
mean recently I got to see how sometimes
I'll see something that's just like what
like this is crazy so I just laugh but
then I continue to engage in it and it's
taking me off of course and so there is
a place where you know I mean I get
realize this is probably a kids show too
so I want to keep it you know G-rated
but it at some point for certain things
it makes sense to go
that but also laugh at yourself for
saying that yeah and then move on
so the question is are you you get stuck
or do you move on sure right sure but
like there's a lightness of being that
comes with laughter I mean I've gotten
sure like as you know I spent the day
with Elon today he just gave me this
burnt hair do you know what this is I
have no idea I'm sure there's actually
this it should be a human lab episode on
this it's a cologne that's burnt hair
and it's like supposedly a really
intense smell and it is to please it's
not gonna leave you or no that's okay
well that's okay I'll take a whiff it as
if you have a chemical spray it on
yourself because I don't know if you can
so I'm reading an amazing book yeah
called an immense World by Ed young he
won a Pulitzer for uh we contain
multitudes or something like that I
think it's the title of the other book
um and the first chapter is all battle
faction and the incredible power that
olfaction has
that smells terrible I mean it doesn't
leave you ah for those listening it
doesn't quite smell terrible it's just
intense and it stays with you
this this to me represents like just
laughing at the absurdity of it all so I
have to ask so you were rolling Jiu
Jitsu yeah so is that fight between
um Elon and and azak actually going to
happen I think Elon is a huge believer
of this idea of uh the most entertaining
outcome is the most likely
and he almost like there's
almost the sense that there's not a free
will and the universe has a kind of
deterministic
gravitational field pulling towards the
most fun
and he's just a player in that game so
from that perspective I think it seems
like something like that is inevitable
like like a little scrap in the parking
lot of Facebook or something like
exactly sorry meta yeah but it looks
like they're they're training for real
and Zuck has competed right Jiu Jitsu so
um I think he is approaching it as a
sport yeah Elon is approaching it as a
spectacle and I mean the way he talks
about it he's a huge fan of History he
talks about all the Warriors that have
fought throughout history if you look he
wants to really do it at the Coliseum
and you know the Coliseum is for 400
years I was there's so many so much
great writing about this
um I think over 400 000 people have died
in the Coliseum Gladiators so this is
this historic place that sheds so much
blood so much fear so much anticipation
of battle all of this so he loves this
kind of spectacle and also the uh the
meme of it a hilarious absurdity of it
the two Tech CEOs are battling it out on
sand in a place where Gladiators fought
to the death and then Bears and Lions
eight prisoners as part of the execution
process what's also going to be an
instance where Mark Zuckerberg and Elon
Musk has changed bodily fluids
they bleed this one thing's about
fighting you know I think it was in um
that book it's great book a Fighter's
heart where he talks about you know sort
of the intimacy of of sparring I have I
only rolled Jiu Jitsu with you once but
there was a period of time where I boxed
and um which I don't recommend
um I got hit I hit some guys and I
definitely got hit back
um I'd Spar on Wednesday nights when I
lived on San Diego
um and
um you know when you spar with somebody
even if they hurt you especially if they
hurt you you know you see that person
afterwards and there's there's an
intimacy right you're it was it was in
that book Fire's heart where he explains
you know you're exchanging bodily fluids
with a stranger right and CR there's a
you're in your primitive mind and so
there's an intimacy there that that
persists so you go together through a
process of fear anxiety like yeah when
they get you you nod I mean you watch
somebody like catch somebody if you know
not so much in professional fighting but
if people are sparring that they catch
you you acknowledge that they caught you
like you got me there and on the flip
side of that so we trained and then
after that we played Diablo 4. I don't
know what that is I don't play video
games sorry but it's a video game so
it's like it's a um
you know pretty intense combat in the
video you're fighting like demons okay
last video game played was Mike Tyson's
punch out there you go that's pretty I
met him recently went on his podcast you
want you want wait it hasn't come out
yet oh it hasn't come yeah okay yeah I
asked um Mike
um his kids are great they came in
they're super smart kids goodness
gracious they ask great questions
um asked Mike what he did with the piece
of evander's ear that that he bit off
did you remember yeah he's like get back
to him here you go sorry about that he
sells Edibles that are in the shape of
ears with a little bite out of it
um yeah that his his life has been
incredible he's um uh and I met yeah he
he his family you get the sense that
they're really a great family they're
really um Mike Tyson that's a heck of a
journey right there of a man yeah my now
friend Tim Armstrong like I said leads
to hearing from ranty he put it best he
said you know that Mike Tyson's life is
you know Shakespearean and you know down
up down up and just that the arcs of his
life are just like sort of an only in
America kind of tale too right so
speaking of Shakespeare I've recently
gotten to know Neri oxman who's this
incredible uh scientist that works at
the intersection of Nature and
engineering and
she uh reminded me of this uh Anna ahmat
of a line This is this great Soviet poet
that I really love from uh over a
century ago that each of Our Lives is a
Shakespearean drama raised to the
Thousand degree so I have to ask why do
you think humans are attracted to
this kind of Shakespearean drama
is there some aspect we've been talking
about the subconscious mind that that
pulls us towards
the drama even though the place of
mental health is peace
yes and yes do you have some of that
draw towards drama
yeah
if you look at the empirical data yes I
mean right if I look at the empirical
data I mean I think about who I chose to
work for as an undergraduate right I was
a you know barely finished high school
finally get to College
barely I think this is really
embarrassing and not something to Aspire
to you know I was
um you know thrown out of the dorms for
fighting
um I barely passed my classes you know
the girlfriend and I split up I mean I
was living in a squad got into a big
fight it was getting in trouble with the
law I eventually got my act together go
back to school start working for
somebody who do I choose to work for a
guy who's an ex-navy guy who smokes
cigarettes in the fume Hood drinks
coffee and we're injecting rats with
MDMA yeah and you know I was drawn to
like the personality his energy but I
also he was a great he was a great
scientist worked out a lot on a thermal
regulation in the brain and
um and more
um you know go to graduate school I'm
working for somebody and
decide that yeah doing working in her
laboratory wasn't quite right for me so
I'm literally sneaking into the
laboratory next door and working for the
woman next door because I like the
relationships that she had to a certain
set of questions and she was a kind of a
quirky person and you know so drawn to
drama but drawn to I like characters I
like people that have texture yeah and
I'm not drawn to Raw ambition I'm
drawing people that seem to have a real
passion for what they do and a
uniqueness to them that I I you know you
can kind of not kind of I'll just say
how it is I can feel their heart for
what they do and I'm I'm drawn to that
like um and that can be good
the same reason I went to work for Ben
Barris as a postdoc it wasn't because he
was the first transgender Man member of
the National Academy of Sciences that
was just a feature of who he was I loved
how he loved glea he would talk about
these cells like they were the most
enchanting things that he'd ever seen in
his life and I was like this is like the
biggest nerd I've ever met and I love
him
I think we're Dr I'm drawn to that
um this is another thing that Conti
makes uh elaborates on quite a bit more
in the series on Mental Health coming
out but there are different drives
within us there's this
there are aggressive drives not always
for fighting but for intense interaction
I mean look at Twitter look at some of
look at people clearly have an
aggressive Drive there's also a pleasure
Drive some people also have a strong
pleasure Drive they want to experience
pleasure through food through sex
through friendship through Adventure you
know but I think the Shakespearean drama
is the drama of the different drives in
different ratios in different people I I
know somebody and she's incredibly kind
has an extremely high pleasure Drive
loves taking great care of herself and
people around her through food and
through Retreats and through all these
things and makes spaces beautiful
everywhere she goes and is gifts these
things that are just so unbelievably
feminine and incredible these gifts to
people and the kind and thoughtful about
what they like and then
um but I would say very little
aggressive Drive
um from my read and then I know other
people who are just have a ton of
aggressive drive and very low pleasure
drive and I think so there's this
alchemy that exists where people have
these things in different ratios and
then you blend in
um you know the differences in the
chromosomes and differences in hormones
and differences in personal history and
what you end up with is a species
that
creates incredible recipes of drama but
also peace also relief from drama
contentment I mean I realize this isn't
the exact topic of the question but
um someone I know
very dearly actually an ex-girlfriend of
mine long-term partner mine
um sent me something recently I think it
hit the nail on the head which is that
ideally
for a man they eventually settle where
they find and feel peace or they feel
peaceful where they can be themselves
and feel peaceful now I'm sure there's a
equivalent or mirror image of that for
women but this particular post that she
sent was about men and I totally agree
and so
um it isn't always that we're seeking
friction but
for periods of our life we see friction
drama Adventure excitement
fights
um you know
and doing hard hard things and then I
think at some point I'm certainly coming
to this point now where it's like yeah
that's all great and checked a lot of
boxes but had a lot of close calls flew
really close to the Sun on a lot of
things with life and limb and and part
and spirit and some of you know people
close to us didn't make it and sometimes
not making it means their the career
they wanted went off a cliff or the the
their health went off a cliff or their
life went off a cliff but I think that
um there's also the Shakespearean drama
of the characters that exit the play and
are living their lives happily in the
backdrop it just doesn't make for as
much entertainment
that's one other thing that's a benefit
you could say is the benefit of getting
older is uh
um finding the Shakespearean drama less
appealing or finding the joy in the
peace yeah definitely I mean I think
that
um I think there's real peace with age I
think the other thing is this notion of
checking boxes is a real thing I for me
anyway I I have a morning meditation
that I do
um well I wake up now I get my sunlight
I hydrate I use the bathroom I do all
the things that I talk about
um I've started to practice a prayer in
the last year which is new ish for me
which is we could talk about in the
morning yeah can you talk about it a
little bit sure yeah and I and then I
have a meditation that I do that
actually is where I think through with
the different roles that I play so I
like I start very basic
um I say okay I'm an animal like we are
we are like biologically animals right
human
you know I'm a man I'm a scientist I'm a
teacher I'm a friend I'm a brother I'm a
son you know I go through this I have
this list and I think about the
different roles that I have and the
roles that I still want in my life going
forward that I haven't yet fulfilled it
just takes me it's sort of an inventory
of where I've been where I'm at and
where I'm going as they say
um and I don't know why I do it but I
started doing it this last year I think
because
um it helps me understand just how many
different uh contexts I have to exist in
and and remind myself that there's still
more that I haven't done that I'm
excited about So within each of those
contexts there's like things that you
want to kind of accomplish to Define
that yeah and I'm ambitious so I think
you know I'm a brother I have an older
sister and I love her tremendously and I
think I want to be the best brother I
can be to her which means maybe a call
maybe just
um you know we do an annual trip
together for our birthdays our birthdays
are close together we always go to New
York for our birthdays if we've gone for
last three four years like really like
reminding myself of that role not
because I'll forget but because I have
all these other roles I'll get pulled
into I say the first one I'm an animal
because I have to remember that I have a
body that needs care
like any of us I need sleep I need food
I need hydration I need that I'm human
that that the brain of a human is is
marvelously complex but also
um marvelously uh self-defeating at
times and so I've been thinking about
these things in the context of the
different roles and the whole thing
takes about four or five minutes and I
just find it brings me a certain amount
of clarity that then allows me to
ratchet into the day the prayer piece um
yeah I think I've been reluctant to talk
about
um until now
um because I don't believe in pushing
religion on people and
um and I think that
um and I'm not
um it's a highly individual thing and I
do believe that one can be an atheist
and still pray
um or agnostic and still pray but uh for
me it really came about through
understanding that there are certain
aspects of myself
that I just couldn't
resolve on my own and no matter how much
therapy no matter how much and I haven't
done a lot of it but no matter how much
plant medicine or other sorts of
medicine or exercise or
um podcasting or science or friendship
or any of that I was just not going to
resolve and so
um I started this because uh someone
close to me
um said a male friend said you know
prayer is powerful
and I said well how and I said I don't
know how but if you if you can get it
can allow you to Get outside yourself
get let you give up control and at the
same time take control I don't even like
saying take control but the whole notion
is that
again forgive me but there's no other
way to say it the whole notion is that
you know like God works through US
whatever God is to you he he him her
whatever the life force nature whatever
it is to you right that it works through
us and so I do a prayer I'll just
describe it where I I ask
um I make an ask to help remove my
defects my Character defects I I pray to
God to help remove my Character defects
so that I can show up
um better in all the roles of my life
and do good work like to which for me is
learning and teaching learning and
teaching and and so you might say well
how is that different than a meditation
well it I'm acknowledging that there is
something that bigger than me bigger
than nature as I understand it that I
cannot understand or control nor do I
want to and I'm just giving over to that
and does that make me less of a
scientist I I sure tell hope not I
certainly know I there's the head of our
neurosciences at Stanford until recently
um I you should talk to him directly
about it Bill Newsom has talked about
his religious life
um for me it's really a way of getting
outside myself and then understanding
how I fit into this bigger picture and
it's and the Character defects part is
real right I'm a human I have defects
like
I got a lot of flaws in me like anybody
but
um and trying to acknowledge them and
asking for help in removing them not
magically but through right action
through my right action
so I do that every morning and um I have
to say that it's helped it's helped a
lot it's helped me be better to myself
be better at other people
um I still make mistakes
um but it's a it's becoming a bigger
bigger part of my life and I never
thought I'd talk like this
um but
I think
it's clear to me that
if we don't
believe in something
again doesn't have to be traditional
standardized religion but if we don't
believe in something bigger than
ourselves we uh at some level will
self-destruct
I really I really think so it's power
and it's powerful in a way that all the
other stuff meditation and all the tools
is is not because it's really operating
at a much deeper and bigger level and um
you know if
yeah I think I think that's all I can
talk about it um mostly because I'm
still working out you know the
scientists in me wants to understand how
it works and I want to understand and
the point is to just go you know
there's some there's you know for lack
of a better language for it there's
higher power than me and what I can
control I'm giving up control on certain
things and somehow that restores a sense
of agency
for for right action better action I
think perhaps a part of that is just the
humility that comes with acknowledging
there's something bigger and more
powerful than you and then you can't
control everything yeah it's I mean that
you go through life as a hard driving
person you know forward Center of mass I
remember being that way since I was
little it's like a new LEGOs I'm like
all the Lego so it's like on the
weekends you know learning about
medieval weapons and giving lectures
about it in class when I was five or six
years old we're learning about tropical
fish and you know cataloging all of them
at the store and then organizing it and
making my you know my dad drive me or my
mom drive me to some fish store and then
spending all my time there until they
throw me out you know all of that but I
also remember my entire life I would
secretly pray
when things were good and things weren't
good but mostly when things weren't good
because it's important to pray for me
it's important to pray each morning
regardless but when things
weren't right I couldn't get make sense
of them I would secretly pray but I felt
kind of ashamed of that for whatever
reason and then it was once in college I
distinctly remember I I was having a
hard time with a number of things
um and I took a run
down to Sans Beach it was UC Santa
Barbara and I remember I just I was like
I don't know if I even have the right to
to do this but I'm just praying I just
prayed for uh
the ability to be as brutally honest
with myself
and with other people as I possibly
could be about a particular situation I
was in at that time
I mean I I think now it's probably safe
to say I'd gone off to college because
of a high school girlfriend we'd she
essentially she was my family more
frankly more than my biological family
was at a certain stage of life and we'd
reached a point where we were diverging
and it was it was incredibly painful it
was like losing everything I had and I
was like what do I do how do I manage
this do I you know I was ready to quit
and join the Fire Service just to
support us so we could move forward and
and
um and you know it's just but praying
just saying I can't figure this out on
my own it's sort of like I can't think
of this out on my own and how
frustrating that is no number of friends
could tell me or and inner wisdom
couldn't tell me and eventually led me
to the right answers and she and I are
friendly friends to this day she's
happily married with a child and
um we're on good terms but I think
you know it's
it's a it's a scary thing but it's the
best thing when you I can't control all
this and asking for help I think is also
the piece you're not asking for some
magic hand to come down and take care of
it you're asking for the help to come
through you right so that your body is
used to do these right works right
action isn't it interesting that this
secret thing that you're almost
embarrassed by that you did it as a
child is something you oh man it's
another thing you do as you get older is
you realize like those things are part
of you and it's actually a beautiful
thing yeah a lot of the content of the
podcast is you know deep epic content
and we talk about everything from you
know uh Eating Disorders to bipolar
disorder to depression you know a lot of
different topics but the tools are the
protocols as we say right the sunlight
viewing all the rest
um you know a lot of that stuff is just
stuff I wish I had known when I was in
graduate school if I'd known to go
outside every once in a while and get
some sunlight not just stay in the lab
I would have you know I might not have
hit a like a really tough round of
depression when I was a postdoc and
working twice as hard and you know when
my body would break down or I'd get sick
a lot I don't get sick Much Anymore
occasionally about once every 18 months
to two years I get I'll get something
but
um
learn you know I used to break my foot
skateboarding all the time I couldn't
understand what's wrong with my body I'm
getting injured I can't do what everyone
else can now I developed more slowly at
a long Arc of puberty
um but I so that was part of it I was
still developing but you know how to get
your body stronger how to build
endurance that no one told me the
information wasn't there so a lot of
what I put out there is the information
that I wish I had had because once I had
it I was like wow like a this stuff
really works B it's grounded in
something real you know some place
sometimes certain Protocols are a
combination of you know animal human and
animal and human studies sometimes
clinical trials sometimes there's some
mechanistic conjecture for some not all
I always make clear which but in the end
like
figuring out how things work so that we
can be happier healthier more productive
suffer less like reduce the suffering of
the world
um and I think that
well I'll just say thank you and um for
asking about the prayer piece
um
again I'm not pushing or even
encouraging it on anyone I've just found
it to be tremendously useful for me
you know I mean about prayer in general
you said information and uh figuring out
how to get stronger healthier smarter
all those kinds of things a part of me
believes that deeply you know you can
gain a lot of knowledge and wisdom
through learning
but a part of me believes that all the
wisdom I need was all was there when I
was
11 and 12 years old
and then it got cluttered over well
listen I can't wait for you and Conti to
talk again because
when he gets going about the
subconscious and the amount of this that
sits below the surface like an iceberg
and
and I and the fact that when we're kids
we're not
obscuring a lot of that subconscious as
much and and sometimes that can look a
little more primitive I mean I mean a
kid that's disappointed will let you
know a kid that's excited will let you
know and you feel that raw exuberance or
that raw dismail and I think that
um as we grow older we learn to cover
that stuff up we we wear masks and we
have to to be functional right I don't
think we all want to go around just
being completely
um raw but as you said as you get older
you also you get to this point where
you're gonna go
you know what what are we really trying
to protect anyway I mean I have this
theory that
you know certainly my experience has
taught me that a lot of people
but
I'll talk about men because that's what
I know best
whether or not they show up strong or
not
that they're really afraid of
being weak like they're just afraid like
sometimes the strength is even a way to
try and not be weak right which is
different than being strong for its own
sake I'm not just talking about physical
strength I'm talking about intellectual
strength I'm talking about money I'm
talking about
um
expressing Drive I've been watching this
um series a little bit of uh chimp
Empire oh yeah so chimp Empire is
amazing right they have the head champ
he's not the head chimp but the the the
alpha in the group yeah and he's getting
older and so what does he do every once
in a while he goes on these Vigor
displays he goes and he grabs Branch he
starts breaking him he starts thrashing
him and he's incredibly strong and
they're all kind of like watching I mean
yeah I immediately think of people like
they're dead lifting on Instagram and I
just think the displays a Vigor this is
just the primate sewing that displays
the figure now what's interesting is
that he's doing that specifically to say
hey I still have what it takes to lead
this troop okay then they're the the
ones that are subordinate to him but not
so not so far behind it seems to be that
there's a very clear like numerical
ranking there is like it's it's clear
who's the number two number three yeah I
mean who gets to mate first who gets to
eat first this exists in other animal
societies too but uh Bob sapolski would
be a great person to talk about this
with because he knows obviously
tremendous amount about it and I I know
just the top Contour but
um yeah so number two three and four
males are
aware that he's doing these Vigor
displays but they're also aware because
in primary Evolution they got some extra
forebrain too not as much as us but they
got some and they're aware that the
Vigor displays are displays that because
they've done them as well in a different
context might not just be displays of
vigor but might also be an insurance
policy against people seeing weakness
okay so now they start using that
prefrontal cortex to do some interesting
things so in in primate world if a male
is friendly with another man wants to
affiliate with him and say hey I'm
backing you they'll go over and they'll
they'll pick off the little
um parasites and eat them and so the
grooming is extremely important in fact
if they want to ostracize or kill one of
the members of their
um troop they will just leave it alone
no one will groom it and then there's
actually a really disturbing sequence in
that show of then the parasites start to
eat away on their skin they get
infections they have issues no one will
mate with them no one they have other
issues as well and can potentially die
so the interesting thing is is number
two and three start to line up a
strategy to groom this guy but
they are actually thinking about over
taking the entire troop setting in a new
Alpha but
the current Alpha did that to get where
he is so he knows that they're doing
this grooming thing but they're not
might not be sincere about the grooming
so what does he do he takes the whole
troop on a raid to another troop and
sees who will fight for him and who
won't this is advanced
Contracting of behavior
for a species that normally we don't
think of as as sophisticated as us so
it's very interesting and it gets to
something that I hope will have an
opportunity to talk about because it's
something that I'm obsessed with lately
is this notion of overt versus covert
contracts right there are overt
contracts where you exchange work for
money or you exchange any number of
things in an overt way but then there
are covert contracts um and those take
on a very different form and always lead
to uh in my belief bad things well how
much of human and chimp relationships
are over versus covert well here's one
thing that we know is true
dogs and humans the dog to human
relationship is 100 overt they don't
manipulate you now you could say they do
in the sense that they learn that if
they look a certain way or roll on their
back they get food but there's no
um there's no banking of that behavior
for a future date where then they are
going to undermine you and take your
position okay so in that sense dogs can
be a little bit manipulative in some
sense but
um now okay so overt contract
would be
we both want to do some work together
we're going to make some money you get X
percentage I get X percentage it's overt
covert contract
which is in my opinion bad always bad
would be we're gonna do some work
together you're gonna get a percentage
of money I'm gonna get a percentage of
money
could look just like the overt contract
but secretly I'm resentful that I got
the percentage I got
so what I start doing is covertly taking
something else what do I take maybe I
take the opportunity to jab you verbally
every once in a while maybe I take the
opportunity to show up late maybe I take
the opportunity to get to know one of
your co-workers so that I might start a
business with them that's covert
Contracting and you see this sometimes
in romantic relationships one person we
won't set the male or female in any
direction here and just say
it's I'll make you feel powerful if you
make me feel desired okay great there's
nothing explicitly wrong about that
contract if they both know and they both
agree but what if it's I'll do that but
I'll have kids with you so you feel
powerful you'll have kids with me so I
feel desired but secretly I don't want
to do that
or they one person says I don't want to
do that or both don't so what they end
up doing is saying okay so I expect
something else I expect you to do
certain things for me or I expect you to
pay for certain things for me covert
contracts are the signature of
everything bad overt contracts are the
signature of all things good yeah and I
think about this a lot because I've seen
a lot of examples of this I've
like anyone we participate in these
things whether or not we want to or not
and the thing that gets transacted the
most
is
well I should say the things that get
transacted the most are the overt things
you'll see money
um time
sex
um property
whatever happens to be information but
what ends up happening is that when
people I believe don't feel safe they
feel threatened in some way like it's
they don't feel safe in a certain
interaction what they do is they start
taking something else
while still engaging in in the exchange
and I'll tell you
if there's one thing about human nature
that's bad it's that
feature why that feature or is it a bug
or a feature as you Engineers like to
say
um I think it's because we were
allocated a certain extra amount of
prefrontal Cortex that makes us more
sophisticated than a dog
more sophisticated than a chimpanzee but
they do it too and
it's because it's often harder
to deal with in the short term to deal
with the real sense of this is scary
this feels threatening than it is to
play out all the iterations it takes a
lot of brain work you're playing chess
and go simultaneously trying to figure
out where things are going to end up and
we just don't know so it's a way I think
of creating a false sense of certainty
but I'll tell you covert contracts the
only certainty is that it's going to end
badly the question is how badly
conversely overt contracts always end
well
always the problem with overt contracts
is that you can't be certain that the
other person is not engaging in a covert
contract you can only take
responsibility for your own Contracting
well one of the challenges of being
human is looking at another human being
and figuring out
the way their way of being their
behavior which of the two types of
contracts it represents because they
look awfully the same on the surface and
it's one of the one of the challenges of
being human is the decision we all make
is are you somebody that takes a leap of
trust and trusts other humans that are
willing to take the hurt are you going
to be cynical and skeptical and avoid
most interactions until they're uh they
over a long period of time prove your
trust yeah I never liked the phrase
history repeats itself
um when it comes to humans because it
doesn't apply if the people or the
person is actively working to resolve
their own flaws I do think that if
people are willing to do dedicated
introspective work go into their
subconscious
do the hard work have hard conversations
and get better at hard conversations
something that I'm constantly trying to
get better at I think people can change
but they have to want to change it does
seem like
deep down we all can kind of tell the
difference between over and covert like
we have a good sense I think one of the
benefits of having this characteristical
mind where I value loyalty I've been
extremely uh fortunate to spend most of
my life in overt relationships and I
think that creates a really fulfilling
life but there's also this thing that
maybe we're in this uh portion of the
podcast now but
um this is late at night we're talking
that's right certainly late for me but
I'm two hours I came in today on uh I'm
still in California we should also say
that you came here to wish me a happy
birthday I did I did I and the podcast
is just like a a fun last minute thing I
suggested yeah some um close friends of
yours have arranged a dinner that I'm
really looking forward to I won't say
which night but it's the next couple of
nights
um you know your circadian clock
um is one of the most robust features of
your biology I know you can be nocturnal
or you can be diurnal we know you're
mostly nocturnal um at certain times of
the year relaxed but
um but they're very very few people can
get away with no sleep very few people
can get away with a chaotic sleep wake
schedule so you have to obey a 24-hour
AKA circadian uh Rhythm um if you want
to remain healthy of Mind and Body we
also have to acknowledge that it's
aging is in linear
right so um what do you mean well I mean
you the the degree of change between
years 35 and 40 is not going to be the
degree of change between 40 and 45 but I
will say this
I'm 48 and I feel better in every aspect
of my psychology and biology
now than I did when I was in my 20s
yeah sort of quality of of thought
um time spent
um physically I can do what I did then
which is probably says more about what I
could do then than what I can do now but
if you keep training you can continue to
get better the key is to not get injured
and I I've never trained super hard I've
trained hard but I've been cautious to
not for instance weight train more than
two days in a row I do a split which
basically three days a week and the
other day is a run take one full day off
take a week off every 12 to 16 weeks
I've not been the guy hurling the
heaviest weights or running the furthest
distance but I have been the guy who's
continuing to do it when a lot of my
friends are talking about knee injuries
hey hey hey
but of course with sport you can't
account for everything the same way you
can with Fitness and and I have to
acknowledge that you know
um unless one is power lifting you know
weight lifting and running you can get
hurt but it's not like skateboarding
where if you if you're going for you're
gonna get hurt that's just you're
landing on concrete and
um it with Jiu Jitsu like people are
trying to hurt you so that you say stop
um so with a sport it's different
um and these days I don't really do a
sport any longer
um I work out
um to stay fit I I used to
um continue to do sports but I kept
getting hurt and frankly now like a
rolled ankle
um
I may put out a little small skateboard
part in 2024 because people have been
saying we want to see the kickflip you
want to say well I'll do a heel flip
instead but okay
um uh I might put out a little part
because some of the guys that work on
our podcast are from DC I think by now I
I I should at least do it just to show
like I'm not making it up
um and I probably will but I think that
doing a sport is different that's how
you get hurt
overuse and doing it an actual sport and
so you know hat tip to those do an
actual sport
and that's a difficult decision like I a
lot of people have to make I have to
make with Jiu Jitsu for example like if
you just look empirically I've trained
really hard from all my life and
grappling Sports and fighting Sports and
all this kind of stuff and I've avoided
injury for the most part and I would say
I would attribute that to
um training a lot sounds
counterintuitive but training well and
safely and correctly keeping good form
saying no and I need to say no but
training a lot and taking it seriously
now when this training is kind of a side
really a side thing I find that the
injury is uh becomes a higher and higher
probability when you're just doing it
every once in a while every once in a
while yeah that I think you said
something really important that the um
saying no I mean the times I have gotten
hurt training is when someone's like hey
let's hop on this workout together and
it becomes uh let's challenge each other
to do something outrageous
um sometimes that can be fun though I
went up to cam haines's gym and he does
these very high repetition weight
workouts that are in circuit form I was
sore for two weeks but
um I learned a lot and didn't get
injured and um and yes we ate bow hunted
elk afterwards nice but the the injury
has been a really difficult
psychological thing for me because um
so I've injured my uh my finger pinky
fingered my knee yeah your kitchen is
filled with splints splints I'm trying
to figure I'm trying to figure out
it's like if you look at Lex's kitchen
there's there's some really good snacks
I had some right before
um he's very good about keeping cold
drinks in the fridge
um and all the water has element in it
which is great I love that
um but then there there's a whole like
Hospital's worth of splints yeah I'm
trying I'm trying to figure out so
here's the thing you uh I think like pop
out like this right uh pinky finger I'm
trying to figure out how do I splint in
such a way that I can still program
still play guitar
but protect this kind of torque motion
that creates a huge amount of pain and
that's a bit of a jiu jitsu injury
Jiu-Jitsu but it's a it's not the kind
of it's probably more like a
skateboarding style injury which is
it's unexpected in a silly in a silly
thing that happens in a second I didn't
break my foot doing anything important
Yeah I broke my
fifth minute stepping off a curb so it's
that's why they're called accidents
yeah if you get hurt doing something
awesome that's a trophy yeah that you
have to work through it's part of your
payment to the universe
if you get hurt stepping off a curb or
you know doing something stupid
called a stupid accent
since we brought up chimp Empire let me
ask you about relationships
I think we talked about relationships
yeah I only date Homo sapiens
uh the morning meditation the night is
still young you are human no but you are
also animal
don't sell yourself short no I always
say listen any discussion on the human
Lab podcast about sexual health or
anything I always be the the critical
Force consensual age-appropriate context
appropriate species appropriate species
appropriate well can I just tell you
about sexual selection
um I've been watching Life in Color with
David Attenborough because I've been
watching a lot of nation documentaries
talking about inner peace it brings me
so much peace to watch nature and it's
worse than at its best so Life in Color
is a series on Netflix where
it presents some of the most colorful
animals on Earth and kind of tells their
story of how they got there through
natural selection so you know you have
the peacock with the feathers and it's
just such incredible colors like the
peacock has these
uh tail feathers uh the male
that are like gigantic and they're super
colorful and they're these eyes
on on it it's not eyes it's like I like
areas and and they wiggle their ass like
to show the Tails they wiggle the tails
the eye spots the eye spots yes thank
you you know this probably way better
than me I'm just quoting it no David at
least continue but it was it's just I'm
watching this and then the female is as
boring looking as pot like she has no
colors or nothing but she's standing
there bored just seeing this entire
display and I'm just wondering like the
entirety of life on Earth or not the
entirety post-bacteria is like
in at least in part maybe in a large
part can be described through this
process of natural selection of sexual
selection so
dudes fighting
and then women selecting it seems like
it's just the the entirety of that
series shows some incredible birds and
insects and shrimp they're all beautiful
and colorful and just a shrimp Manta
shrimp they're just they're incredible
and it's all about getting laid it's
fascinating like I just
um and there's nothing like watching
that and Champa Empire to make you
realize we humans that's the same thing
that's all we're doing and all the
beautiful variety all the bridges in the
buildings and the rockets and the
internet all of that is this kind is is
at least in part this kind of uh a
product of this kind of showing off for
each other
and all the wars and all this anyway uh
well there's that I'm asking oh
relationships well right um before you
ask about relationship I think what's um
clear is that every species it seems
animal species wants to make more of
itself and protect its young
with the protect this young is
non-obvious so not destroy enough
um of itself uh that it can't get more
to reproductive competent age I mean I
think that
you know we have a natural I mean
healthy people have a natural reflex to
protect
children
well I don't know and those that can't
wait a minute wait wait wait wait a
minute I've seen enough animals that are
murdering the children sure some other
sure there's even simplicide they're
like
first of all I just want to say that I I
was um delighted in your Delight around
Animal Kingdom stuff because this is a
favorite uh theme of mine as well but
there's for instance
some fascinating uh data on for instance
uh for those that grew up on farms
they'll be familiar with free Martins
you know about free Martins this is
they're cows that have multiple
um calves inside them and there's a
situation in which the calves will
secrete if there's more than one inside
will secrete chemicals that will
um hormonally castrate the cap next to
them so they can't reproduce so already
in the womb they are fighting for future
resources that's how early this stuff
can start so it's chemical warfare in
the womb Against The Sibling sometimes
there's outright sibilicide siblings are
born they kill one another
um this also becomes biblical stories
right
um there are instances of cuttlefish
beautiful cephalopods like octopuses um
and that is the plural as we yeah um
the internet oh yeah that became a meme
or a little discussion yeah pretty quick
oh yeah and now we just resurfaced it
that's great the dismay in your voice is
so amusing
um in any event that the male cuttlefish
will disguise themselves by as female
cuttlefish infiltrate the female
cuttlefish uh
um group and then mate with them you
know
um all sorts of
um you know
types of covert uh operations so I think
that
combat it's like a drinking game where
every time we say covert in a contract
in this uh episode you have to take a a
shot of espresso please don't do that
you'd be dead by the end
um so it actually is just a small
tangent it does make me wonder how much
intelligence covert contracts require it
seems like not much if they if we could
if you can do it in the animal kingdom
there's some kind of instinctual it is
based perhaps in like fear yeah it could
be um simple algorithm if if you know if
there's some ambiguity about numbers and
I'm not with these guys and you know
then flip to the alternate strategy I
actually have a story about this that I
think is relevant I used to have
cuttlefish in my lab in San Diego uh we
went and got them from a guy out in the
desert we put them in the lab is amazing
and they I had a postdoc who was
studying prey capturing cuttlefish they
have a very ballistic extremely rapid
strike and grab of the shrimp and they
um we were using high speed cameras uh
to to characterize all this looking at
binocular they normally have their eyes
on the side of their head when they see
something they want to eat the eyes
translocate to the front which allows
them stereopsis depth perception allows
them to strike we were doing some
unilateral eye removals they would miss
Etc okay
this has to do with eye spots
this was during a government shutdown
period where the ghost shrimp that they
normally
um feed on that we would ship in from
the Gulf down here weren't available to
us so we had to get different shrimp and
what we noticed was the the Cuttlefish
normally would just sneak up on the
shrimp we learned this by data
collection and if the shrimp was facing
them they would do this thing with their
tentacles of kind of enchanting the
cuddle the the shrimp and if the shrimp
wasn't facing them they wouldn't do it
and they would ballistically grab it and
and eat them
well when we got these new shrimp the
new shrimp had eye spots on their tails
and then the Cuttlefish would do this
kind of attempt to enchant regardless of
the position of the ghost shrimp so what
does that mean okay well it means that
there's some sort of algorithm in the
cuttlefish's mind that says okay if you
see two spots move your tentacles so it
can be as you pointed out it can be a
fairly simple operation but it looks
diabolical it looks cunning but all it
is is strategy B
yeah but it's still somehow
emerged I mean I I I don't think that
it's like calling it an algorithm
doesn't I feel like well there's a
circuit there that gets implemented in a
certain context but that circuit had to
evolve you do realize it super
intelligent AI will look at us humans
and we'll say the exact thing there's a
circuit in there that evolved to do this
the algorithm a and algorithm B and it's
trivial and to us humans it's fancy and
beautiful where I poetry about it but
it's because so we don't understand the
subconscious because they want that AI
algorithm cannot see into what it can't
see it doesn't understand the
underworkings of what allows all of this
conversation stuff to manifest and we
can't even see it how could AI see it
maybe it will maybe maybe AI will solve
and give us access to our subconscious
maybe your AI friend or coach like I
think Andreessen and others are are
arguing is going to happen at some point
it's going to say Hey you know Lex
you're making decisions lately that are
not good for you but it's because of
this
algorithm that you picked up in
childhood that if you don't State your
explicit needs up front
you're not going to get what you want so
why do it from now on you need to
actually make a list of every absolutely
outrageous thing that you want no matter
how outrageous and communicate that
immediately and that will work we're
talking about coefficient sexual
selection and then we went into some uh
where do we go well and you said you
were excited I was I was I was excited
well you were just saying what about
these these covert contracts and animals
do them I think it's simple contextual
engagement of a neural circuit which is
not just nerd speak for saying they do a
different strategy saying that there has
to be a circuit there hardwired circuit
maybe learned but probably hardwired
that can be engaged right you can't
build neural Machinery out of in a
moment
um you need to build that circuit over
time what is building it over time you
select for it the the Cuttlefish that
did not have that alternate context
driven circuit didn't survive when there
was a uh when all the shrimp that they
normally disappear here in the ice
spotted shrimp showed up and there were
a couple that had some miswiring this is
why mutation right X-Men type stuff is
real
um they had a mutation they had some
alternate wiring and that wiring got
selected before it became a mutation
that was adaptive as opposed to male
adaptive this is something people don't
often understand about genetics is that
it only takes a few generations to
devolve a trait make it worse but it
takes a long time to evolve an Adaptive
trait there are exceptions to that but
most often that's true so a species
needs a lot of generations we are
hopefully still evolving as a species
and it takes a long time but uh to
evolve more adaptive traits but doesn't
take long to to devolve
adaptive traits so that you're getting
sicker or you're not functioning as well
so choose your mate wisely and that's
perhaps a good segue into sexual
selection humans I could tell you you're
good at this
uh who said well why did I bring up
sexual selection it's good relationship
so um it's extra selection in humans
even I I don't think you've done an
episode on relationships
no I did um an episode on attachment
right um but not on relationships the
the series with Conti includes one
episode of the four that's all about
relational understanding and how to
select a mate based on
um matching of drives and all the the
the the the Demons Inside the
subconscious how to match demons and
they dance well together or what and how
generative two people are what does that
mean means that um how the way he
explains it is how devoted to creating
growth within the context of the family
the relationship with work well let me
ask you about mating rituals and uh how
to find such a relationship
I mean you're really big on friendships
on the value of friendships I am
um
and that I think extends itself into a
one of the deepest kinds of friendships
you can have which is a romantic
relationship
what uh What uh uh mistakes
successes and wisdom can you impart well
I've certainly made some mistakes I've
also made some good choices in this
realm
um
first of all we have to Define what sort
of relationship we're talking about if
if one is looking for a life partner you
know potentially somebody to establish
family with with or without kids with or
without pets right families can take
different forms
um I mean I certainly experience being a
family in a prior relationship where it
was the two of us and our two dogs and
it was like it was family like we had
our little family
um
I think
based on my experience and based on
input from friends who themselves have
very successful relationships I must say
I've got friends who
um are in long-term monogamous
very happy
uh relationships where there seems to be
um a lot of love a lot of laughter
a loud Challenge and a lot of growth
and both people
it seems really want to be there and
enjoy being there
it's just a pause on that one thing
to do I think by way of advice is listen
to people who are in long-term
successful relationships that's like uh
it seems dumb but like like we both know
and are friends with Joe Rogan who's
been in a long-term really great
relationship and he's been an
inspiration to me so you take advice
from that guy definitely and several
members of my podcast team are in
excellent relationships I I think
um one of the things that Rings true
over and over again in the advice and in
my experience is
you know find someone who's really a
great friend like build a really great
friendship with that person now
obviously not just a friend if we're
talking romantic relationship but
um and of course sex is super important
but it should be a part of
that particular relationship alongside
or meshed with the Friendship uh
can it be a majority of the the positive
exchange I suppose it could but I think
the Friendship piece is extremely
important because what's required in a
successful relationship clearly is
joy in being together
Trust
a desire to share experience both you
know mundane and and More Adventurous
support each other
acceptance
a real
maybe even admiration but certainly
Delight in being with the person you
know earlier we were talking about peace
and I think that that sense of Peace
comes from knowing that the person
you're in friendship with or that you're
in romantic relationship or ideally both
because let's assume healthy relation
the best romantic relationship includes
a friendship component with that person
it's like you just freely Delight in
their presence even if it's a quiet
presence
um
and you Delight in seeing them Delight
in things right
um that's clear uh the trust piece is
huge
um you know and and that's where people
start I you know we don't want to focus
on what works not what doesn't work but
that's where I think people
start engaging these covert contracts
they're afraid of being betrayed so they
betray
they're afraid of giving up too much
vulnerability so they hide their
vulnerability or in the worst cases they
feign vulnerability
um again that's a covert contract that
just simply undermines everything it
becomes one equals two minus one to
Infinity
conversely I think if people can have
really hard conversations this is
something I've had to work really hard
on in recent years that I'm still
working hard on but the Friendship piece
seems to be the thing that rises to the
top when I talk to friends who are in
these great relationships it's like they
they have so much respect and love and
joy in being with their friend is the
person that they want to spend as much
of their non-working non
uh platonic friendship time with and the
person they want to experience things
with and share things with and
um and it sounds so kind of canned and
cliche nowadays but I think if you step
back and examine how most people go
about finding a relationship so I'm like
oh like am I attracted of course
physical attraction is important in
other forms of Attraction too and they
sort of enter through that portal which
makes sense that's that's the mating
dance right that's the peacock situation
that's hopefully not the Cuttlefish
situation
um but but I think that
um there seems to be
a history of people close to me getting
into great relationships where they were
friends for a while first or maybe
didn't sleep together right away yeah
that they actually intentionally
deferred on that
um this has not been
my habit or my experience you know I've
gone to more
um I think typical like oh there's an
attraction like this person there's an
interest you kind of explore all
dimensions of relationship really
quickly except perhaps the moving in
part and having kids part
um which ideally because it's a bigger
step harder to undo without more severe
consequences
but I think
the whole take it slow thing
um I don't think is about getting to
know someone slowly I think it's about
that physical piece because that does
change the nature of the relationship
and I think it's because it gets right
into the more hardwired primitive
circuitry around our feelings of of
safety vulnerability
um you know there's something about
uh romantic and sexual interactions
where it's almost like
it's like assets and liabilities right
where people are trying to figure out
how much to engage their time and their
energy and multiple people I'm talking
about from both sides you know male
female or whatever it decides but where
it's like assets and liabilities and and
that that's where it starts getting I um
into those
complicated contracts early on I think
and so maybe that's why if a really
great friendship and admiration is is
established first
even if people are romantically and
sexually attracted to one another then
that piece can be added in a little bit
later in a way that
really kind of just seals up the whole
thing and then who knows maybe they
spend 90 of their time having sex I
don't know
um that that's not for me to say or or
decide obviously but there's something
there about
staying out of a certain amount of um
uh risk of having to engage covert
contract in order to protect oneself
but I I do think like
uh
love at first sight this kind of idea is
uh in part realizing very quickly that
you are great friends like I've had that
interesting experience a friendship
recently just it's not really friendship
but like oh you get each other with
humans not I'm not in a romantic setting
right friendship yeah just friendship
dare I say I felt that way about you
when we met right but we also this
dude's cool and he's smart and he's
funny and he's driven and he's giving
and he um and he's got an edge and
um like
I want to want to learn from want to
hang out with them like that I mean that
was the beginning of our friendship was
essentially you know that set of of
internal realization I'm going just keep
going that good keep going shark dresser
yeah yeah it just looks great shirtless
on Horseback yes no no no listen I mean
it's despite what some people might say
on the Internet it's a purely platonic
um friendship somebody said uh somebody
asked if Andrew cooperman has a
girlfriend and somebody says I think so
and the the third comment was this
really like uh breaks my heart like that
uh Alex and Andrew are not a not an item
we are not we are great friends but we
are not an item that's true it's
official the um uh I hear over and over
again from friends that have made great
choices and awesome partners and have
these fantastic relationships for long
periods of time that can seem to
continue to thrive at least that's what
they tell me and that's what I've
observed
establish the Friendship first
and give it a bit of time before
sex and so
you know
I think that's the feeling that's the
feeling and and these are we're talking
micro features and macro features we're
talking you know and this isn't about
perfection it's actually about the
imperfections which is kind of cool I
like quirky people I like characters
I'll tell you where I've gone badly
wrong where I see other people going
badly wrong
if there is no rule that says that you
have to be attracted to all Attractive
people
by any means it's very important to
develop a sense of taste in romantic
attractions I believe what you really
like in terms of a certain style you
know a certain way of being and of
course that includes
um sexuality
um and sex itself the verb but it I
think it also includes there's just
general way of being you know and when
you really adore somebody you like the
way they answer the phone and when they
don't answer the phone that way you know
something's off and you want to know and
so I think that
[Music]
um
the more
you can tune up your powers of
observation not looking for things that
you like
and the more that stuff just kind of
washes over you the more likely you are
to quote unquote fall in love as a
mutual friend of ours uh said to me you
know listen when it comes to romantic
relationships if it's not a hundred
percent in you
it ain't happening and I've never seen
a violation of that statement
where it's like it yeah it's mostly good
and they're this is like the
negotiations well already you're you're
you're it's doomed and that doesn't mean
someone has to be perfect the
relationship has to be perfect but it's
got to feel 100 inside like yes yes and
yes I think diceroth when he was on here
uh your podcast
um mentioned something that you know
like I think the words were you or maybe
it was in his book I don't recall but
that you know love is one of these
things that we story into with somebody
we create this idea of ourselves in the
future and we look at our past
time together and then you story into it
I mean the very few things like that I
can't story into
you know building flying cars I I have
to actually go do something I mean
um
yeah and love is also retroactively
constructed I mean anyone who's gone
through a breakup understands the grief
of knowing ah like this is something I
really shouldn't be in for whatever
reason if because it only takes one if
the other person doesn't want to be it
then you shouldn't be in it but then
missing so many things and that's just
the attachment Machinery really at work
I have to ask you a question that uh
somebody in our amazing team wanted to
ask
he's happily married another like you
mentioned incredible relationship are
they good friends are there Amazing
Friends there you go but okay I'm not
saying who it is so I can say some stuff
which is they it started out as a great
uh sexual connection oh well there you
go but then became very close friends
after that listen there you go uh So
speaking of sex
he was uh he has a wonderful son and
he's wanting to have a second kid and he
wanted to ask the great Andrew huberman
is there uh like sexual positions or any
kind of thing that can help
maximize the chance that they have a
girl versus a boy because they're that
wonderful boy they want a girl is there
is there a way to control the gender
this has been debated for a long time
and I did a uh four and a half hour
episode on fertility and the reason I
did a four and a half hour episode of
fertility is that first of all I find
that the reproductive biology be
fascinating and I wanted a resource for
people that
um were thinking about or struggling
with having kids uh for whatever reason
um and it felt important to me to
combine the male and female components
in the same episode it's all time
stamped so you don't have to listen to
the whole thing I'm gonna talk about IVF
and virtual fertilization we talk about
natural pregnancy okay the data on
position is very interesting but let me
just say a few things there are a few
clinics now in particular some out of
the United States that are spinning down
sperm and finding that they can separate
out fractions as they're called you know
that can spin the sperm down at a given
speed and they'll separate out at
different
um sort of depths within the test tube
that allow them to pull out the sperm on
top or below and bias the probability
towards male or female births it's not
perfect it's not 100 it's a very costly
procedure it's still very controversial
um now with in vitro fertilization it
can extract eggs you can do introduce a
sperm directly by pipette it's a process
called ixy or you can set up a sperm
race in a dish and if you get a number
of different embryos
um meaning the eggs get fertilized to
duplicate and for start to form a
blastocyst which is a ball of cells
early embryo then you can do karyotyping
so you can do look for XX or XY select
the XY which then would give rise to a
male offspring and then plant that one
so there is that kind of sex selection
um
with respect to position there's a lot
of lore that you know if
um the woman is on top or the woman's on
the bottom or whether or not the
penetration is from behind whether or
not it's going to be male or female
Offspring and frankly the data are not
great as you can imagine because those
those would be interesting studies to
run perhaps
um there is studies there is paper there
are some there are they're not I guess
yeah there's more lore than science and
there's a lot of and there are a lot of
other variables that are hard to control
so for instance if it if it's um
ejaculation during intermission during
during sex penetration Etc
um
then you can't measure for instance
sperm volume as opposed to when it's IVF
and they can actually measure how many
milliliters how many forward motile
sperm it's hard to control for for
certain things and um this can vary
between individuals and even from one
ejaculation the next and okay so there's
too many variables however the position
thing is interesting
in the following way
um and then I'll answer whether or not
you can bias towards a female
um as long as we're as long as we're
trying I have other questions about sex
but as long as we're talking about
sexual position all right there are data
that support the idea that in order to
increase the probability of successful
fertilization
that indeed the woman should not stand
upright after sex
and should right after right after the
man is ejaculated inside her and should
adjust her pelvis say 15 degrees upwards
I mean you know
some of the fertility experts MDS will
say that's crazy you know but others
that I
sought out and not specifically for this
answer but for researching that episode
said that yeah you know what you're
talking about is trying to get the
maximum number of sperm and it's
contained in semen and yes the semen can
leak out and so keeping um the pelvis
tilted for about at 15 degrees for about
15 minutes obviously tilted in the
direction that would have things running
Upstream not Downstream so to speak
would gravity it's real
um you know
um so so for maximizing uh fertilization
you know that the doctors I spoke to
just said look given that if people are
trying to get pregnant what is spending
15 minutes on their back
um you know this sort of thing okay so
then with respect to there to female
getting a female Offspring or XX
female Offspring
um
selectively there is the idea that as
fathers get older they're more likely to
have daughters as opposed to Sons that's
a from the papers I've read is a
significant but still mildly significant
result so at with each passing year
um this person increases the probability
they're gonna have a daughter not a son
look um so that's interesting but the
probability differences are probably
tiniest I mean it's it's not you know
it's a signif it's not trivial it's not
a trivial difference
um but if they want to ensure having
a daughter then they should do IVF and
select an xxm um embryo and um when you
go through IVF they genetically screen
them for karyotype which is xxxy
um and they look at mutations genotypic
mutations for things like you know
trisomies and the employees all the
stuff you don't want
but there is a lot of lore if you look
on the internet sure different foods uh
so a lot of variables there's a lot of
area but there haven't been systematic
studies so
um I think probably the best thing to do
unless they're going to do IVF is just
you know roll the dice and um you know
and I think uh with each passing year
they increase the probability of getting
a female Offspring
um and with but of course with each
passing year the egg and sperm quality
degrade so you know get after it soon so
uh I went down a rabbit hole there's
like sexology there's there's journals
oh yeah on sex sure okay so I and some
of them some of them not all quite
reputable
um yeah and some of them really
pioneering in the sense that
um they've taken on topics that are you
know
considered you know outside the main
frame of what people talk about they're
very important
um we have episodes coming out soon with
for instance the head of
um male Urology sexual health and
reproductive Health at Stanford Michael
Eisenberg but also
um you know one with a female urologist
Sexual Health reproductive Health uh Dr
Rena Malik who's on has a quite active
YouTube presence she does these really
um like dry
um present like scientific presentation
but very nice she has a lovely voice and
she but she'll be talking about you know
erections or squirting or like oh is it
like she does like very kind of Internet
type content
um but she's a legitimate urologist
reproductive health expert and in the
podcast we we did talk about
um both male and female orgasm we talked
a lot about sexual function dysfunction
we talked a lot about pelvic floor one
interesting factoid is that
only three only three percent of sexual
dysfunction is
foreign
in nature it's more often related to
some pelvic floor or vasculature blood
flow related or other issue and then
when Eisenberg came on the podcast he
said that far less sexual dysfunction is
psychogenic in origin then people
believe that far more of it is pelvic
floor neuro and Vascular so you know
there's there are the myths of
um I mean it's not saying that it's that
psychogenic dysfunction doesn't exist
but that a lot of the sexual dysfunction
that people assume is related to
hormones or that is related to
psychogenic issues are related to
vascular or neural issues and the good
news is that there are great remedies
for those and um and so those both those
episodes detail some of the
um more Salient points about what those
remedies are and could be I mean one of
the kind of again
factoids but it's interesting that you
know a lot of people have pelvic floor
issues and they think that their pelvic
floors are
um quote unquote messed up so they go on
the internet they learn about kegels
kegels that you know and it turns out
that some people need Giggles they need
to strengthen their pelvic floor guess
what
a huge number of people with sexual and
neurologic
dysfunction
have pelvic floors that are too tight
and kegels are going to make them far
worse and they actually need to learn to
relax their pelvic floor instead of
seeing a pelvic floor specialist is
important I think in the next five ten
years we're going to see a dramatic
shift towards more discussion about
sexual and reproductive Health in a way
that acknowledges that yeah the clitoris
is comes from the same origin tissue as
the the penis and in many ways that the
neural innervation of the two while
clearly different has some overlapping
features that
um you know that there's going to be
discussion around kind of anatomy and
hormones and pelvic floors and
um in a way that's gonna you know um
erode some of the the kind of like
cloaking of these topics because they've
been cloaked for a long time and there's
a lot of like
but let's just call what it is there's a
lot of out there about what's
what
um and now the hormonal issues by the
way just to clarify can impact desire so
a lot of people who have lack of desire
as opposed to lack of anatomical
function this could be male or female
that that can originate with either
things like ssris or hormonal issues and
so we talk about that as well so it's a
pretty vast topic okay you've uh you're
one of the most productive people I know
uh what what's the secret to your
productivity how do you uh maximize the
number of productive hours in a day your
scientist your teacher you're a very
prolific educator
well thanks for the kind words I
struggle like everybody else but I
um I'm pretty
Relentless about
meeting deadlines oh I miss them
sometimes but sometimes that means
cramming sometimes that means starting
early but has that been hard sorry to
interrupt with the podcast you uh
there's certain episodes
I mean you're like taking just
incredibly difficult topics and you know
they're going to be there's going to be
a lot of really good scientists
listening to those with a very skeptical
and careful eye
like how hard do you struggle meeting
that deadline sometimes yeah so we've
pushed out episodes because I want more
time with them I also I haven't
advertised this um but I have another
uh fully tenured professor that's
started um checking my my
um podcasts and helping me
um find papers he's a close friend of
mine he's an incredible expert in
neuroplasticity and that's been helpful
but I research all my all I do all the
primary research for the episodes myself
although my niece has been doing a
summer internship with me and finding
amazing papers she did last summer as
well she's really good at it
um just sick that kid on the internet
and she gets great stuff
um just going on tangents here
what's the hardest finding the papers or
understanding what a paper is saying or
finding finding the best papers yeah
because you have to you know you read a
bunch of reviews figure out who's
getting cited call people in a field
make sure that this is the stuff I mean
you know I did this episode recently on
ketamine about ketamine I wasn't on
ketamine and um and you know there's
this whole debate about s versus arcade
I mean Sr Academy and I called two
clinical experts at Stanford I had a
researcher at UCLA help me even then you
know a few people had gripes about it I
don't think they understood a section
that I was perhaps could have been
clearer about
um but yeah you you're always concerned
that people won't either won't get it or
I won't be clear so that the researching
is mainly about finding the best papers
and then I'm looking for papers that
establish thoroughness of understanding
um that are interesting obviously it's
fun to get occasionally look at some of
the odd or more Progressive papers that
are you know what's new in a field and
then where there are actionable
takeaways to to Really
um export those with with a lot of
thoughtfulness I mean I think that
um going back to the productivity thing
um you know I I do I get up I look at
the sun I I don't stare at the Sun but I
get my sunshine I it all starts with a
really good night's sleep I think that's
really important to understand so much
so that if I wake up and I don't feel
rested enough I'll often do a non-sleep
depressed Yoga Nidra or go back to sleep
for a little bit get up really
prioritize one you know the big block of
work for the thing that I'm researching
I think a little bit of anxiety and a
little bit of concern about deadline
helps
um turning the phone off helps
um
realizing that those peak hours whenever
they are for you you you do not allow
those hours to be invaded unless there's
a you know a nuclear bomb goes off
um and
and nuclear bomb is just a you know a
phraseology for um you know it could be
family crisis would be and you know
would be a good justification if there's
an emergency obviously but
um it's all about Focus it's all about
focus in the moment it's not even so
much about
um how many hours you log it's really
about focusing about how much total
focus can you give to something and then
I like to take walks and think about
things
um and sometimes talk about them in my
voice recorder so I'm just always
churning on it all the time and um
and then of course learning to turn it
off and engage with people socially and
you know not not be podcasting 24 hours
a day in your head is key but I think I
love learning and researching and
finding that those papers and the
information and I love teaching it and
these days I use a whiteboard before I
start I don't have any notes no
teleprompter then the white board that I
use beforehand is to really sculpt out
the different elements and and the flow
get the flow right and move things
around the the Whiteboard is such a
valuable tool then take a couple
pictures of that
when I'm happy with it put it down on
the desk and these are just bullet
points and then just churn through and
just turn through and nothing feels
better than you know researching and
sharing information and and I and as you
did you know grew up writing papers and
it it's hard and I like the friction of
like uh can't you know I want to get up
I want to use the bathroom when I was in
College I was trying to make up
deficiencies from my lack of attendance
in high school
so much so that I I would set a timer I
wouldn't let myself get up to use the
bathroom even never had an accident but
I was you know I mean it's like I
listened to music classical music rancid
a few other things some Bob Dylan maybe
thrown in there
um and just study and just and it felt
and then you know hit the two hour mark
and you're in pain and then you get up
yeah like use the bathroom like that
felt so good there's something about the
human brain that likes these kind of
friction points and working through them
and you just have to work through them
so yeah I'm productive and and my life
has arranged around it and you know
that's been a bit of a barrier to
personal life at times but my life's
been arranged around it I've set up
everything so that I can learn more
teach more
um including
you know some of my home life and
um but I do you know still watch chimp
Empire still got time to watch Jim Bob
look the great Joe Strummer
all right Clash or my favorite
mescaleros he said you know this famous
drummer quote no input no output
so you need you need experience you need
outside things in order to Foster the
the process but
uh yeah just nose to the grindstone man
I don't know I don't I don't know and
that's what and that's what I'm happy to
do with my life I don't think anyone
should do that just because but this is
how I'm showing up and you know if you
don't like me then Scrolls whether they
say swipe left so whatever I I don't
know I'm not on the apps the dating apps
so that's the other thing I keep waiting
for when um
listens to like Freeman podcast is a
check box on like hinge or Bumble or
whatever it is but I don't even know are
those that are field is I don't know
what the what are the apps now I've
never used an app and I I I those
file Troublesome how little information
is provided on apps well they're the
ones that are like a stocked Lake like
like Raya you know it's like that they
like they sort of like companies will
actually fill them with people that look
a certain way and well soon it'll be
filled with AI oh yeah that's the way
you said oh yeah that's a hard break
within that well I you know I'm guilty
of liking real human interaction
that have you tried AI interaction
no but I have a feeling you're gonna
convince me to
one day
um yeah I've I've also struggled
finishing projects that are new there
are some something new
like for example some one of the things
that really struggled finishing is
something that's in Russian that
requires translation and overdub and all
that kind of stuff the other project
I've been working on for like over
at least a year
and off and on but trying to finish is
something we've talked about in the past
is I'm still on it uh project on Hitler
in World War II I've written so much
about it and I just don't know why I
can't finish it I have trouble like
really
um
I think I'm terrified being in front of
the camera
like this like this or so well actually
no no no solo well if you want to do
solo and seriously because we've done
this before right our our clandestine uh
study missions I'll I'm happy to sit in
the corner and work on my book or do
something if you want to if it feels
good it's just just for the feeling of
somebody else definitely what do you I
mean how do you you don't seem to
you seem to have been Fearless to just
sit in front of the camera
by yourself to do the episode yeah it
was weird I mean the first year of the
podcast it just spilled out of me it was
just I had all that stuff I was so
excited about I've been talking to
everyone and who would listen and anyone
uh anyone who they run away I'd keep
talking you know before there was ever a
camera wasn't on social media in 2019 I
posted a little bit 2020 as you know I
started going on podcast but yeah I had
so I just
I just
the zest and Delight in this stuff it's
like circadian rhythms I'm going to tell
you about this stuff I just felt like
here's the opportunity and just let it
burst and then as we've gotten into
topics that are a little bit further
away from my my um home knowledge you
know it the it's like
I still get super excited about it it's
music in the Brain Episode I've been
researching for a while and I'm just so
hyped like about it it's so so
interesting there's so many facets
singing versus improvation
improvisational excuse me music versus
I'm listening to music versus
um learning music I mean it just goes on
and on there's just so much that's so
interesting I just can't get enough and
and I think
oh you put a camera in front of me I
sort of forget about it uh and I'm just
trying to just teach yes that's the
difference that's interesting I mean I
forget the camera maybe I need to find
that joy as well but like for me a lot
of the joys in the in the writing and uh
the the camera there's something well
the best lecturers as you know and
you're in a phenomenal lecturer so you
embody this as well but the when I teach
at Stanford I was directing this course
in neuroanatomy and Neuroscience and for
medical students and I noticed that the
best lecturers would come in and they're
teaching the material from a place of
deep understanding but they're also
experiencing it as a first-time learner
as at the same time so it's just sort of
embodying the Delight of it but also the
authority over them not Authority but
the the sort of Mastery of the material
and it's really the Delight in it that
the students are linking on to and of
course they need and deserve the best
accurate material so they have to know
what they're talking about but
um yeah just tap into that energy of
learning and loving it and people were
along for the ride or you know I get
accused of being long-winded but you
know things get taken out of context
that leads to Greater misunderstanding
and also I look at listen I come from a
lineage of three debt advisors three all
three
so I don't know when the reaper is
coming for me I'm doing my best to stay
alive a long time but whether or not
it's a bullet or a bus or
cancer or whatever or just old age I
mean I'm trying to get it all out there
as best I can and if it means you have
to hit pause and come back a day or two
later like that seems like a reasonable
compromise to me I'm not gonna go
um go longer than I need to and I'm
trying to shorten them up but uh again
that's just kind of how I show up it's
like Tim Armstrong would say about
writing songs I asked him do you write
how often you write every day
every day was Rick ever stop creating no
is Joe ever stop preparing for comedy
are you ever stopping to think about
world issues and and technology and who
you can talk to I mean it seems to me
you've always got a plan
the inside the the thing I love about
your podcast the most
to be honest these days is the surprise
of like I don't know who the hell is
going to be there it's almost like like
I get a little nervously excited about
when a new episode comes out because I
have no idea no idea and you know I mean
I have some guesses based on what you
told me during the break I mean yeah
you've got someone people where it's
just like whoa Lexus went there awesome
can't wait click you know there you know
I think that's really cool like you're
constantly surprising people so you're
doing it so well like it's such a high
level and I think it's also important
for people to understand that what
you're doing relax
there's no precedent for it sure there
have been interviews before there have
been podcasts before their discussions
before but it's not like how many of
your peers can you look to to find out
how best to do the content like yours
zero there's one peer you
and so you know that should give you
great peace and great excitement because
you're you're a Pioneer you're the
you're literally the tip of the spear I
I don't want to take an unnecessary
tangent but I think this might thread
together two of the things that we've
been talking about which are I think of
pretty key importance one is romantic
relationships and the other is creative
process and work and this again is
something I learned from Rick but that
he and I have gone back and forth on and
that
um I think is worth elaborating on which
is
earlier we're saying you know the best
relationship is going to be one where
you where it brings you peace I think
peace also can be translated to among
other things
lack of distraction so when you're with
your partner can you really focus on
them and the relationship
can you not be distracted by
things that you're upset about from
their past or from your past with them
or their and of course the same is true
for them right they ideally will feel
that way towards you too they can really
focus also
when you're not with them can you focus
on your work can you not be worried
about whether or not they're okay
because you trust that they're an adult
and they can handle things or they will
reach out if they need things
um they're going to communicate their
needs like an adult you know not
creating message just to get attention
and things like that or
or disappearing you know for that matter
so
peace and focus are intimately related
and distraction is the enemy of peace
and focus
so there's something there I believe
um because with people that have a
strong generative drive and want to you
know be productive in their home life in
the sense have a rich family life
um or partner life whatever that is and
in their work life
you know the ability to really drop into
the work and
like okay you might have that sense like
I hope they're okay or you know need to
check my phone or something but just
know like we're good yeah so so peace
and focus I think and present being
present are so key and it's key at every
level of romantic relationship from
um you know certainly presence and focus
you know everything from sex to
listening to
um to you know raising a family to
tending to the house
um and in work it's absolutely critical
so I think that those things are kind of
mirror images of the same thing and
they're both important reflections of
the other and when you start to just you
know when work is not going well then
the relationship the focus on
relationship can suffer and vice versa
so and it's crazy how important that is
oh
how incredibly
um uh wonderful it could be to have a
person in your life that kind of uh
enables that creative Focus yeah and you
supply the the peace and focus for their
Endeavors whatever those might be I mean
that that symmetry there
um because clearly people have different
needs and the need to just really trust
you know like when Lex is working he's
in his generative mode and and and I
know he's good and so then they they
feel sure they've contributed to that
but then also what you're doing is
supporting them in whatever way it
happens to be and I think that sometimes
you'll see that people will pair up
along creative creative or Musical
musical or
um computer scientists but I think again
going back to this Conti episode on on
relationships is that the superficial
labels are less important it seems than
just the desire to create that kind of
home life in a relationship together and
as a consequence the the work mode and
for some people there both people aren't
working and sometimes they are but I
think that's I think that's the good
stuff you know and and I think that's
the big learning in all of it is that
the further along I go with each
birthday I guarantee you're gonna be
like what I want is simpler and simpler
and harder and harder to to uh create
but oh so worth it
the inner and the outer piece it's uh
been over two years I think
uh since Costello passed away
it still tears me up uh I cried about
him today I cried about him today huh
it's it's it's it's proportional to the
love
but yeah I'll cry about it right now if
I think but it wasn't putting him down
it wasn't the act of him dying any of
that actually that was a beautiful
experience
um I didn't expect it to be but it was
in my place when I was living in Topanga
during the pandemic where we launched
the podcast and I did it at home
and he hated the Vats I did at home and
it was he gave out this huge
right at the end and I could just tell
he had been in just not a lot of pain
fortunately but he had just been working
so hard just to move at all and the
craziest thing happened like it was
unbelief I've never had an experience
like this I expected my heart to break
and I felt a broken heart before I felt
it frankly one of my parents split I
felt it when Harry shot himself I heard
I felt it when Barbara died I even felt
it when you know when Ben went
um so as well and so many friends like
way too many friends I mean the end of
2017 my friend Aaron King
John Johnny Farrer John eichelberry
stomach cancer suicide fentanyl it's
like whoa all in a freaking week and I
just remember thinking like what the but
when cust like and it's just
heartbreaking you just carry that and
it's like uh but and that's just a short
list you know and I don't say that for
SOB stories just for a guy that wasn't
in the military or didn't grow up in the
inner city like it's an unusual number
of like deaths like close people
um
when Costello went the craziest thing
happened my heart warmed up it like
heated up and I wasn't on MDMA and I
wasn't I I was just it just the moment
he went he just went
and I was like what the hell is this and
it was just it was like a supernatural
experience to me I just never had that
I'd put my grandfather on the ground I
was a pallbearer at the funeral I've
like done that more times than I'd like
to
to have ever done it and
you just heat it up with costume I
thought what the is this and it was
almost like and you can make up these we
make up these stories about what it is
but it was almost like he was like all
right I have to be careful because I
will cry here
um and I don't want to
um
it was almost like he was like
all that effort because I've been
putting so much effort into him it was
like all right you get that back it was
like the giant freaking thank you and it
was it was incredible you know and I'm
not embarrassed to shed a tear or two
about it if I have to like I was like
holy like that's how close I was to
that animal where do you think where do
you think you can find that kind of love
again man I don't know I mean when um
excuse me for for welling up but it was
just I mean it's a freaking dog right I
get it but for me it was
um the first real home I ever had
um but when Costello went
it was like we'd have this home in
Topanga we'd set it up and we're like
and he was just so happy there and I
think it just um
I don't know it was it was like this
weird like Victory slash massive loss
like like we didn't 11 years
freaking did everything everything to
make him as comfortable as possible and
he was super loyal beautiful animal but
also just
funny and fun and and I was like I did
it like like you know I gave as much of
myself to this being as a human I felt I
could without making it you know like
you know detract detracting from the
rest of my life and he Lo and so I don't
know
um when I think about Barbara especially
um I well up and I and it's hard for me
but I mean I talked to her before she
died and that was a brutal conversation
saying goodbye to someone
especially with kids and
um that was hard
um I think that really
um flipped a switch in me where I'm like
I I always knew I wanted kids I say I
want kids I want a lot of kids that flip
to switching me I was like I want kids I
want my own kids you might be able to
find that kind of love yeah I I think
because it was the caretaking it wasn't
about what he gave me all that time and
the more I could take care of him and
see him happy the better I felt it was
crazy and I I'm I don't know so
the miss them every day every day every
day you're uh you got a heart that's so
full of love I can't wait uh for you to
have kids uh for you to be a father yeah
I can't wait I'm ready for it when uh
you know uh when when God decides I'm
ready I'll I'll have them
and then I will still beat you to it as
I told you many times before I think you
should
um absolutely have kids I mean look at
the people in our life because because
we're kind of the if you in case you
haven't realized it already like we're
the the younger of the podcasters but
you know like Joe and Peter and
Segura and you know I'm you know and the
rest right there they're the like the
they're like the tribal Elders right and
um and we're you know we're not the the
youngest in the crew but we're we're if
you look at all those guys
they all have kids
they all adore their kids and their kids
bring tremendous meaning to their life
like we we'd be morons if
you know if you didn't go off and start
a family I didn't start off yeah to
start a family
um and yeah I think that's that's the
goal I mean I think the kids of the
goals that's one of them the kids not
only make them uh their life more joyful
and brings love to their life it's also
makes them more productive makes them
better people all that it's like oh it's
it's it's uh it's kind of obvious yeah I
think that's what Costello wanted I
think I have this story in my head that
he was just like okay like take this I
can yeah and don't forget
Lord knows don't this up Andrew I
love you brother this is incredible love
you too thank you I appreciate you uh
let's as we will talk often on each
other's podcast for many years to come
yes many many years to come thank you
thanks for for having me on here and um
there are no words for how much I
appreciate your example and your
friendship so love you brother love you
too
thanks for listening to this
conversation with Andrew huberman to
support this podcast please check out
our sponsors in the description and now
let me leave you with some words from
Albert Camus in the midst of winter I
found that was within me an invincible
summer and that makes me happy for it
says that no matter how hard the world
pushes against me within me there's
something stronger something better
pushing right back
thank you for listening and hope to see
you next time